<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
<?dbsuse-bugtracker url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi"
   product="SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1"
   component="Documentation"
   assignee="sknorr@suse.com" ?>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname><phrase os="sles">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</phrase></productname>
  <productnumber>12 SP1</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
<!-- msvec and marketing, 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- new initial para -->
   <para>
    This document provides guidance and an overview to high level general
    features and updates for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1. Besides
    architecture or product-specific information, it also describes the
    capabilities and limitations of SLES 12 SP1.
   </para>

   <para>
    If you are skipping one or more service packs, check the release notes
    of the skipped service packs as well. Release notes usually only list
    changes that happened between two subsequent releases. If you are only
    reading the release notes of the current release, you could miss
    important changes.
   </para>

   <para>
    General documentation can be found at:
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/"/>.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</title>
  <remark> SLE definition: general information </remark>
<!-- Marketing, Kerry Kim, 2009-02-09 -->
<!-- Changed by MgE, 2012-02-02 -->
<!-- Feedback by Robert, 2012-02-27 -->
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is a highly reliable, scalable, and secure
   server operating system, built to power mission-critical workloads in
   both physical and virtual environments. It is an affordable,
   interoperable, and manageable open source foundation. With it,
   enterprises can cost-effectively deliver core business services, enable
   secure networks, and simplify the management of their heterogeneous IT
   infrastructure, maximizing efficiency and value.
  </para>
  <para>
   The only enterprise Linux recommended by Microsoft and SAP, SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server is optimized to deliver high-performance
   mission-critical services, as well as edge of network, and web
   infrastructure workloads.
  </para>
  <para>
   Designed for interoperability, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server integrates
   into classical Unix as well as Windows environments, supports open
   standard interfaces for systems management, and has been certified for
   IPv6 compatibility.
  </para>
  <para>
   This modular, general purpose operating system runs on three processor
   architectures and is available with optional extensions that provide
   advanced capabilities for tasks such as real time computing and high
   availability clustering.
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is optimized to run as a high performing
   guest on leading hypervisors and supports an unlimited number of virtual
   machines per physical system with a single subscription, making it the
   perfect guest operating system for virtual computing.
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is backed by award-winning support from
   SUSE, an established technology leader with a proven history of
   delivering enterprise-quality support services.
  </para>
<!-- bnc#821338 -->
<!-- bnc#828478 -->
<!-- bnc#882262 -->
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 has a 13 years life cycle, with 10 years
   of General Support and 3 years of Extended Support. The current version
   (SP1) will be fully maintained and supported until 6 months after the
   release of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP2. If you need additional
   time to design, validate and test your upgrade plans, Long Term Service
   Pack Support can extend the support you get an additional 12 to 36 months
   in twelve month increments, giving you a total of 3 to 5 years of support
   on any given service pack.
  </para>
  <para>
   For more information, check our Support Policy page
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/policy.html"/> or the Long Term
   Service Pack Support Page
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/programs/long-term-service-pack-support.html"/>.
  </para>
  <section id="Intro.New" remap="Intro:New">
   <title>What's New?</title>
   <remark> Marketing POV. </remark>
   <remark> ** Update information : link to severity ratings documentation ** Installation : change,
    new kernel, compatibility ** features : features description (not technical) ** System update :
    link to the documentation (not just the tittle) ** Update related notes : specific change to
    focus on.
    BNC#898123
   </remark>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 introduces a number of innovative
    changes. Here are some of the highlights:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Robustness on administrative errors and improved management
      capabilities with full system rollback based on Btrfs as the default
      file system for the operating system partition and SUSE's Snapper
      technology.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      An overhaul of the installer introduces a new workflow that allows you
      to register your system and receive all available maintenance updates
      as part of the installation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Server Modules offer a choice of supplemental
      packages, ranging from tools for Web Development and Scripting,
      through a Cloud Management module, all the way to a sneak preview of
      SUSE's upcoming management tooling called Advanced Systems Management.
      Modules are part of your SUSE Linux Enterprise Server subscription,
      are technically delivered as online repositories, and differ from the
      base of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server only by their life cycle.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      New core technologies like systemd (replacing the time honored System
      V based init process) and wicked (introducing a modern, dynamic
      network configuration infrastructure).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The open source database system MariaDB is fully supported now.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Support for the open-vm-tools together with VMware for better
      integration into VMware based hypervisor environments.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Linux Containers are integrated into the virtualization management
      infrastructure (libvirt). Docker is provided as a fully supported
      technology. For more details, see
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/promo/sle/docker/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Support for the 64-bit Little-Endian variant of IBM's POWER
      architecture, in addition to continued support for the Intel 64 /
      AMD64 and IBM System z architectures.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GNOME 3.10 (or just GNOME 3), giving users a modern desktop
      environment with a choice of several different look and feel options,
      including a special SUSE Linux Enterprise Classic mode for easier
      migration from earlier SUSE Linux Enterprise desktop environments
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For users wishing to use the full range of productivity applications
      of a Desktop with their SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, we are now
      offering the SUSE Linux Enterprise Workstation Extension (needs a SUSE
      Linux Enterprise Desktop subscription).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Integration with the new SUSE Customer Center, SUSE's central web
      portal to manage Subscriptions, Entitlements, and provide access to
      Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!-- FATE#312947 -->
   <remark> This is Read Me First information. </remark>
   <para>
    If you are upgrading from a previous SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
    release, you should review at least the following sections:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="Intro.Support"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="InstUpgrade.Upgrade"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="TechInfo"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319415" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319415" -->
    <title>SMT: Supported Products</title>
    <para>
     SMT (Subscription Management Tool) now supports the SLE 10, 11, and 12
     product families.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Documentation">
   <title>Documentation and Other Information</title>
   <para/>
   <section>
    <title>Available on the Product Media</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Read the READMEs on the media.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Get the detailed change log information about a particular package
       from the RPM (where <filename>&lt;FILENAME&gt;.rpm</filename> is the
       name of the RPM):
      </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp &lt;FILENAME&gt;.rpm</screen>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
       media for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated
       packages.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of
       the media of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1. This directory
       includes PDF versions of the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1
       Installation Quick Start and Deployment Guides. Documentation (if
       installed) is available below the
       <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> directory of an installed
       system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
<!-- msvec and marketing, 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location -->
<!-- moved here to the beginning, because 'mustread'now comes
       later... -->
      <para>
<!-- fixme: see bnc#733012 -->
       These Release Notes are identical across all architectures, and the
       most recent version is always available online at
       <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>. Some entries are
       listed twice, if they are important and belong to more than one
       section.
<!-- <ulink -->
<!-- url="http://www.novell.com/linux/releasenotes/x86_64/SUSE-SLES/11-SP2/"/>, -->
<!-- <ulink -->
<!-- url="http://www.novell.com/linux/releasenotes/s390x/SUSE-SLES/11-SP2/"/>, -->
<!-- etc. -->
<!--
         The URL-template ist
         <filename>http://www.novell.com/linux/releasenotes/&lt;ARCH&gt;/&lt;PRODUCT&gt;/&lt;Version&gt;/</filename>.
     -->
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Externally Provided Documentation</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/"/> contains
       additional or updated documentation for SUSE Linux Enterprise
       Server 12 SP1.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find a collection of White Papers in the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
       Resource Library at
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/server/resource-library/?ref=b#WhitePapers"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Sourcecode">
   <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
<!-- msvec and legal (ciaran), 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location as the first section -->
   <para>
    This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
    General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the
    source code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material. The source
    code is available for download at
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>.
    Also, for up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
    request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Requests should be
    sent by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/> or
    as otherwise instructed at
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. SUSE
    may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</title>
   <para>
    To receive support, customers need an appropriate subscription with
    SUSE; for more information, see
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/server/services-and-support/"/>.
   </para>
   <section id="Intro.Support.General" remap="Intro:Support:General">
    <title>General Support Statement</title>
    <para>
     The following definitions apply:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
<!-- Now using http://support.novell.com/products/server/supported_packages/
  -->
     <varlistentry>
<!--
   <term>L1 — Installation Help and Problem Determination</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     With this level of technical support customers obtain compatibility
     information, installation assistance, and basic troubleshooting to
     apply best practises as documented in manuals, knowledgebase and
     other product specific documentation.  This level of support has no
     provisions to address product defects.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   -->
      <term>L1</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Problem determination, which means technical support designed to
        provide compatibility information, usage support, on-going
        maintenance, information gathering and basic troubleshooting using
        available documentation.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
<!--
   <term>L2 — Reproduction and Isolation of a Given Problem</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In addition to all the benefits of L1 support customers obtain
     assistance in isolating potential problem areas.  It includes in
     depth analysis of data and testing to prepare for L3 or to suggest
     workarounds, and it may even include suggestions for conceptual
     changes.  This level of support has provisions to resolve product
     defects.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   -->
      <term>L2</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Problem isolation, which means technical support designed to analyze
        data, duplicate customer problems, isolate problem area and provide
        resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1 or alternatively
        prepare for Level 3.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
<!--
   <term>L3 — Code Debugging and Problem Resolution</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In addition to all the benefits of L2 support customers obtain
     resolution of product defects.  This may also involve code changes
     and patch provisioning done by software engineers.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   -->
      <term>L3</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Problem resolution, which means technical support designed to
        resolve problems by engaging engineering to resolve product defects
        which have been identified by Level 2 Support.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     For contracted customers and partners, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
     SP1 and its Modules are delivered with L3 support for all packages,
     except the following:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Technology Previews
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       sound, graphics, fonts and artwork
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       packages that require an additional customer contract
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       packages provided as part of the Software Development Kit (SDK)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     SUSE will only support the usage of original (e.g., unchanged or
     un-recompiled) packages.
    </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-321136" remap="Intro:Support:General">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321136" -->
     <title>Docker Orchestration Is Not Supported</title>
     <para>
      Starting with Docker 1.12, orchestration (swarm) is now a part of the
      Docker engine, as available from the SLES Containers module. This
      feature is not supported.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-320285" remap="Intro:Support:General">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320285" -->
     <title>Wayland Libraries Are Not Supported on SLES 12 GA and SP1</title>
     <para>
      Wayland is not supported on SLES 12 GA and SLES 12 SP1. While some
      Wayland libraries are available, they should not be installed and are
      not supported by SUSE.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319081" remap="Intro:Support:General">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319081" -->
     <title>Support for Korn Shell (ksh) Extended Until End of March 2022</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis> Support for the legacy package
      </emphasis><literal>ksh</literal><emphasis> in SLE was originally
      slated to end in 2017. However, many customers still depend on
      </emphasis><literal>ksh</literal><emphasis>. </emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      Support for <literal>ksh</literal> has been extended until the end of
      March 2022.
     </para>
     <para>
      Beyond that time, you can use the <literal>mksh</literal>
      implementation of Korn Shell (package <literal>mksh</literal>).
      However, as <literal>mksh</literal> is based on
      <literal>pdksh</literal>, there are certain functional differences.
      For example, its handling of pipelines is similar to Bash.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-314339" remap="Intro:Support:General">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Base System"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/314339" -->
     <title>L3 support for OpenJDK</title>
     <para>
      OpenJDK is now L3-supported.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="Intro.Support.Techpreviews" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews">
    <title>Technology Previews</title>
    <remark> ** clear statement of TP (no support) ** Title of the TP ** full description of the TP
     ** link to official documentation (external) ** link to the SUSE's documentation </remark>
<!-- bnc#662712 -->
    <para>
     Technology previews are packages, stacks, or features delivered by
     SUSE. These features are not supported. They may be functionally
     incomplete, unstable or in other ways not suitable for production use.
     They are mainly included for customer convenience and give customers a
     chance to test new technologies within an enterprise environment.
    </para>
    <para>
     Whether a technical preview will be moved to a fully supported package
     later, depends on customer and market feedback. A technical preview
     does not automatically result in support at a later point in time.
     Technical previews could be dropped at any time and SUSE is not
     committed to provide a technical preview later in the product cycle.
    </para>
    <para>
     Give your SUSE representative feedback, including your experience and
     use case.
<!--
  Alternatively, use the Novell Requirements Portal
  at <ulink url="http://www.novell.com/rms"/>.
  -->
    </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319392" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Virtualization / Containers"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319392" -->
     <title>Virtual Machine Sandbox</title>
     <para>
      <literal>virt-sandbox</literal> provides a way for the administrator
      to run a command under a confined virtual machine using qemu/kvm or
      LXC libvirt virtualization drivers. The default sandbox domain only
      allows applications the ability to read and write stdin, stdout, and
      file descriptors handed to it. It is not allowed to open any other
      files. Enable SELinux on your system to get it usable. For more
      information, see
      <ulink url="http://sandbox.libvirt.org/quickstart/#System_service_sandboxes">http://sandbox.libvirt.org/</ulink>.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-316354" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Virtualization / KVM"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316354" -->
     <title>KVM Nested Virtualization</title>
     <para>
      KVM Nested Virtualization is available in SLE 12 as a technology
      preview. For more information about nested virtualization, see
      <ulink url="https://github.com/torvalds/linux/blob/master/Documentation/virtual/kvm/nested-vmx.txt">nested-vmx.txt</ulink>.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-314409" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Storage Drivers,Storage and Partitioning"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/314409" -->
     <title>Support LibStorageMgmt to Manage Storage Hardware</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>LibStorageMgmt was introduced in 2012, and offers an open
      infrastructure for modules, which even can include (closed source)
      vendor specific tools.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      Provide LibStorageMgmt, a library for storage management, to integrate
      better with storage vendors. It is an infrastructure to facilitate
      management automation, ease of use and take advantage of storage
      vendor supported features, which improve storage performance and space
      utilization.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
    <section id="Intro.Support.Techpreviews.SystemZ" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews:SystemZ">
     <title>Technology Previews: System z (s390x)</title>
     <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
     <section role="notoc" id="fate-318070" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews:SystemZ">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318070" -->
      <title>Technology Preview: Extended CPU Performance Metrics in HYPFS for Linux z/VM Guests</title>
      <para>
       The HYPFS is extended to provide the "diag 0C data" also for Linux
       z/VM guests that distinguish "management time" spent as part of CPU
       load.
      </para>
     </section>
     <section role="notoc" id="fate-318029" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews:SystemZ">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="RAS"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318029" -->
      <title>Technology Preview: LPAR Watchdog for IBM z Systems</title>
      <para>
       SLES 12 SP1 contains an enhanced watchdog driver for IBM z Systems.
       The driver can be used for Linux running on logical partitions
       (LPARs) and Linux running as a guest under z/VM. The update provides
       automatic reboot and automatic dump capabilities if a Linux system
       becomes unresponsive.
      </para>
     </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
    </section>
   </section>
<!-- see fate#316990 -->
   <section id="Intro.Support.External" remap="Intro:Support:External">
    <title>Software Requiring Specific Contracts</title>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316990" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Software Requiring Specific Contracts</title -->
    <para>
     The following packages require additional support contracts to be
     obtained by the customer in order to receive full support:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       PostgreSQL Database
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Derived_Products">
   <title>Derived and Related Products</title>
   <remark> Marketing POV. </remark>
<!--
   <section id='SDK'>
    <title>Software Development Kit</title>
    now via fate#317704
    -->
   <remark> ** clear statement of SDK (no support) ** list of SDK available ** version comparison
    table from previous SP/Product ** Version of SDK </remark>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/desktop/">SUSE Linux
      Enterprise Desktop</ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-cloud/">Cloud</ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-manager/">SUSE
      Manager</ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/highavailability/">SUSE
      Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension</ulink> — With the
      <emphasis>SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability
      Extension 12</emphasis>, SUSE offers the most modern open source High
      Availability Stack for Mission Critical environments.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Certification">
   <title>Security, Standards, and Certification</title>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1 has been submitted to the
    certification bodies for:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/">Common Criteria
      Certification</ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      FIPS 140-2 validation, see:
      <ulink url="http://csrc.nist.gov/groups/STM/cmvp/documents/140-1/140InProcess.pdf"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For more information about certification, refer to
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/certificates.html"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- In SLED, we want this in derived resp. 'Related Products'
 <section id="Third_Party">
  <title>Third Party</title>
  <remark>
   descripton and information of technology
  </remark>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     VMDP
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     VMware
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Third party software
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
-->
<!-- ============================================================== -->
<!-- =============== Technical Part Starts Here =================== -->
<!-- ============================================================== -->
 <section id="InstUpgrade" remap="InstUpgrade">
  <title>Installation and Upgrade</title>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server can be deployed in several ways:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Physical machine
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Virtual host
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Virtual machine
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     System containers
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Application containers
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-317900" remap="InstUpgrade">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317900" -->
   <title>Creation of Snapshots During the Upgrade Process</title>
   <para>
    The upgrade process is safer than ever. When upgrading using the DVD, if
    snapshots are enabled and the root file system is Btrfs, two new
    snapshots will be created:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      One before any change is made to the system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Another one just after the upgrade process is finished.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    If something goes wrong, the system can be easily restored to a known
    state using Snapper.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  <section id="InstUpgrade.Installation" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
   <title>Installation</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320203" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320203" -->
    <title>AutoYaST Uses Wrong crashkernel Value During First Boot</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> If you install using AutoYaST with a profile that, in the
     </emphasis><literal>&lt;kdump&gt;</literal><emphasis> section, has
     </emphasis><literal>&lt;add_crash_kernel&gt;</literal><emphasis> set to
     </emphasis><literal>true</literal><emphasis> but that does not include
     </emphasis><literal>&lt;crash_kernel&gt;</literal><emphasis>, an
     incorrect kernel parameter will be set initially. During the first
     boot, that is, the second AutoYaST stage, the following will be set:
     </emphasis>
    </para>
<screen>crashkernel=""</screen>
    <para>
     <emphasis>AutoYaST will correct this automatically. However, the
     corrected value will only go into effect after a reboot.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     To solve this, reboot the system. Afterwards, Kdump will be configured
     properly.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320019" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320019" -->
    <title>When Installing Extensions via DVD During OS Installation, There Is No Way to Specify the Registration Code</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>During the installation of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
     SP1, you can choose to install extensions from DVD. When doing so, you
     will not be asked to register the extension by entering a registration
     code and will therefore also miss out on updates.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Consider installing extensions from the registration server instead.
     Alternatively, register the extension after the installation by
     running:
    </para>
<screen>SUSEConnect -p &lt;PRODUCT_NAME&gt;/&lt;VERSION&gt;/&lt;ARCHITECTURE&gt; -r &lt;REGISTRATION_CODE&gt;</screen>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319930" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319930" -->
    <title>Creating an AutoYaST XML File</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> In the YaST installer, on the page </emphasis>Installation
     Settings<emphasis>, the headline </emphasis>Clone System
     Configuration<emphasis> and the button </emphasis>Export
     Configuration<emphasis> allow creating an AutoYaST XML file. However,
     generating files using these options will result in an invalid package
     selection and network configuration. This means that when the file is
     used for an installation, that installation could fail. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     To create valid AutoYaST XML files, use an installed system. Ensure
     that the latest YaST updates have been installed and run:
    </para>
<screen>yast clone_system</screen>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319644" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319644" -->
    <title>Building a Silver Image for Use in Private Clouds</title>
    <para>
     When deploying a SLES to a private cloud, or any virtualization
     infrastructure, it is a common practice to build <literal>silver
     images</literal> with requisite software pre-installed, pre-configured
     for the intended environment.
    </para>
    <para>
     When such a silver image gets cloned and deployed to a cloud platform,
     it will receive network MAC addresses different from the instance it
     was originally installed on. Therefore, clean up any mapping associated
     with persistent network device names:
    </para>
<screen>rm -f /etc/udev/rules.d/70-persistent-net.rules</screen>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319135" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319135" -->
    <title>SMT: Upgrading Database Schema and Engine</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>SMT 12 comes with a new database schema and is standardized
     on the InnoDB database back-end.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis> In order to upgrade SMT 11 SPx to SMT 12, it is necessary
     that SMT 11 is configured against SCC (SUSE Customer Center)
     </emphasis>before<emphasis> initializing the upgrade of SLES and SMT to
     version 12 SP1 or newer. If the host is upgraded to SLES 12 SP1 or
     newer without switching to SCC first, the installed SMT instance will
     no longer work. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Only SMT 11 SP3 can be configured against SCC. Older versions
     need to be upgraded to version 11 SP3 first.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Whether the schema or database engine must be upgraded is checked
     during package upgrade and displayed as an update notification. Back up
     your database before doing the database upgrade. Both the schema and
     database engine upgrade are done by the utility
     <literal>/usr/bin/smt-schema-upgrade</literal> (can be called directly
     or via <literal>systemctl start smt-schema-upgrade</literal>) or are
     done automatically after <literal>smt.target restart</literal>
     (computer reboot or via <literal>systemctl restart smt.target</literal>). However, manual database tuning is required for optimal performance.
     For details, see
     <ulink url="https://mariadb.com/kb/en/mariadb/converting-tables-from-myisam-to-innodb/#non-index-issues">https://mariadb.com/kb/en/mariadb/converting-tables-from-myisam-to-innodb/#non-index-issues</ulink>
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319132" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319132" -->
    <title>SMT Supports SCC Exclusively</title>
    <para>
     Support for NCC (Novell Customer Center) was removed from SMT. SMT can
     still serve SLE 11 clients, but must be configured to receive updates
     from SCC.
    </para>
    <para>
     Before migrating from SMT 11 SP3, SMT must be reconfigured against SCC.
     Migration from older versions of SMT is not possible.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319117" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319117" -->
    <title>Automatic Configuration of Snapper for LVM with AutoYaST</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>In SLE 12, AutoYaST configures Snapper if the root file
     system uses Btrfs. But only if LVM is not used for the root file
     system.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In SLES 12 SP1, AutoYaST always configures Snapper if the root file
     system uses Btrfs. If Snapper is not wanted, disable this feature in
     the AutoYaST profile.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318488" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318488" -->
    <title>Using an HTTP Proxy for Registration During the Installation</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>In networks that enforce the usage of a proxy server to
     access remote Web sites, registration was not possible during
     installation. This resulted in an initial installation without updated
     packages. Updates had to be installed in a separate step after system
     installation had been finished.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Before the installation begins, a proxy server can be configured in the
     boot loader by pressing F4. This enables both product registration and
     online updates during the installation workflow.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318392" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318392" -->
    <title>Installing into a Snapper-Controlled Btrfs Subvolume</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Prior to SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 SP1, after the first
     rollback of the system the original root volume was no longer reachable
     and would never be removed automatically. This resulted in a disk space
     leak.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with SP1, YaST installs the system into a subvolume controlled
     by Snapper.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317216" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317216" -->
    <title>Floppy Support Removed from yast2-bootloader</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Probing floppy devices can slow down the boot process on some
     machines that have a timeout even if there is no floppy
     device.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     yast2-bootloader no longer tries to detect nor supports floppy devices.
    </para>
    <para>
     If it is needed to boot from a floppy disk, GRUB 2 can be configured
     manually.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317085" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317085" -->
    <title>CJK Languages Support in Text-mode Installation</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>CJK languages (Chinese, Japanese, and Korean) do not work
     properly during text-mode installation if the framebuffer is not used
     (Text Mode selected in boot loader).</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     There are three ways to resolve this issue:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use English or some other non-CJK language for installation then
       switch to the CJK language later on a running system using
       YaST+System+Language.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use your CJK language during installation, but do not choose Text
       Mode in the boot loader using F3 Video Mode. Select one of the other
       VGA modes instead. Select the CJK language of your choice using F2
       Language, add <literal>textmode=1</literal> to the boot loader
       command-line and start the installation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use graphical installation (or install remotely via SSH or VNC).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InstUpgrade.Upgrade" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
   <title>Upgrade-Related Notes</title>
   <para>
    This section includes upgrade-related information for this release.
   </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319638" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319638" -->
    <title>Automatic Removal of Add-on Products Must Be Manually Confirmed</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> When updating SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 to the Service
     Pack 1 release, any add-on products that have a hard dependency on the
     SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 GA release will be flagged for automatic
     removal. For example, this includes driver kits provided on
     </emphasis><ulink url="https://drivers.suse.com"><emphasis>https://drivers.suse.com</emphasis></ulink><emphasis>. On the installation settings page, a message will be displayed,
     similar to the following: </emphasis>
    </para>
<screen>Update Options
* Some products are marked for automatic removal.
* Contact the vendor of the removed add-on to provide you with a new
  installation media
* Or select the appropriate online extension or module in the registration step
* Or to continue with product upgrade go to the software selection and mark
  the product (the -release package) for removal.
* Product SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 will be updated to SUSE Linux
  Enterprise Server 12 SP1 RC2
* Error: Product [NAME OF ADD-ON PRODUCT] will be automatically removed.
* Only update installed packages where [NAME OF ADD-ON PRODUCT] will be
  the name of the product to be removed.</screen>
    <para>
     If the add-on product named on the error line should not be removed,
     contact the vendor of the add-on for an update compatible with Service
     Pack 1 or verify that the correct extensions or modules are selected
     for update. In this state, the upgrade cannot continue.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you want to remove the add-on product, manually delete the
     <literal>*-release</literal> packages associated with the add-on
     product.
    </para>
    <para>
     YaST GUI:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click on <emphasis>Packages</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Go to the <emphasis>Search</emphasis> pane.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Search for <literal>release</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find the <literal>*-release</literal> packages flagged with a small
       red <emphasis>X</emphasis> underlined with three dots.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Right click on the packages and select <emphasis>Delete</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       At this point the packages will be flagged with a large red
       <emphasis>X</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <emphasis>Accept</emphasis> and confirm any package changes.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     YaST on the command line:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <emphasis>Packages</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Search for release.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Delete all <literal>*-release packages</literal> flagged with
       <emphasis>a-</emphasis> by selecting them and pressing
       <emphasis>-</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <emphasis>a</emphasis> will be removed and the packages will be
       flagged with <emphasis>-</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <emphasis>Accept</emphasis> and confirm any package changes.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     The error message will be replaced with a warning and the upgrade can
     continue.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319118" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319118" -->
    <title>Updating Registration Status After Rollback</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>When performing a service pack migration, it is necessary to
     change the configuration on the registration server to provide access
     to the new repositories. If the migration process is interrupted or
     reverted (via restoring from a backup or snapshot), the information on
     the registration server is inconsistent with the status of the system.
     This may lead to you being prevented from accessing update repositories
     or to wrong repositories being used on the client.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     When a rollback is done via Snapper, the system will notify the
     registration server to ensure access to the correct repositories is set
     up during the boot process. If the system was restored any other way or
     the communication with the registration server failed for any reason
     (for example, because the server was not accessible due to network
     issues), trigger the rollback on the client manually by calling
     <literal>snapper rollback</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     We suggest always checking that the correct repositories are set up on
     the system, especially after refreshing the service using
     <literal>zypper ref -s</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316756" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316756" -->
    <title>[GMC] Lower Version Numbers in SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 SP1 Than in Version 12</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>When upgrading from SUSE Linux Enterprise Server or Desktop
     12 to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server or Desktop 12 SP1, you may
     experience a version downgrade of specific software packages, including
     the Linux Kernel.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     This is expected behavior. It is important to remember that the version
     number is not sufficient to determine which bug fixes are applied to a
     software package.
    </para>
    <para>
     All SLE 12 SP1 software packages and updates are contained in the SLE
     12 SP1 repositories. No packages from SLE 12 repositories are needed
     for installation or upgrade.
    </para>
    <para>
     In case you do add SLE 12 update repositories, be aware of one
     characteristic of the repository concept: Version numbers in the SLE 12
     update repository can be higher than those in the SLE 12 SP1
     repository. Thus, if you update with the SLE 12 repositories enabled,
     you may receive the SLE 12 version of a package instead of the SLE 12
     SP1 version.
    </para>
    <para>
     Using package versions from a lower product version or SP can result in
     unwanted side effects. If you do not need them, switch off all SLE 12
     repositories.
    </para>
    <para>
     Only keep old repositories if your system depends on a specific older
     version of a package. If you need a package from a lower product
     version or SP though, and thus have SLE 12 repositories enabled, make
     sure that the packages you intended to upgrade have actually been
     upgraded.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316754" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316754" -->
    <title>Online Migration with Debuginfo Packages Not Supported</title>
    <para>
     Online migration from SLE 12 to SLE 12 SP1 is not supported if
     <literal>debuginfo</literal> packages are installed.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-315161" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/315161" -->
    <title>New Method of Online Migration Between Service Packs</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>In the past, you could use YaST Wagon to migrate between
     Service Packs. YaST Wagon is now unsupported.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     You can now use either the <emphasis>YaST Online Migration</emphasis>
     module or <literal>zypper migration</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To learn more about migrating between Service Packs, see the section
     <emphasis>Service Pack Migration</emphasis> in the <emphasis>Deployment
     Guide</emphasis>:
     <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/book_sle_deployment/data/cha_update_spmigration.html">https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/book_sle_deployment/data/cha_update_spmigration.html</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Note that when performing the SP migration, both YaST and Zypper will
     install all recommended packages. Especially in the case of custom
     minimal installations, this may increase the installation size of the
     system significantly.
    </para>
    <para>
     There are two ways to change this behavior:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To change the default behavior of YaST, adjust
       <literal>/etc/zypp/zypp.conf</literal> and set the variable
       <literal>solver.onlyRequires = true</literal>. This changes the
       behavior of all package operations, such as the installation of
       patches or new packages. For YaST, this is the only solution.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To change the default behavior of Zypper, adjust
       <literal>/etc/zypp/zypp.conf</literal> and set the variable
       <literal>solver.onlyRequires = true</literal> and make sure
       <literal>installRecommends</literal> is not set to
       <literal>true</literal>. This changes the behavior of all package
       operations, such as the installation of patches or new packages.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To change the behavior of Zypper for a single invocation, add the
       parameter <literal>--no-recommends</literal> to your command line.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>For More Information</title>
   <para>
    For more information, see <xref linkend="InfraPackArch"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch">
  <title>Infrastructure, Package and Architecture Specific Information</title>
  <remark> This is highly technical * Know issues categorized ** full description of the problem **
   how to reproduce the issue ** link to Bugzilla number ** command line change/configuration change
   ** work around if available
  </remark>
  <remark> Move items from technical.xml to a proper location. </remark>
<!-- Arch Independent -->
<!-- basically empty, including directly
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
              href="known-issues.xml"/>
  -->
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent">
   <title>Architecture Independent Information</title>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Kernel" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
    <title>Kernel</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-312101" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Competitive Environment,Linux Kernel,Partner Request"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/312101" -->
     <title>Opt-in Memory cgroup Isolation</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis> Memory cgroups help to put workloads into separate groups
      where each workload's memory usage can be restricted by a separate
      memory limit (</emphasis><literal>memory.hard_limit_in_bytes</literal><emphasis>).
      Memory pressure in one group is limited only to this group, granted
      the system as a whole is not under memory pressure. This can be used
      for a basic memory isolation of different workloads. Such a
      configuration, however, requires that all the processes are capped in
      a limited memory cgroup and those have to be configured so that the
      system is not put under the global memory pressure. </emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      Starting with SLE 12 SP1 memory cgroup offers a new mechanism allowing
      easier workload opt-in isolation. Memory cgroup can define its so
      called low limit (<literal>memory.low_limit_in_bytes</literal>),
      which works as a protection from memory pressure. Workloads that need
      to be isolated from outside memory management activity should set the
      value to the expected Resident Set Size (RSS) plus some head room. If
      a memory pressure condition triggers on the system and the particular
      group is still under its low limit, its memory is protected from
      reclaim. As a result, workloads outside of the cgroup do not need the
      aforementioned capping.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Kernel_Modules" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel_Modules">
    <title>Kernel Modules</title>
<!-- 2014-03-19, ke: bnc#869159 -->
<!-- 2014-04-29, ke: find the same text in the SLED RN -->
    <para>
     An important requirement for every Enterprise operating system is the
     level of support a customer receives for his environment. Kernel
     modules are the most relevant connector between hardware
     ("controllers") and the operating system.
    </para>
    <para>
<!--  bnc#869159 -->
     For more information about the handling of kernel modules, see the SUSE
     Linux Enterprise Administration Guide.
    </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318829" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel_Modules">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318829" -->
     <title>Memory Compression with zswap</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Usually, when a system's physical memory is exceeded, the
      system moves some memory onto reserved space on a hard drive, called
      "swap" space. This frees physical memory space for additional use.
      However, this process of "swapping" memory onto (and off a hard drive
      is much slower than direct memory access, so it can slow down the
      entire system.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      The <literal>zswap</literal> driver inserts itself between the system
      and the swap hard drive, and instead of writing memory to a hard
      drive, it compresses memory. This speeds up both writing to swap and
      reading from swap, which results in better overall system performance
      while using swap.
     </para>
     <para>
      To enable the <literal>zswap</literal> driver, write
      <literal>1</literal> or <literal>Y</literal> to the file
      <literal>/sys/module/zswap/parameters/enabled</literal>.
     </para>
     <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Storage Back-ends</bridgehead>
     <para>
      There are two back-ends available for storing compressed pages,
      <literal>zbud</literal> (the default), and <literal>zsmalloc</literal>. The two back-ends each have their own advantages and disadvantages:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The effective compression ratio of <literal>zbud</literal> cannot
        exceed 50 percent. That is, it can at most store two uncompressed
        pages in one compressed page. If the workload's compression ratio
        exceeds 50% for all pages, <literal>zbud</literal> will not be able
        to save any memory.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>zsmalloc</literal> can achieve better compression ratios.
        However, it is more complex and its performance is less predictable.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>zsmalloc</literal> does not free pages when the limit set
        in <literal>/sys/module/zswap/parameters/max_pool_percent</literal>
        is reached. This is reflected by the counter
        <literal>/sys/kernel/debug/zswap/reject_reclaim_fail</literal>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
      It is not possible to give a general recommendation on which storage
      back-end should be used, as the decision is highly dependent on
      workload. To change the storage back-end, write either
      <literal>zbud</literal> or <literal>zsmalloc</literal> to the file
      <literal>/sys/module/zswap/parameters/zpool</literal>. Pick the
      back-end before enabling zswap. Changing it later is unsupported.
     </para>
     <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Setting
            zswap
            Memory</bridgehead>
     <para>
      Compressed memory still uses a certain amount of memory, so
      <literal>zswap</literal> has a limit to the amount of memory which
      will be stored compressed, which is controllable through the file
      <literal>/sys/module/zswap/parameters/max_pool_percent</literal>. By
      default, this is set to <literal>20</literal>, which indicates
      <literal>zswap</literal> will use 20 percent of the total system
      physical memory to store compressed memory.
     </para>
     <para>
      The <literal>zswap</literal> memory limit has to be carefully
      configured. Setting the limit too high can lead to premature
      out-of-memory situations that would not exist without
      <literal>zswap</literal>, if the memory is filled by non-swappable
      non-reclaimable pages. This includes mlocked memory and pages locked
      by drivers and other kernel users.
     </para>
     <para>
      For the same reason, performance can also be hurt by
      compression/decompression if the current workload's workset would, for
      example, fit into 90 percent of the available RAM, but 20 percent of
      RAM is already occupied by <literal>zswap</literal>. This means that
      the missing 10 percent of uncompressed RAM would constantly be swapped
      out of/in to the memory area compressed by <literal>zswap</literal>,
      while the rest of the memory compressed by <literal>zswap</literal>
      would hold pages that were swapped out earlier which are currently
      unused. There is no mechanism that would result in gradual writeback
      of those unused pages to let the uncompressed memory grow.
     </para>
     <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Freeing
            zswap
            Memory</bridgehead>
     <para>
      <literal>zswap</literal> will only free its pages in certain
      situations:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The processes using the pages free the pages or exit
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        When the storage back-end <literal>zbud</literal> is in use,
        <literal>zswap</literal> will also free memory when its configured
        memory limit is exceeded. In this case, the oldest
        <literal>zswap</literal> pages are written back to disk-based swap.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Memory Allocation Issues</bridgehead>
     <para>
      In theory, it can happen that <literal>zswap</literal> is not yet
      exceeding its memory limit, but already fails to allocate memory to
      store compressed pages. In that case, it will refuse to compress any
      new pages and they will be swapped to disk immediately. For
      confirmation whether this issue is occurring, check the value of
      <literal>/sys/kernel/debug/zswap/reject_alloc_fail</literal>.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Security" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
    <title>Security</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319300" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319300" -->
     <title>Secure Hash Algorithm 2 in OpenLDAP Password Operations</title>
     <para>
      SHA-2 is a set of new hash functions featuring a higher level of
      security than its predecessor SHA-1. This OpenLDAP update brings the
      possibility to use SHA-2 in LDAP-hashed passwords.
     </para>
     <para>
      Before using the new hash functions, the OpenLDAP configuration has to
      be adjusted to load a new module located at:
     </para>
<screen>/usr/lib/openldap/pw-sha2.la</screen>
     <para>
      Here is an example based on <literal>slapd.conf</literal> style
      configuration:
     </para>
     <para>
      moduleload /usr/lib/openldap/pw-sha2.la
     </para>
     <para>
      If you are using <literal>slapd.conf</literal> style configuration,
      the OpenLDAP server will have to be restarted for the new module to
      become live.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319053" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Security,zypp"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319053" -->
     <title>Zypper Can List Already Installed and Unneeded Patches by CVE Number</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis> The Zypper subcommands </emphasis><literal>zypper
      list-patches</literal><emphasis> and </emphasis><literal>zypper
      patch</literal><emphasis> are aware of the CVE metadata inside the
      update information. However, </emphasis><literal>zypper
      search</literal><emphasis> is not able to search for CVE numbers in
      the patch metadata. </emphasis><literal>zypper
      list-patches</literal><emphasis> only lists patches applicable to your
      system by default. </emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      To find out whether a fix for a specific CVE number is installed or
      necessary for your system, you need to search for the CVE number in
      all patches, including installed and unneeded ones. To do so, for
      example, run:
     </para>
<screen>zypper list-patches -a --cve="CVE-2015-7547"</screen>
     <para>
      <emphasis>(Note: This entry was corrected. Previously, it incorrectly
      stated that</emphasis> <literal>zypper search</literal> <emphasis>has
      the desired functionality.)</emphasis>
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318988" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318988" -->
     <title>Incorrect SSL/TLS Certificate Verification Considered a Defect</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Bugs and vulnerabilities in software packages could be
      discovered relating to verification of SSL/TLS certificates,
      intermediate certificates, certificate chains, or certificate
      revocation lists. These elements protect the security,
      confidentiality, and integrity of the user's systems and
      activities.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      Any incorrect verification of SSL/TLS certificates, intermediate
      certificates, certificate chains or certificate revocation lists, will
      be considered a security issue and will be corrected, at the potential
      detriment of customer backwards compatibility scenarios.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318574" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318574" -->
     <title>Password Protection Behavior for Boot Entries</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>With SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, booting other systems was
      very restricted. A password was needed to even select a different boot
      entry.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      With SP1, the old behavior known from SLE 11 is back. Now again, a
      password is needed only for modifying a boot loader entry. Anyone can
      boot any entry and the default boot entry is automatically used if the
      timeout has passed.
     </para>
     <para>
      There is now a new configuration option in the
      <literal>yast2-bootloader</literal> dialog, where you can enable the
      restricted boot behavior. Once enabled, a password is also needed to
      select a different boot entry.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-317116" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317116" -->
     <title>SELinux Enablement</title>
     <para>
      SELinux capabilities have been added to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
      (in addition to other frameworks, such as AppArmor). While SELinux is
      not enabled by default, customers can run SELinux with SUSE Linux
      Enterprise Server if they choose to.
     </para>
     <para>
      SELinux Enablement includes the following:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The kernel ships with SELinux support.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        We will apply SELinux patches to all “common” userland packages.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The libraries required for SELinux (<literal>libselinux</literal>,
        <literal>libsepol</literal>, <literal>libsemanage</literal>, etc.)
        have been added SUSE Linux Enterprise.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Quality Assurance is performed with SELinux disabled—to make sure
        that SELinux patches do not break the default delivery and the
        majority of packages.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The SELinux-specific tools are shipped as part of the default
        distribution delivery.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        SELinux policies are not provided by SUSE. Supported policies may be
        available from the repositories in the future.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Customers and Partners who have an interest in using SELinux in
        their solutions are encouraged to contact SUSE to evaluate their
        necessary level of support and how support and services for their
        specific SELinux policies will be granted.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
      By enabling SELinux in our code base, we add community code to offer
      customers the option to use SELinux without replacing significant
      parts of the distribution.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Network" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
    <title>Networking</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-320709" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320709" -->
     <title>No Support for Samba as Active Directory-Style Domain Controller</title>
     <para>
      The version of Samba shipped with SLE 12 GA and newer does not include
      support to operate as an Active Directory-style domain controller.
      This functionality is currently disabled, as it lacks integration with
      system-wide MIT Kerberos.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319710" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319710" -->
     <title>Customizing the Name of Network Interfaces</title>
     <para>
      You can customize the name of a network interface in YaST using the
      Network Settings dialog.
     </para>
     <para>
      Customization is only supported with types <literal>eth</literal>,
      <literal>bond</literal>, <literal>bridge</literal>, and
      <literal>vlan</literal>. Other device types cannot be renamed.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318522" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318522" -->
     <title>Intel 10GbE PCI Express Adapters: Setting MAC Address of a VF Interface</title>
     <para>
      When using the ixgbe and ixgbevf drivers (Intel 10GbE PCI Express
      adapters) in the context of SRIOV, it is possible to set the MAC
      address of a VF interface via two methods:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        through the PF: This would typically be done on the virtualization
        host using a command such as <literal>ip link set p4p1 vf 0 mac
        d6:2f:a7:28:78:c2</literal>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        through the VF: This would typically be done on the virtualization
        guest using a command such as <literal>ip link set eth0 address
        d6:2f:a7:28:78:c2</literal>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
      Initially, either methods are permitted. However, after the
      administrator has explicitly configured a MAC address for a VF through
      its PF, the ixgbe driver disallows further changes of the MAC address
      through the VF. For example, if an attempt is made to change the MAC
      address through the VF on a guest after the MAC address for this
      device has been set on the host, the host will log a warning of the
      following form:
     </para>
<screen>[  884.838134] ixgbe 0000:08:00.0: p4p1: VF 0 attempted to override administratively set MAC address
[  884.838138] Reload the VF driver to resume operations</screen>
     <para>
      To avoid this problem, either avoid configuring an address for the VF
      through the PF (on the virtualization host) and let a trusted guest
      set whatever MAC address is desired, or set the desired MAC address
      through the PF such that further changes through the VF are not
      needed.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318496" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318496" -->
     <title>Enabling NFSv2 Support</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>nfs-utils 1.2.9 changed the default so that NFSv2 is not
      served unless explicitly requested.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      If your clients still depend on NFSv2, enable it on the server by
      setting
     </para>
<screen>NFSD_OPTIONS="-V2"
MOUNTD_OPTIONS="-V2"</screen>
     <para>
      in <literal>/etc/sysconfig/nfs</literal>. After restarting the
      service, check whether version 2 is available with the command:
     </para>
<screen>cat /proc/fs/nfsd/versions
==&gt;
+2 +3 +4 +4.1 -4.2</screen>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318116" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318116" -->
     <title>Davfs2 FUSE Based Support Added</title>
     <para>
      Accessing WebDAV enabled server resources is now supported also
      through the FUSE based <literal>davfs2</literal> utility.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-316311" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="NFS Service"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316311" -->
     <title>NFSv4 only configuration</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>NFS traditionally requires a number of different services to
      be running including nfsd, lockd, statd, and rpcbind (previously known
      as portmap). The more network services are running, the greater the
      possible attack surface, so reducing the number of services is
      encouraged when possible.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      NFSv4 is a more focused protocol than previous versions and does not
      need as many services to be running. Disabling NFSv3 (and lower) can
      reduce the attack surface. Setting NFS3_SERVER_SUPPORT=no in
      <literal>/etc/sysconfig/nfs</literal> will disable NFSv3 support and
      ensure that lockd and statd are not started. It does not prevent
      rpcbind from starting though. This is in part because rpcbind is
      needed for other services including NIS (aka yellow-pages) and
      automatically determining that none of these are required is
      problematic.
     </para>
     <para>
      If rpcbind is not needed (so only NFSv4 is used), it can be disabled
      with the command:
     </para>
<screen>systemctl disable rpcbind.socket</screen>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-316305" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Customer Request,Monitoring Services"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316305" -->
     <title>Support for netgroups in snmp</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Host-based security so far needed hosts to be listed
      explicitly. For larger groups of hosts, this gets cumbersome and hard
      to maintain.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      net-snmp now also allows specifying netgroups in host-based access
      restriction patterns by prefixing them with <literal>@</literal>
      (creating, for example <literal>@netgroupname</literal>).
     </para>
     <para>
      With this change, the following can be done much easier:
     </para>
<screen>rocommunity public monitoringnode1
rocommunity public monitoringnode2
rocommunity public monitoringnode3</screen>
     <para>
      If all nodes from above are part of a netgroup called
      <literal>monitoringnodes</literal>, you can now use a single line:
     </para>
<screen>rocommunity public @monitoringnodes</screen>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-316289" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Customer Request,Monitoring Services"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316289" -->
     <title>snmpstatus Allows Suppressing Status Messages of Network Interfaces</title>
     <para>
      <literal>snmpstatus</literal><emphasis> can report some NIC states
      wrongly, causing a flood of snmp messages. </emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      <literal>snmpstatus</literal> now has two new optional flags
      <literal>-Si</literal> and <literal>-Sn</literal> which allow you to
      suppress certain messages. For details, see the man page of
      <literal>snmpstatus</literal>.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
  </section>
<!--
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
              href="known-sysman.xml"/>
  -->
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.SystemsManagement" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
   <title>Systems Management</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-323175" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323175" -->
    <title>The YaST Module for SSH Server Configuration Has Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The YaST module for configuring an SSH server which was
     present in SLE 11, is not a part of SLE 12. It does not have any direct
     successor.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The module <emphasis>SSH Server</emphasis> only supported configuring a
     small subset of all SSH server capabilities. Therefore, the
     functionality of the module can be replaced by using a combination of 2
     YaST modules: The <emphasis>/etc/sysconfig Editor</emphasis> and the
     <emphasis>Services Manager</emphasis>. This also applies to system
     configuration via AutoYaST.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319467" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319467" -->
    <title>Return Codes of Zypper</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> In some conditions, Zypper returned an exit value of
     </emphasis><literal>0</literal><emphasis> even if it was aborted. This
     happened if a user decided to abort because of conflicts or if Zypper
     ran in a non-interactive mode, but was waiting for user input.
     </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In these cases, Zypper will now return a suitable error code.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319136" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319136" -->
    <title>Recommended Packages (Weak Dependencies)</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>In the past, the YaST Qt package manager UI auto-installed
     packages for already installed packages.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The YaST Qt packager UI no longer defaults to installing recommended
     packages for already installed packages. The persistent option
     controlling this feature is moved to a one-time option Extras/Install
     All Matching Recommended Packages (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=902394">https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=902394</ulink>).
    </para>
    <para>
     For newly installed packages, the weak dependencies are still installed
     by default, but now this can be disabled in the UI with the option
     Dependencies/Install Recommended Packages (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=900853">https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=900853</ulink>).
    </para>
    <para>
     The YaST Qt packager UI is also using the configuration file
     <literal>/etc/sysconfig/yast2</literal> as the ncurses package manager
     UI (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=900853">https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=900853</ulink>).
    </para>
    <para>
     We do not recommend disabling the installation of recommended packages
     during installation unless you are trying to install a minimal system.
     If you do so, make sure to review the package selection. The
     functionality associated with patterns expects recommended packages to
     be installed, too. If any of them are missing, some functionality of
     the patterns may not be available.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319108" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319108" -->
    <title>Rollback of Service Packs</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>After a rollback of a Service Pack to the previous version,
     SCC and SMT need to be informed about this to reset the access rules
     for the old product repositories.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>During a Service Pack migration, SCC and SMT change the
     access rules for this machine and switch it from the old Service Pack
     to the new one. If you roll back from a Service Pack, SCC and SMT will
     not grant access to the old repositories again until they are told to
     do so.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     If the rollback is done via Snapper (that is, using Btrfs snapshots),
     services and repositories are adjusted automatically. If this fails, or
     the rollback is done in other ways (for example, using VMware/KVM/LVM
     snapshots, or restoring from a backup), this needs to be done manually
     using:
    </para>
<screen>SUSEConnect --rollback</screen>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319078" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319078" -->
    <title>SUSEConnect Now Autorefreshes the Services</title>
    <para>
     When a new product gets activated with the SUSEConnect command line
     tool, the added service will be configured to autorefresh periodically.
     This is now fully compatible with YaST's behavior.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318760" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318760" -->
    <title>Installing only patches from a certain category with a certain severity</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>For some systems, it may be desired to limit patches that are
     installed to those that are most necessary.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The version of Zypper shipped with SLE 12 SP1 now allows more
     fine-grained control over which patches are installed using the
     <literal>--severity</literal> parameter. For example, to install only
     critical security patches, use:
    </para>
<screen>zypper patch --category security --severity critical</screen>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317066" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Snapshot/Rollback"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317066" -->
    <title>New Option --sync for snapper Delete Command</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Btrfs frees disk space asynchronously after deleting
     snapshots. So if the user deletes Snapper-controlled snapshots, the
     user must either wait or manually call several Btrfs commands to have
     the disk space actually freed.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The delete command of Snapper has a new option
     <literal>--sync</literal> that triggers Btrfs to free the disk space
     and waits until the disk space is actually freed.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317016" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317016" -->
    <title>Boot Menu Entry 'Failsafe' Has Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     The boot menu entry 'Failsafe' has been removed from the list of
     default boot menu entries, as in case of an error, the "right"
     combination of parameters to fix needs to be found anyway.
    </para>
    <para>
     SLE 12 also supports booting from snapshots which are meant to provide
     a fallback in case the system is not booting after a change.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316968" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316968" -->
    <title>Re-Introduce bootcycle Functionality for GRUB 2</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>bootcycle</literal> package from SLE 11 was re-introduced
     in SLE 12 SP1.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316732" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316732" -->
    <title>Read-Only Root File System</title>
    <para>
     It is possible to run SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 on a shared read-only
     root file system. A read-only root setup consists of the read-only root
     file system, a scratch and a state file system. The
     <literal>/etc/rwtab</literal> file defines, which files and directories
     on the read-only root file system are replaced with which files on the
     state and scratch file systems for each system instance.
    </para>
    <para>
     The <literal>readonlyroot</literal> kernel command line option enables
     read-only root mode; the <literal>state=</literal> and
     <literal>scratch=</literal> kernel command line options determine the
     devices, on which the state and scratch file systems are located.
    </para>
    <para>
     In order to set up a system with a read-only root file system, set up a
     scratch file system, set up a file system to use for storing persistent
     per-instance state, adjust <literal>/etc/rwtab</literal> as needed, add
     the appropriate kernel command line options to your boot loader
     configuration, replace <literal>/etc/mtab</literal> with a symlink to
     <literal>/proc/mounts</literal> as described below, and (re)boot the
     system.
    </para>
    <para>
     Replace <literal>/etc/mtab</literal> with the appropriate symbolic
     links:
    </para>
<screen>ln -sf /proc/mounts /etc/mtab</screen>
    <para>
     See the rwtab(5) manual page for more information and
     <ulink url="http://www.redbooks.ibm.com/abstracts/redp4322.html">http://www.redbooks.ibm.com/abstracts/redp4322.html</ulink>
     for limitations on System z.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316647" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316647" -->
    <title>YaST Snapper Module Uses Snapper DBus Interface</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The YaST Snapper module bypassed the snapperd daemon while
     working on Snapper-controlled snapshots. This could lead to
     inconsistent data between YaST Snapper and Snapper.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The YaST Snapper module now uses the DBus interface when working on
     Snapper-controlled snapshots.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316000" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="CIM"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316000" -->
    <title>openlmi-bmc</title>
    <para>
     lmi-bmc is a CIM-XML provider based on openlmi framework. This provider
     publishes information about the service processor via CIM-XML. The
     information currently includes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       IP addresses
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       MAC address
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       VLAN ID
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Firmware Version
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       List of supported protocols
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Interface mode (shared vs dedicated)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-312298" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Systems Management,zypp"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/312298" -->
    <title>Zypp History Now Includes Patch Installation</title>
    <para>
     The Zypp history file now includes information about patch
     installation. The lines in the history are tagged
     <literal>|command|</literal> and show the user, command line and
     optional user data of the process that triggered the commit.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
<!-- include directly
       <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="known-performance.xml"/>
  -->
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Performance" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
   <title>Performance Related Information</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319480" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319480" -->
    <title>The sapconf Package: Dependency Changes and New Features</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>sapconf is a software package for automated system tuning,
     dedicated to SUSE Enterprise Linux users who wish to run SAP software
     products. The new release of sapconf comes with important dependency
     changes, and brings new features.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>In previous releases, sapconf automatically tuned a system
     for SAP Netweaver products only. It provided a system service
     (sapconf.service) and an executable (/usr/sbin/sapconf). The executable
     file mimics a SysV-style init script and executes an action (start,
     restart, try-restart, reload, status, stop) based on command line
     parameter input.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In this release, the implementation of sapconf is revamped to offer
     more features and tuning profiles for the system tuning daemon
     (tuned.service), while keeping compatibility with the previous
     releases.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you have been using a previous release of sapconf and plan to
     upgrade to SLES 12 SP1, please check that <literal>tuned</literal>
     package is installed after running the distribution upgrade (run as
     root: <literal>zypper install tuned</literal>), because in certain
     cases a distribution upgrade may ignore the dependency on
     <literal>tuned</literal> package and thus resulting in a
     non-functioning sapconf; if the package <literal>tuned</literal> is not
     installed, sapconf will prompt you to install the missing package when
     it runs.
    </para>
    <para>
     As with the previous releases, invoking sapconf with action
     <literal>start</literal> will activate SAP Netweaver tuning profile
     only if an SAP-product tuning profile (sap-hana, sap-netweaver) is not
     active at the time; if an SAP-product tuning profile is already active
     (such as sap-hana or sap-netweaver), sapconf will simply make sure that
     tuning is activated, without forcibly switching to sap-netweaver tuning
     profile.
    </para>
    <para>
     With this release, sapconf comes with two more actions: "hana" and "b1"
     (BusinessOne). Invoking sapconf (for example "sapconf hana") with
     either action name will result in SAP HANA tuning profile being
     activated. SAP HANA and BusinessOne use an identical method for system
     tuning, thus there exists only one SAP HANA tuning profile for both
     cases.
    </para>
    <para>
     System service <literal>sapconf.service</literal> continues to stay and
     it makes sure that system tuning is automatically applied upon reboot.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information, see the following new or updated manual pages:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       sapconf (8)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       tuned-adm (8)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       tuned-profiles-sap-hana (7)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       tuned-profiles-sap-netweaver (7)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319091" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319091" -->
    <title>Using the "noop" I/O Scheduler for Multipathing and Virtualization Guests</title>
    <para>
     For advanced storage configurations like 4-way multipath to an array,
     we will end up with an environment where the host OS is scheduling I/O
     and the storage array is scheduling I/O. It is a common occurrence that
     those schedulers end up competing with each other and ultimately
     degrade performance. Because the storage array has the best view of
     what the storage is doing at any given time, enabling the
     <literal>noop</literal> scheduler on the host is telling the OS to just
     get out of the way and let the array handle all of the scheduling.
    </para>
    <para>
     Following the same rationale, also for block devices within
     virtualization guests the <literal>noop</literal> I/O scheduler should
     be used.
    </para>
    <para>
     To change the I/O scheduler for a specific block device, use:
    </para>
<screen>echo [scheduler name] &gt; /sys/block/[device]/queue/scheduler</screen>
    <para>
     For more information, see the <emphasis>SUSE Linux Enterprise System
     Analysis and Tuning Guide</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-315593" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="NFS Service,Performance"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/315593" -->
    <title>NFS Tuning</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>On systems with a high NFS load, connections may
     block.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     To work around such performance regressions with NFSv4, you could open
     more than one TCP connection to the same physical host. This could be
     accomplished with the following mount options:
    </para>
    <para>
     To request that the transport is not shared use
    </para>
<screen>mount -o sharetransport=N server:/path /mountpoint</screen>
    <para>
     Where <literal>N</literal> is unique. If <literal>N</literal> is
     different for two mounts, they will not share the transport. If
     <literal>N</literal> is the same, they might (if they are for the same
     server, etc).
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
<!-- <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="known-storage.xml"/> -->
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Storage" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
   <title>Storage</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320870" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320870" -->
    <title>Root File System Conversion to Btrfs Not Supported</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>If it is not the root file system and if the file system has
     at least 20 % free space available, in-place conversion of an existing
     Ext2/Ext3/Ext4 or ReiserFS file system is supported for data mount
     points.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     SUSE does not recommend or support in-place conversion of OS root file
     systems. In-place conversion to Btrfs of root file systems requires
     manual subvolume configuration and additional configuration changes
     that are not automatically applied for all use cases.
    </para>
    <para>
     To ensure data integrity and the highest level of customer
     satisfaction, when upgrading, maintain existing root file systems.
     Alternatively, reinstall the entire operating system.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319317" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319317" -->
    <title>Safer Btrfs Balance Operation</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>First-time users of Btrfs often run the following command
     without any options:</emphasis>
    </para>
<screen>btrfs balance start</screen>
    <para>
     <emphasis>This results in a long I/O-intensive operation that has a
     noticeable impact on system performance.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The <literal>btrfs balance</literal> command requires additional
     options to perform a full file system re-balance. For more information,
     see the man page btrfs-balance(8).
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319010" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319010" -->
    <title>Loopback Mounting of Images with 4k blocksize</title>
    <para>
     It is now possible to loopback mount images with 4k blocksize.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318918" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318918" -->
    <title>Ceph RADOS Block Device (RBD) Kernel Module</title>
    <para>
     The Ceph RADOS Block Device (RBD) kernel module has been updated to
     include the following features:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Support for block discard requests, allowing for significantly
       improved space utilization. RBD can be notified of unused file system
       blocks via the fstrim command or otherwise. RBD is now capable of
       forwarding these requests to the underlying OSDs, to ensure that
       unused space is freed up within the Ceph RADOS pool.This feature is
       available for immediate use with existing RBD images and pools.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Prefix OSD writes with allocation hints in an effort to reduce
       fragmentation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enable message signatures by default for improved message integrity.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Support for erasure coded pools. Images residing on erasure coded
       RADOS pools can now be mapped locally with RBD.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318842" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318842" -->
    <title>Setting up kdump on Systems with Many Devices</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Although required crash kernel reservation size does not
     depend on total installed RAM (contrary to popular belief), it does
     depend on the number of attached devices. A system connected to
     multiple SANs with hundreds of LUNs requires more RAM than a system
     with a single internal SATA disk.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     With SLE 12 SP1, it is possible to configure very large crash kernel
     reservations. The amount can be configured during installation or at
     any later time using YaST Kdump module. See <emphasis>System
     Analysis</emphasis> and <emphasis>Tuning Guide</emphasis> for more
     information on choosing a suitable value.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318805" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318805" -->
    <title>Creating New Subvolumes Underneath the / Hierarchy</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> Creating a new subvolume underneath the
     </emphasis><literal>/</literal><emphasis> hierarchy after system
     installation and after the first snapshot to the
     </emphasis><literal>/</literal><emphasis> filesystem is supported. If
     the new subvolume is permanently mounted via
     </emphasis><literal>/etc/fstab</literal><emphasis> (that is, in a way
     that the new subvolume is also available in future snapshots), the
     snapshot the subvolume has been created at cannot be deleted anymore,
     though. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Example:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis> The root file system is mounted from
       </emphasis><literal>/@/.snapshots/212/snapshot</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis> A new subvolume is created as
       </emphasis><literal>/mynewsubvol</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis> This technically translates to
       </emphasis><literal>/@/.snapshots/212/snapshot/mynewsubvol</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis> The respective
       </emphasis><literal>/etc/fstab</literal><emphasis> entry looks like
       this: </emphasis><literal>/dev/sda /mynewsubvol btrfs
       subvol=/@/.snapshots/212/snapshot/mynewsubvol 0 0</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis>Removing Snapshot 212 will fail</emphasis>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     <emphasis> Technical Reason: Subvolumes in Btrfs always need an
     </emphasis><literal>origin</literal><emphasis> in the filesystem tree,
     and this </emphasis><literal>origin</literal><emphasis> is the original
     point where the subvolume has been created, that is, literally the
     path. In our example: </emphasis>
    </para>
<screen>/@/.snapshots/212/snapshot/mynewsubvol</screen>
    <para>
     A subvolume which should be permanently mounted via
     <literal>/etc/fstab</literal> should be created from an origin which is
     not a snapshot itself. This is why the <literal>/@/</literal> subvolume
     has been created: It serves as an independent root for permanent
     subvolumes such as <literal>/var</literal>, <literal>/srv</literal>,
     etc.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318752" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Storage and Partitioning"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318752" -->
    <title>LVM: using lvm_metad to activate volume</title>
    <para>
     With SLES 12 SP1 lvmetad is now enabled by default. With
     <literal>lvmetad</literal> lvm command can now work faster as they need
     not to scan the disks for the information, but can ask lvmetad about
     the disk information.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318487" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318487" -->
    <title>YaST iSCSI Client Does Not Change Startup Mode of Already Connected Targets</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>There was no possibility to keep the startup mode
     ('automatic', 'manual', or 'on boot') of already connected targets.
     Using either 'Discovery' on 'Discovered Targets' or 'Add' on 'Connected
     Targets' screen has reset the startup mode to default mode
     'manual'.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Now It is possible when using the 'Add' button on 'Connected Targets'
     screen to detect additional targets. The startup mode of the targets
     already connected will not change then.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318346" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="NFS Service,Storage and Partitioning"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318346" -->
    <title>pNFS Client Block Mode Support</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>SLE 12 already supported pNFS File and Objects models as a
     pNFS client, but not block mode.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The pNFS client included with SLE 12 SP1 now supports block mode.
    </para>
    <para>
     Block-mode pNFS involves the NFS client accessing the data directly
     using iSCSI or fibre channel (or similar) rather than using NFS. NFS is
     used for metadata management, for creating and deleting files and for
     finding out where in the block devices the data is. Once the client
     knows where the data is and has permission from the server, it accesses
     the storage device directly.
    </para>
    <para>
     The client needs to be running <literal>blkmapd</literal> which uses
     <literal>device-mapper</literal> to stitch together various block
     devices into a form that the NFS client can use.
    </para>
    <para>
     <literal>blkmapd</literal> can be started with:
    </para>
<screen>systemctl enable nfs-blkmap</screen>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317929" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317929" -->
    <title>Configuring iSNS Server Address Required</title>
    <para>
     If the <literal>target-isns</literal> package is installed, you can use
     YaST to configure the iSNS Server Address.
    </para>
    <para>
     Alternately, edit <literal>/etc/target-isns.conf</literal> after
     installation: Set the parameter <literal>isns_server</literal> to the
     IP address of the server where an iSNS daemon is running.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-315210" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel,Performance,Storage and Partitioning"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/315210" -->
    <title>Multitier Block I/O Caching</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>While flash-based storage is fast, traditional rotational
     hard disks are slow but provide an excellent price per gigabyte.
     Multitier I/O Caching describes the means of implementing a cache to
     amplify read and write operations in the fast, but smaller and
     expensive flash based storage.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     SUSE Linux Enterprise Server implements two different ways of
     performing caching between flash and rotational devices:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>bcache</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>dm-cache</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Both caching solutions provide the following caching modes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Write-through
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Write-back
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Pass-through/Write-around
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     <literal>dm-cache</literal> requires a backing device (HDD), a caching
     device (SSD, NVMe) and a metadata device. <literal>bcache</literal>
     only requires a backing device and a caching device.
    </para>
    <para>
     Both systems only work on block devices. Thus, network filesystems like
     NFS cannot be used as backing stores.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Virtualization" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization">
   <title>Virtualization</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319517" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Certifications,Interoperability,Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319517" -->
    <title>Virtual Machine Driver Pack 2.3</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>SUSE Linux Enterprise Virtual Machine Driver Pack is a set of
     paravirtualized device drivers for Microsoft Windows operating systems.
     These drivers improve the performance of unmodified Windows guest
     operating systems that are run in virtual environments created using
     Xen or KVM hypervisors with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 SP4 and
     SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1. Paravirtualized device drivers are
     installed in virtual machine instances of operating systems and
     represent hardware and functionality similar to the underlying physical
     hardware used by the system virtualization software layer.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The new features of SUSE Linux Enterprise Virtual Machine Driver Pack
     2.3 include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Support for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Support for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 SP4
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Support for new Microsoft Windows releases
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The drivers have been changed to the unified driver model first seen
       in Windows 2012r2. This makes the Xen to KVM transition much easier,
       as there is no need to change drivers.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Named pipes are now supported in guest agent.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Memory stats are now reported in the balloon driver (virtio).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Balloon driver fixes: Ballooning crash fix (Xen and virtio).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Hibernation fix (virtio).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Block driver fixes: Codepage 83 is now supported.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SCSI driver fixes: hibernation fix (virtio), blue screen due to
       pagefault fix (virtio).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Block/SCSI drivers: In the absence of a "real" serial number, "0"
       (character zero) is used rather than the previous eight space
       character string.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Xen ballooning fix: migrations now complete without freezing or
       crashing the VM.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Setup fixes: can now upgrade from VMDP 1.7 correctly. Setup now
       correctly identifies the running hypervisor when VMs are installed on
       SLES 12 SP1
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For more information on VMDP 2.3, see the official documentation.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Virtualization.KVM" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
    <title>KVM</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-317015" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Virtualization / KVM"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317015" -->
     <title>RDMA-Based Live Guest Migration</title>
     <para>
      RDMA-based (Remote Direct Memory Access) live guest migration helps
      make the migration of VM guests more deterministic under heavy load
      because it significantly reduces latency and increases throughput over
      TCP/IP.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-317014" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317014" -->
     <title>Containment of SR-IOV Device Errors When VFs Are Assigned to Guests</title>
     <para>
      If an SR-IOV device encounters an error and if any of the VFs
      belonging to the SR-IOV device is assigned to a guest(s), the affected
      guest(s) will be brought down without impacting any other running
      guests or the host. The VM guests can be brought up after the host
      driver for the SR-IOV device recovers the device.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-315674" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Virtualization / KVM"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/315674" -->
     <title>KVM: Supervisor Mode Access Prevention (SMAP)</title>
     <para>
      SMAP prevent the kernel from accessing user space and misusing user
      space contents as trusted. This feature can be exposed to a KVM guest
      OS.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-314497" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Scalability,Virtualization,Virtualization / KVM"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/314497" -->
     <title>KVM: Make Guests NUMA Aware</title>
     <para>
      NUMA host topology could be reflected and specified in the VMGuest OS
      using the <literal>numa</literal> element.
     </para>
     <para>
      Qemu now supports for pinning memory on host NUMA nodes. The existing
      options <literal>-mem-prealloc</literal>,
      <literal>-mem-path</literal>, <literal>-machine mem-merge</literal>
      and <literal>-machine dump-guest-core</literal> are subsumed by the
      QOM objects <literal>memory-backend-ram</literal> and
      <literal>memory-backend-file</literal>, and by the
      <literal>memdev</literal> option of <literal>-numa node</literal>.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-314466" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Virtualization / KVM"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/314466" -->
     <title>KVM: VM Guest OS with Memory Hotplugging Capability</title>
     <para>
      QEMU now supports memory hotplugging using the new
      <literal>pc-dimm</literal> device and the QOM objects
      <literal>memory-backend-ram</literal> and
      <literal>memory-backend-file</literal>.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Virtualization.XEN" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
    <title>XEN</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-320625" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Performance,Xen Virtual Machine Monitor"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320625" -->
     <title>Enabling Indirect Descriptors in the blkfront Module</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis> The </emphasis><literal>blkfront</literal><emphasis> driver
      originally shipped with SLES 12 and SLES 12 SP1 (Paravirtualization:
      </emphasis><literal>xenblk</literal><emphasis>, Hardware Virtual
      Machine: </emphasis><literal>xen-vbd</literal><emphasis>) does not
      enable indirect descriptors in environments not hosted on SUSE systems
      (such as those from Amazon, Oracle, etc.). This can lead to lower data
      bandwidth on single volumes in Xen. </emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      To allow improving data bandwidth, an additional
      <literal>blkfront</literal> driver (Paravirtualization:
      <literal>xen-blkfront</literal>, Hardware Virtual Machine:
      <literal>xen-vbd-upstream</literal>) has been added to the packages
      <literal>kernel-xen</literal> and <literal>xen-default-kmp</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The original <literal>blkfront</literal> module has been preserved and
      will continue to be the default <literal>blkfront</literal> module for
      both Paravirtualization and Hardware Virtual Machine environments.
      <literal>modprobe</literal> rules can then be used to determine which
      <literal>blkfront</literal> driver is used.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-320402" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320402" -->
     <title>GRUB Does Not Support vfb/vkbd Any More</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>The version of GRUB shipped with SLES 12 SP1 and SP2 does
      not support vfb/vkbd any more. This means that in Xen paravirtualized
      machines, there is no graphical display available while GRUB is
      active.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      To be able to see and interact with GRUB, switch to the text-based
      xencon protocol: Modify the kernel parameter of the PV guest, add
      <literal>console=hvc0 xencons=tty</literal>, and connect with the
      command <literal>console DOMAINNAME</literal> of the
      <literal>libvirt</literal> toolstack.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-315675" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Xen Virtual Machine Monitor"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/315675" -->
     <title>Xen: Supervisor Mode Access Prevention (SMAP)</title>
     <para>
      SMAP prevents the kernel from accessing user space and misusing user
      space contents as trusted. This feature can be exposed to a Xen guest
      OS.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Virtualization.Containers" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Containers">
    <title>Containers</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319426" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Containers">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319426" -->
     <title>zypper-docker, the Updater for Docker Images</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis> To discover if a Docker container is in need of an update,
      a manual </emphasis><literal>zypper lu</literal><emphasis> was needed.
      After patching, the changes had to be committed to make them
      persistent, and the container needed to be restarted. This was
      necessary for each container. </emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      Use <literal>zypper-docker</literal> to list and apply updates to your
      Docker images. This ensures any container based on the given image
      will receive the updates.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319425" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Containers">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319425" -->
     <title>Docker Image: Support for SLES 12 SP1</title>
     <para>
      The SLES 12 SP1 docker image is now added to the containers module.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319375" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Containers">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319375" -->
     <title>Docker Image: Support for SLES 11 SP4</title>
     <para>
      The SLES 11 SP4 docker image is now added to the containers module.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Virtualization.libvirt" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
    <title>libvirt</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318349" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Virtualization / KVM"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318349" -->
     <title>SUSE Enterprise Storage (Powered by Ceph) Client</title>
     <para>
      This update provides the functionality required for SUSE Linux
      Enterprise Server 12 to act as a client for SUSE Enterprise Storage.
     </para>
     <para>
      qemu can now use storage provided by the SUSE Enterprise Storage Ceph
      cluster via the RADOS Block Device (rbd) back-end. Applications can
      now be enhanced to directly incorporate object or block storage backed
      by the SUSE Enterprise Storage cluster, by linking with the
      <literal>librados</literal> and <literal>librbd</literal> client
      libraries.
     </para>
     <para>
      Also included is the <literal>rbd</literal> tool to manage RADOS block
      devices mapped via the <literal>rbd</literal> kernel module, for use
      as a standard generic block device.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-315157" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Xen Virtual Machine Monitor"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/315157" -->
     <title>Support for virtlockd in the libvirt Xen Driver</title>
     <para>
      The libvirt Xen drivers integrate the support of
      <literal>virtlockd</literal> to provide locking of virtual machine
      resources such as disks. This prevents simultaneous use of resources
      by multiple virtual machines.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Virtualization.Other" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Other">
    <title>Others</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318394" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Other">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318394" -->
     <title>virt-manager Update</title>
     <para>
      virt-manager version 1.2.1 is included in SLE 12 SP1. Check
      <ulink url="https://git.fedorahosted.org/cgit/virt-manager.git/tree/NEWS?id=v1.2.1">virt-manager
      1.2.1 NEWS</ulink> for more information.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-317749" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Other">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317749" -->
     <title>Libguestfs: add Python bindings</title>
     <para>
      Libguestfs python binding is now provided with
      <literal>guestfs</literal> tools.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-315578" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Other">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/315578" -->
     <title>virt-manager: hide PCI/SR-IOV devices already claimed/used by VMs</title>
     <para>
      <literal>virt-manager</literal> hide PCI/SR-IOV devices that are
      unavailable for PCI passthrough/SR-IOV if other VMs already claim
      those devices.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-315577" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Other">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/315577" -->
     <title>virt-manager: Setting Up SR-IOV Devices During VM Guest OS Creation</title>
     <para>
      <literal>virt-manager</literal> provides the ability to set up SR-IOV
      devices at VMGuest OS creation time.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
  </section>
 </section>
<!--
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
              href="known-x86_64.xml"/>
  -->
 <section id="InfraPackArch.x86_64">
  <title>AMD64/Intel64 64-Bit (x86_64) Specific Information</title>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.x86_64.Virtualization" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64:Virtualization">
   <title>Virtualization</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319422" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64:Virtualization">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319422" -->
    <title>Inclusion of virt-top Tools</title>
    <para>
     <literal>virt-top</literal> is a top-like utility for showing
     statistics for virtualized domains. Many keys and command line options
     are the same as for ordinary <literal>top</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.Power" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
  <title>POWER (ppc64le) Specific Information</title>
  <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-319640" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319640" -->
   <title>Starting X After Upgrading to SLES 12 SP1</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis>On SLES 12 on the POWER architecture, the display manager is
    configured not to start a local X server by default. On SLES 12 SP1
    installations on this architecture, the default setting has been
    changed: The display manager now starts an X server.</emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    To avoid problems during upgrade, the SLES 12 setting is not changed
    automatically. If you want the display manager to start an X server
    after the upgrade, open <literal>/etc/sysconfig/displaymanager</literal>
    and edit:
   </para>
<screen>DISPLAYMANAGER_STARTS_XSERVER="no"</screen>
   <para>
    to read:
   </para>
<screen>DISPLAYMANAGER_STARTS_XSERVER="yes"</screen>
   <para>
    Despite the default setting, due to a bug, GDM started an X server on
    SLES 12 (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=919723">https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=919723</ulink>). This problem has been fixed with a maintenance update for SLES 12 and
    SLES 12 SP1.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-319125" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319125" -->
   <title>SystemTap Probes Support on ppc64le</title>
   <para>
    With SLES 12 SP1, the SystemTap tool can now probe symbols on the
    ppc64le platform.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-319109" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319109" -->
   <title>Virtual Ethernet: Large Send / Receive Offload for ibmveth</title>
   <para>
    SLES 12 SP1 contains an update to the ibmveth driver that enables GRO
    (Generic Receive Offload) and TSO (TCP Segmentation Offload) for both
    IPv4 and IPv6.
   </para>
   <para>
    This feature allows Linux to send large packets resulting in a
    performance improvement.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-318367" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Virtualization / Containers"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318367" -->
   <title>Container support for Docker on IBM Power</title>
   <para>
    Provides the infrastructure and tool set to manage and deploy
    applications based on docker images based on gccgo.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-318012" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="RAS"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318012" -->
   <title>vmalloc address translation support in makedumpfile for ppc64le arch</title>
   <para>
    Makedumpfile tool supports filtering out sensitive data (e.g. security
    keys and confidential data) from a vmcore file, through '--eppic' and
    '--config' options. But to use these options, vmalloc address
    translation support is necessary. This feature adds vmalloc address
    translation support to makedumpfile tool so as to help in filtering out
    sensitive kernel data from vmcore file before passing it on.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-318011" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318011" -->
   <title>YaST Support to Configure Firmware-assisted Dump for ppc64le</title>
   <para>
    Earlier, manual steps were needed to configure fadump. This feature adds
    support to configure firmware-assisted dump in yast2-kdump.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the YaST kdump dialog, selecting "Enable Kdump" &amp; "Use
    Firmware-Assisted Dump", configures the system with fadump.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ">
  <title>System z (s390x) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   For more information, see
   <ulink url="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/linux390/documentation_novell_suse.html"/>
  </para>
  <para>
   IBM zEnterprise 196 (z196) and IBM zEnterprise 114 (z114) further on
   referred to as z196 and z114.
  </para>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Hardware" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
   <title>Hardware</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318376" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318376" -->
    <title>zEDC Compression</title>
    <para>
     zEDC compression can be used via the GenWQE (Generic Workqueue Engine)
     device driver. It is a PCIe card used to do zlib style compression and
     decompression according to RFC1950, RFC1951, and RFC1952.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318248" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318248" -->
    <title>snIPL interface to control dynamic CPU capacity</title>
    <para>
     Remote control of the capacity of target systems in HA setups allows to
     maintain the bandwidth during failure situations and removes the need
     for keeping unused capacity activated during normal operation
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318247" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318247" -->
    <title>PCI infrastructure enablement for IBM System z</title>
    <para>
     This feature provides prerequisites for the System z specific PCI
     support.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318066" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318066" -->
    <title>SE/HMC file access</title>
    <para>
     Files on the USB/DVD drive of the SE/HMC of z Systems hardware can now
     be accessed.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318063" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Infiniband,Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318063" -->
    <title>10GbE RoCE Express Feature</title>
    <para>
     SLES 12 SP1 supports the 10GbE RoCE Express feature on zEC12, zBC12 and
     IBM z13 via the Ethernet device using TCP/IP traffic without
     restrictions. Before using this feature on an IBM z13, make sure that
     the minimum required service is applied: z/VM APAR UM34525 and HW ycode
     N98778.057 (bundle 14).
    </para>
    <para>
     SLES 12 SP1 includes RDMA enablement and DAPL/OFED for s390x as a
     technology preview, but these can only be used on LPAR when running on
     an IBM zEC12 or zBC12. They cannot be used on an IBM z13.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318041" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Hardware and Drivers,Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318041" -->
    <title>SMT Base Support for Linux on z Systems</title>
    <para>
     With SLES 12 SP1 Linux on z Systems includes support for SMT
     (Simultaneous Multi Threading) that is available with the IBM z13 or
     later hardware.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317195" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317195" -->
    <title>New cputype Command</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Often it is difficult to correlate the commonly used name of
     the processor with the IBM model number for that processor.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The cputype command is now included in the s390-tools package. The
     cputype command prints both the IBM model number as well as the more
     commonly used processor name.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Virtualization" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
   <title>Virtualization</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320021" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320021" -->
    <title>At the End of the Installation of SLES 12 SP1 in zKVM, Do Not Allow the System to Reboot</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>At the end of the installation of SLES 12 SP1, you will be
     asked to reboot the system. However, on zKVM, immediately rebooting
     means that the installer will start anew.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Instead of rebooting the system, make sure that the system shuts down.
     You can then adapt your VM configuration for the changed kernel/initrd
     parameters. After that, you can reboot into the newly installed system
     as usual.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319342" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="zSeries"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319342" -->
    <title>qclib: Improved Capacity Query for LPARs, z/VM, and KVM</title>
    <para>
     This feature provides a library to determine the capacity of an
     environment for accounting purposes. Applications can trigger system
     and capacity details regarding the System, LPAR, z/VM, and KVM
     environments in terms of available CPU (shares).
    </para>
    <para>
     If you are using z/VM 6.3, we strongly suggest installing the APAR
     VM65419 (or higher) to improve the output of qclib.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318474" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318474" -->
    <title>vhostmd/vm-dump-metrics</title>
    <para>
     Improved performance handling by querying host performance metrics from
     within VM is now enabled via <literal>vm-dump-metrics</literal>, which
     is available in the <literal>vhostmd</literal> package.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318373" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Virtualization,Virtualization / Containers"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318373" -->
    <title>Container support for Docker on IBM z Systems</title>
    <para>
     Provides the infrastructure and tool set to manage and deploy
     applications based on docker images based on gccgo.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318060" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318060" -->
    <title>Support of Long Names for Linux Guests</title>
    <para>
     The limitation of eight characters for Linux guest names is removed and
     long names can be reflected in <literal>/proc/sysinfo</literal> with up
     to 255 characters.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Storage" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Storage">
   <title>Storage</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318045" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318045" -->
    <title>Reintroduce selected zfcp unit sysfs attributes for scsi devices</title>
    <para>
     Enable to manually trigger LUN recovery and to export debug data for
     zfcp-attached SCSI devices that are attached by automatic LUN scan.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317934" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317934" -->
    <title>Enforcing Partitioned DASDs for LVM</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Because the first sector of a DASD has a special format it is
     not possible to use unpartitioned DASDs for LVM. In YaST it was
     possible to select an unpartitioned DASD in the expert partitioner for
     LVM but then creating the physical volume failed later on.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     YaST now disallows to select an unpartitioned DASD for LVM.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Network" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
   <title>Network</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318244" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318244" -->
    <title>qeth: Accurate ethtool Output</title>
    <para>
     Provides improved monitoring and service via more timely and accurate
     display of settings and values via the ethtool when running on hardware
     that supports the improved query of network cards
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318241" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318241" -->
    <title>Query OSA Address Table</title>
    <para>
     Provide infrastructure to gather and display OSA and TCP/IP
     configuration information via the "OSA query Address Table" hardware
     function to ease administration of OSA and TCP/IP configuration
     information.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Security" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
   <title>Security</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318043" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318043" -->
    <title>Support of the CEX5S crypto card and more than 16 crypto domains</title>
    <para>
     The cryptographic device driver includes support for the CEX5S crypto
     card introduced with the IBM z13. The support of crypto domains is
     extended above 16 domains and now supports up to 256 domains.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318042" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318042" -->
    <title>In-kernel crypto: DRBG support</title>
    <para>
     The generation of pseudo random numbers include enhanced support for
     "Deterministic Random Bit Generator" (DRBG) according to updated
     security specification NIST SP 800-90A.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.RAS" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
   <title>Reliability, Availability, Serviceability (RAS)</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318246" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318246" -->
    <title>Linux support for concurrent Flash MCL updates</title>
    <para>
     Enables to apply concurrent hardware microcode level upgrades (MCL)
     without impacting I/O operations to the Flash storage media and
     notifies users of the changed Flash hardware service level
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318087" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="High Availability,RAS"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318087" -->
    <title>Enhanced watchdog support for KVM</title>
    <para>
     Linux on z Systems now includes the DIAG288 watchdog support that
     provides improved High Availability and RAS characteristics for Linux
     KVM guests
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318034" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="RAS"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318034" -->
    <title>Improve zfcp auto port scan resiliency</title>
    <para>
     Improved Fibre Channel port scan behaviour of the zfcp device driver to
     avoid excessive scanning and scan bursts. Scan bursts can occur in
     large virtual server environments.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318033" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="RAS"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318033" -->
    <title>OSA-Express5s Cards Support in qethqoat</title>
    <para>
     Support for OSA-Express5s cards has been added to the qethqoat tool,
     which is part of the s390tools package. This enhancement extends the
     serviceability of network and card setups for OSA-Express5s cards.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Performance" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
   <title>Performance</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318243" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318243" -->
    <title>Hot-patching Support for Linux on System z Binaries</title>
    <para>
     Hot-patch support in gcc implements support for online patching of
     multi-threaded code for Linux on System binaries. It is possible to
     select specific functions for hot-patching using a <literal>function
     attribute</literal> and to enable hot-patching for all functions (<literal>-mhotpatch</literal>) via command line option. Because
     enabling of hot-patching has negative impact on software size and
     performance it is recommended to use hot-patching for specific
     functions and not to enable hot-patch support in general.
    </para>
    <para>
     For online documentation, see
     <ulink url="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc/">http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc/</ulink>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318088" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318088" -->
    <title>Software reference bit handling for memory operations</title>
    <para>
     The memory handling on z Systems is now based on Software reference bit
     handling, that replaces the z specific "storage key operations". That
     provides enhanced commonality with other platforms and improved
     performance especially for Linux running as KVM guest
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318056" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318056" -->
    <title>SIMD instruction support in Linux kernel, dump tools, toolchain and LLVM</title>
    <para>
     The Linux kernel now provides support for user space applications to
     use SIMD (Single Instruction Multiple Data) instructions that operate
     on vector registers and are available with IBM z13 and later hardware.
    </para>
    <para>
     Vector registers are now part of kernel dumps. The crash tool is
     extended to display the vector registers of the kernel dump and the
     zgetdump tool is enhanced for converting dump formats.
    </para>
    <para>
     For gcc support, the add on gcc 5.2 is required. The add-on is part of
     the tool chain module.
    </para>
    <para>
     SIMD support has been added to LLVM, resulting in improved performance
     of the software-emulated 3D graphics stack (mesa / llvmpipe).
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318046" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318046" -->
    <title>SMT support in stand alone dump and dump tools</title>
    <para>
     The stand alone dumper and dump tools include support for SMT
     instructions that are supported with the IBM z13 and later hardware
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318038" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Toolchain"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318038" -->
    <title>IBM z13 instruction support in toolchain</title>
    <para>
     The Linux toolchain, gcc, binutils and gdb now supports the hardware
     instructions that were introduced with the IBM z13. With these
     instructions, full hardware functionality and improved performance are
     available. For gcc support, the add-on gcc 5.2 is required. The add-on
     is part of the Toolchain Module.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318028" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318028" -->
    <title>Utilizing the SIMD Vector Instructions introduced with the IBM z Systems z13</title>
    <para>
     User space applications are able to utilize the SIMD vector
     instructions introduced with the IBM z Systems z13
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318026" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318026" -->
    <title>GDB Transactional Diagnostic Block support</title>
    <para>
     The enhanced GDB support now displays the program exception TDB
     "Transactional Diagnostic Block" from a core file, as well as during a
     debug session for debugging code using transactions
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318025" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318025" -->
    <title>The perf Program to Capture Detailed Performance Data</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Performance issues sometimes require more details about CPU
     cycles used by workloads, shared libraries, kernel and device
     drivers.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     With support for the CPU-measurement sampling facility the perf program
     can be used to capture more detailed performance data. It includes the
     following key features to sample workloads:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Sampling of CPU cycles
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Basic sampling - snapshot of various PSW bits and instruction address
       at specific time interval
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Support for raw sample data - sampling data made available to the
       perf program that can be used/posted by external applications
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Support for diagnostic sampling - provides a snapshot of
       hardware-model dependent information
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Misc">
<!-- entries from SP1 RNs -->
   <title>Miscellaneous</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319405" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Misc">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Desktop,Installation,Linux Kernel,Toolchain,zSeries"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319405" -->
    <title>Architecture Level Set</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Newer machines have new instructions and better instruction
     schedulers.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The default for the system compiler is to generate code for z196 / z114
     and do the scheduling for zEC12.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
<!-- 2014-03-17, ke: if still needed, to be provided via fate -->
<!--
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="technical.xml"/>
 -->
 </section>
 <section id="Driver_Updates">
  <title>Driver Updates</title>
  <remark>** list of update by category ** version comparison table from
  previous SP/Product </remark>
  <para/>
  <section id="Driver_Updates.Other" remap="Driver_Updates:Other">
   <title>Other Drivers</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318902" remap="Driver_Updates:Other">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Hardware and Drivers"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318902" -->
    <title>Support for New Intel Processors</title>
    <para>
     This Service Pack adds support for the following Intel processors:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Intel® Xeon® processor E3 v4 product family
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Intel® Xeon® processor E5 v4 product family
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Intel® Xeon® processor E7 v4 product family
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Intel® Xeon® Processor D-1500 Family
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       6th Generation Intel® Core™ processor family
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Packages">
  <title>Packages and Functionality Changes</title>
  <para>
   This section comprises changes to packages, such as additions, updates,
   removals and changes to the package layout of software. It also contains
   information about modules available for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. For
   information about changes to package management tools, such as Zypper or
   RPM, see
   <xref linkend="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.SystemsManagement"/>.
  </para>
  <section id="Packages.New" remap="Packages:New">
   <title>New Packages</title>
   <remark> *** Description of the new package with direct link to the official website (need the
    URL tag) *** Version and release of the package *** Why this new package: enhancements request
    *** link to the official documentation *** link to the SUSE's documentation *** Dependencies and
    Build requires </remark>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318956" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318956" -->
    <title>OpenJDK 8 was added to SLE12 SP1</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>SLE 12 only supported version 7 of OpenJDK. There was no
     solution for customers needing a higher version of Java.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In SLE 12 SP1, OpenJDK 8 was added as an alternative Java version.
     OpenJDK 7 remains available additionally. To choose the right version
     for your use case, use <literal>update-alternatives</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318486" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318486" -->
    <title>Filtering the systemd Journal with the YaST2 Journal Module</title>
    <para>
     Since SLE 12 SP1, YaST includes a new journal module, which enables
     users and system administrators to take advantage of the advanced
     filtering capabilities of the systemd journal.
    </para>
    <para>
     The new module displays the log entries in a table with a search box
     providing grep-like live searching. In addition, it allows to filter
     the entries in the list by date and time, unit, file, or priority.
    </para>
    <para>
     In short, the module offers all the advantages of the old (and still
     present) log viewer with some extra systemd powered goodies.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318412" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318412" -->
    <title>pax Binary Replaced with spax from the star Package</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> The original provider of the
     </emphasis><literal>pax</literal><emphasis> binary was the package
     </emphasis><literal>pax</literal><emphasis>. However, this binary was
     not LSB-compatible and is not maintained upstream. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In SLE 12 SP1, <literal>pax</literal> was replaced with
     <literal>spax</literal> (from the package <literal>star</literal>).
     For backwards compatibility, this package also provides a symbolic link
     for <literal>pax</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The new command <literal>spax</literal> provides many of the same
     options that the former <literal>pax</literal> also offered. However,
     the following options are not supported: <literal>-0</literal>,
     <literal>-B</literal>, <literal>-D</literal>, <literal>-E</literal>,
     <literal>-G</literal>, <literal>-O</literal>, <literal>-P</literal>,
     <literal>-T</literal>, <literal>-U</literal>, <literal>-Y</literal>,
     <literal>-Z</literal>. <literal>spax</literal> does not provide
     options beyond those offered by <literal>pax</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Additionally, the formats supported by the option <literal>-x</literal>
     have changed:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Formats supported by <literal>pax -x</literal> were:
       <literal>bcpio</literal>, <literal>cpio</literal>,
       <literal>sv4cpio</literal>, <literal>sv4crc</literal>,
       <literal>tar</literal>, <literal>ustar</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Current <literal>spax -x</literal> formats are:
       <literal>v7tar</literal>, <literal>tar</literal>,
       <literal>star</literal>, <literal>gnutar</literal>,
       <literal>ustar</literal>, <literal>xstar</literal>,
       <literal>xustar</literal>, <literal>exustar</literal>,
       <literal>pax</literal>, <literal>suntar</literal>,
       <literal>bin</literal>, <literal>cpio</literal>,
       <literal>odc</literal>, <literal>asc</literal>,
       <literal>crc</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     It is also possible that other options have slightly different behavior
     than you are used to. For more information, see the
     <literal>spax</literal> manual pages.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318345" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318345" -->
    <title>Additional FreeRADIUS Packages</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> SLE 12 GA shipped with a
     </emphasis><literal>freeradius</literal><emphasis> version that was
     stripped to its core and removed certain functionality that was
     available in SLE 11. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     SLE 12 now ships with additional packages that fix the feature
     omissions:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>freeradius-server-python</literal>,
       <literal>freeradius-server-perl</literal>: Allow writing FreeRadius
       modules in Python/Perl.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>freeradius-server-krb5</literal>,
       <literal>freeradius-server-ldap</literal>: Modules for
       authentication via Kerberos 5 and LDAP.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>freeradius-server-mysql</literal>,
       <literal>freeradius-server-postgresql</literal>,
       <literal>freeradius-server-sqlite</literal>: Database backend
       modules for the frontend SQL module (<literal>rlm_sql</literal>) in
       the corresponding SQL databases.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318304" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318304" -->
    <title>Support for Shibboleth Added</title>
    <para>
     The packages necessary to set up Shibboleth authentication were added.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Packages.Update" remap="Packages:Update">
   <title>Updated Packages</title>
   <remark> *** Description of the new package with direct link to the official website *** version
    comparison table from previous SP/product *** Bugs fixed since previous SP/Product (link to
    Bugzilla) *** Enhancements request (link to Fate number) *** link to the official documentation
    *** link to the SUSE's documentation *** Security fixes (link to CVE or SUSE's security web
    site), link to PIF *** Changelog diff (all other information non relative to security/fate/bugs) </remark>
   <para/>
<!-- For the moment, track version info here -->
<!-- to be provided via fate
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
               href="features-basic.xml"/>
   -->
<!-- included directly
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
               href="features-desktop.xml"/>
   -->
<!-- 2014-03-20, ke: feedback by fcrozat
2014-09-24, aginies: remove has already in another section
<section>
 <title>Desktop</title>
 <para />
 <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    bnc#804973
   <para>
     GNOME 3.10
   </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>
     X.org 7.7
   </para>
  </listitem>

 </itemizedlist>
</section>
-->
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319961" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319961" -->
    <title>Qt 5 Has Been Updated to 5.5.1</title>
    <para>
     The Qt 5 libraries were updated to 5.5.1. Qt 5.5.1 includes new
     features and security fixes for known vulnerabilities over Qt 5.3.2
     (the version initially shipped in SP1).
    </para>
    <para>
     Among other security fixes, the new version includes a fix for the Qt
     WebEngine's Weak Diffie-Hellman vulnerability (CVE-2015-4000).
    </para>
    <para>
     New features include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Update of Qt WebEngine which updates the includes Chromium snapshot
       to version 40
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       New modules to extend 3D APIs (Qt Canvas 3D and Qt 3D)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Improvements in the QML engine which is the basis of Qt Quick
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Improvements in the Qt Multimedia module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Many other features and bugfixes
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319493" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319493" -->
    <title>Puppet Has Been Updated from 3.6.2 to 3.8.5</title>
    <para>
     Puppet has been updated from 3.6.2 to 3.8.5. All releases between these
     two versions should only bring Puppet 3 backward-compatible features
     and bug and security fixes.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information, read the following release notes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Puppet 3.7 Release Notes:
       <ulink url="http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.7/reference/release_notes.html">http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.7/reference/release_notes.html</ulink>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Puppet 3.8 Release Notes:
       <ulink url="http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.8/reference/release_notes.html">http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.8/reference/release_notes.html</ulink>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     In particular, you should pay attention to the following upgrade notes
     and warnings:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The new default value of the <literal>environment_timeout</literal>
       option is <literal>0</literal>:
       <ulink url="http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.7/reference/release_notes.html#new-default-value-environmenttimeout--0">http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.7/reference/release_notes.html#new-default-value-environmenttimeout--0</ulink>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       You can now set the parser setting per-environment in
       <literal>environment.conf</literal>:
       <ulink url="http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.7/reference/release_notes.html#new-feature-parser-setting-in-environmentconf">http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.7/reference/release_notes.html#new-feature-parser-setting-in-environmentconf</ulink>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Make sure the keepalive timeout is configured to be five or more
       seconds:
       <ulink url="http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.7/reference/release_notes.html#upgrade-warning-rack-server-config">http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet/3.7/reference/release_notes.html#upgrade-warning-rack-server-config</ulink>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319391" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319391" -->
    <title>Tar: Extended Attributes</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> The </emphasis><literal>tar</literal><emphasis> version in
     SLES and SLED 12 (SP0) was not handling extended attributes properly.
     </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     A maintenance update for <literal>tar</literal> fixes this issue. This
     update introduces new package dependencies:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>libacl1</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>libselinux1</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Both of these packages are already required by other core packages in a
     SLE installation.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319388" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319388" -->
    <title>Wireshark Updated to 1.12.x</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The Wireshark 1.10.x series of releases was discontinued
     upstream and does no longer receive security updates or bug
     fixes.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Wireshark was updated to the 1.12.x series of releases, providing for
     delivery of fixes for security issues as well as new and updated
     protocol support and dissectors.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319107" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319107" -->
    <title>KSH 93v Replaced with KSH 93u</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> In the Legacy Module for SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, we
     shipped </emphasis><literal>KSH</literal><emphasis> 93v. However, the
     93v branch was not fully stable yet. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     With SLE 12 SP1, we release <literal>KSH</literal> 93u, which is more
     stable version 93v. In order to provide a regular update path from 93v
     to 93u, a higher version number (93vu) has been used for this update.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319049" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319049" -->
    <title>Upgrading PostgreSQL Installations from 9.1 to 9.4</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>To upgrade a PostgreSQL server installation from version 9.1
     to 9.4, the database files need to be converted to the new
     version.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Note:<emphasis> System Upgrade from SLE 11 </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>On SLE 12, there are no PostgreSQL 8.4 or 9.1 packages. This
     means, you first must migrate PostgreSQL from 8.4 or 9.1 to 9.4 on SLE
     11 before upgrading the system from SLE 11 to SLE 12.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Newer versions of PostgreSQL come with the
     <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> tool that simplifies and speeds up the
     migration of a PostgreSQL installation to a new version. Formerly, it
     was necessary to dump and restore the database files which was much
     slower.
    </para>
    <para>
     To work, <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> needs to have the server
     binaries of both versions available. To allow this, we had to change
     the way PostgreSQL is packaged as well as the naming of the packages,
     so that two or more versions of PostgreSQL can be installed in
     parallel.
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with version 9.1, PostgreSQL package names on SUSE Linux
     Enterprise products contain numbers indicating the major version. In
     PostgreSQL terms, the major version consists of the first two
     components of the version number, for example, 9.1, 9.3, and 9.4. So,
     the packages for PostgreSQL 9.3 are named
     <literal>postgresql93</literal>,
     <literal>postgresql93-server</literal>, etc. Inside the packages, the
     files were moved from their standard location to a versioned location
     such as <literal>/usr/lib/postgresql93/bin</literal> or
     <literal>/usr/lib/postgresql94/bin</literal>. This avoids file
     conflicts if multiple packages are installed in parallel. The
     <literal>update-alternatives</literal> mechanism creates and maintains
     symbolic links that cause one version (by default the highest installed
     version) to re-appear in the standard locations. By default, database
     data is stored under <literal>/var/lib/pgsql/data</literal> on SUSE
     Linux Enterprise.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following preconditions have to be fulfilled before data migration
     can be started:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If not already done, the packages of the old PostgreSQL version (9.3)
       must be upgraded to the latest release through a maintenance update.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The packages of the new PostgreSQL major version need to be
       installed. For SLE 12, this means installing
       <literal>postgresql94-server</literal> and all the packages it
       depends on. Because <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> is contained in the
       package <literal>postgresql94-contrib</literal>, this package must
       be installed as well, at least until the migration is done.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Unless <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> is used in link mode, the server
       must have enough free disk space to temporarily hold a copy of the
       database files. If the database instance was installed in the default
       location, the needed space in megabytes can be determined by running
       the following command as root: <literal>du -hs
       /var/lib/pgsql/data</literal>. If space is tight, it might help to
       run the <literal>VACUUM FULL</literal> SQL command on each database
       in the PostgreSQL instance to be migrated which might take very long.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     Upstream documentation about <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> including
     step-by-step instructions for performing a database migration can be
     found under
     <literal>file:///usr/share/doc/packages/postgresql94/html/pgupgrade.html</literal>
     (if the postgresql94-docs package is installed), or online under
     <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/static/pgupgrade.html">http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/static/pgupgrade.html</ulink>. NOTE: The online documentation explains how you can install
     PostgreSQL from the upstream sources (which is not necessary on SLE)
     and also uses other directory names (<literal>/usr/local</literal>
     instead of the <literal>update-alternatives</literal> based path as
     described above).
    </para>
    <para>
     For background information about the inner workings of
     <literal>pg_admin</literal> and a performance comparison with the old
     dump and restore method, see
     <ulink url="http://momjian.us/main/writings/pgsql/pg_upgrade.pdf">http://momjian.us/main/writings/pgsql/pg_upgrade.pdf</ulink>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319040" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319040" -->
    <title>ntp 4.2.8</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>ntp was updated to version 4.2.8.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis> The ntp server ntpd does not synchronize with its peers
       anymore and the peers are specified by their host name in
       </emphasis><literal>/etc/ntp.conf</literal><emphasis>. </emphasis>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis> The output of </emphasis><literal>ntpq
       --peers</literal><emphasis> lists IP numbers of the remote servers
       instead of their host names. </emphasis>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Name resolution for the affected hosts works
     otherwise.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Configure ntpd to not run in chroot mode by setting
    </para>
<screen>NTPD_RUN_CHROOTED="no"</screen>
    <para>
     in <literal>/etc/sysconfig/ntp</literal>. Then restart the service
     with:
    </para>
<screen>systemctl restart ntpd</screen>
    <para>
     Due to the architecture of <literal>ntpd</literal>, it does not start
     reliably in a chroot environment. Furthermore, the daemon drops all
     capabilities except for the one needed to open sockets on reserved
     ports, so chroot is not required. If policy requirements mandate this,
     AppArmor can be used to further limit the process in what it can do.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Additional Information</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The meaning of some parameters has changed, for example <literal>sntp
     -s</literal> is now <literal>sntp -S</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     After having been deprecated for several years, ntpdc is now disabled
     by default for security reasons. It can be re-enabled by adding the
     line <literal>enable mode7</literal> to
     <literal>/etc/ntp.conf</literal>, but preferably
     <literal>ntpq</literal> should be used instead.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319021" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319021" -->
    <title>Dependency on libHBAAPI Removed from fcoe-utils</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> The package
     </emphasis><literal>fcoe-utils</literal><emphasis> used to depend on
     the back-end libraries
     </emphasis><literal>libHBAAPI</literal><emphasis> and
     </emphasis><literal>libhbalinux</literal><emphasis>. The sole purpose
     of these two libraries is reading informational and statistical data
     from Sysfs. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The commands <literal>fcoeadm</literal> and <literal>fcping</literal>
     from the package <literal>fcoe-utils</literal> have been rewritten to
     directly read the needed information from Sysfs without a third-party
     back-end library.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319006" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319006" -->
    <title>MariaDB Packaging Improvements</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"> New Helper Script and <literal>systemd</literal>
     Unit Files </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     SLE 12 SP1 ships with a new
     <literal>/usr/lib/mysql/mysql-systemd-helper</literal> script and the
     following native <literal>systemd</literal> unit files:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>mysql.service</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>mysql.target</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>mysql@.service</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The reason was to move <literal>rc.mysql-multi</literal> init script to
     the <literal>systemd</literal> services which call
     <literal>mysql-systemd-helper</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Restart on Failure</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Within the unit files, the option <literal>Restart=on-failure</literal>
     is set. This means that the MariaDB instance is automatically restarted
     on failure.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"> Managing Services Using
     <literal>systemd</literal> </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Instead of <literal>chkconfig mysql on</literal> (etc.), use native
     <literal>systemd</literal> commands now, for example:
    </para>
<screen>systemctl enable mysql</screen>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Multiple Instances of MariaDB</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     After setting multiple instances in /etc/my.cnf, they can be managed
     with:
    </para>
<screen>mysqld_multi</screen>
    <para>
     For more information, see <literal>mysqld_multi --help</literal> (same
     as SP0).
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318913" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318913" -->
    <title>Tomcat Updated to Version 8</title>
    <para>
     In Service Pack 1 of SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, Tomcat 7 was replaced by
     Tomcat 8 to allow access to newer features.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318300" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318300" -->
    <title>Python Was Updated to Version 2.7.9</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The Python script interpreter was updated to version 2.7.9. A
     key feature is the improved SSL module which can better check X.509
     certificates used in TLS/SSL communication.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>If certificate validation is enabled, the Python SSL module
     will no longer work with TLS/SSL installations that rely on self-signed
     certificates or are set up improperly.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     For compatibility reasons, TLS/SSL certificate validation remains
     disabled by default.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317988" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317988" -->
    <title>New Package: IBM Java 8</title>
    <para>
     Starting with SLES 12 SP1, IBM Java 8 is available for SLES 12.
    </para>
    <para>
     For documentation and features see:
     <ulink url="http://www-01.ibm.com/support/docview.wss?uid=swg21696670">http://www-01.ibm.com/support/docview.wss?uid=swg21696670</ulink>
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Packages.Deprecated" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
   <title>Removed and Deprecated Functionality</title>
   <remark>
    ** Why this choice?
    ** How to handle this deprecation in your system
    ** specific case (LTSS etc.)
   </remark>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320740" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320740" -->
    <title>Docker Compose Has Been Removed from the Containers Module</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Docker Compose is not supported as a part of SUSE Linux
     Enterprise Server 12. While it was temporarily included as a Technology
     Preview, testing showed that the technology was not ready for
     enterprise use.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     SUSE's focus is on Kubernetes which provides better value in terms of
     features, extensibility, stability and performance.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section id="Packages.Deprecated.rm_with_12" remap="Packages:Deprecated:rm_with_12">
    <title>Packages Removed with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12</title>
    <para>
     The following packages were removed with the major release of SUSE
     Linux Enterprise Server 12:
    </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-316136" remap="Packages:Deprecated:rm_with_12">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Monitoring Services"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316136" -->
     <title>Nagios Server Now Part of a SUSE Manager Subscription</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Support for Icinga (a successor of Nagios) will not be part
      of the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 subscription.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      Fully supported Icinga packages for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
      will be available as part of a SUSE Manager subscription. In the SUSE
      Manager context we will be able to deliver better integration into the
      monitoring frameworks.
     </para>
     <para>
      More frequent updates on the monitoring server parts than in the past
      are planned.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-314685" remap="Packages:Deprecated:rm_with_12">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/314685" -->
     <title>YaST Modules Dropped Starting with SUSE Linux Enterprise 12</title>
     <para>
      The following YaST modules or obsolete features of modules are not
      available in the SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 code base anymore:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-phone-services
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-repair
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-network: DSL configuration
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-network: ISDN configuration
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-network: modem support
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-backup and yast2-restore
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-apparmor: incident reporting tools
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-apparmor: profile generating tools
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-*creator (moved to SDK)
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        YaST installation into directory
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-x11
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-mouse
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-irda (IrDA)
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        YaST Boot and Installation server modules
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-fingerprint-reader
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        yast2-profile-manager
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="Packages.Deprecated.rm_with_12sp1" remap="Packages:Deprecated:rm_with_12sp1">
    <title>Packages Removed with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1</title>
    <para>
     The following packages were removed with the release of SUSE Linux
     Enterprise Server 12 SP1:
    </para>
<!--
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>PKG</term>
     <listitem><para></para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>...</term>
     <listitem><para></para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   -->
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319712" remap="Packages:Deprecated:rm_with_12sp1">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Xen Virtual Machine Monitor"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319712" -->
     <title>Xen: blktap Superseded by blktap2</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis> The </emphasis><literal>blktap</literal><emphasis> driver
      is no longer maintained upstream and is thus also no longer supported
      on SLE 12 SP1. </emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      You should now use the <literal>blktap2</literal> driver.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319666" remap="Packages:Deprecated:rm_with_12sp1">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319666" -->
     <title>wpa_supplicant Replaces xsupplicant</title>
     <para>
      In SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 SP1 and 12 SP2,
      <literal>xsupplicant</literal> was removed entirely.
     </para>
     <para>
      For pre-authentication of systems via network (including RADIUS) and
      specifically wireless connections, install the
      <literal>wpa_supplicant</literal> package.
      <literal>wpa_supplicant</literal> now replaces
      <literal>xsupplicant</literal>. <literal>wpa_supplicant</literal>
      provides better stability, security and a broader range of
      authentication options.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section id="Packages.Deprecated.Future" remap="Packages:Deprecated:Future">
    <title>Packages and Features to Be Removed in the Future</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-316144" remap="Packages:Deprecated:Future">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="zSeries"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316144" -->
     <title>Deprecate DMSVSMA for snIPL for SLES 12 SP1</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>The RPC protocol is used with old z/VM versions only that
      are going out of service.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      The support of remote access for snIPL to z/VM hosts via the RPC
      protocol is being deprecated starting with SLES 12 SP1. It is
      recommended to use remote access to z/VM hosts via SMAPI, provided by
      supported z/VM 5.4, and z/VM 6.x versions. For details about setting
      up your z/VM system for API access see <emphasis>z/VM Systems
      Management Application Programming</emphasis>, SC24-6234.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
  </section>
<!-- was: InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Package -->
  <section id="Packages.Packaging" remap="Packages:Packaging">
   <title>Changes in Packaging and Delivery</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319418" remap="Packages:Packaging">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319418" -->
    <title>Graphviz PDF output Requires X11</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>In order to be able to create PDFs, graphviz needs the
     package graphviz-gnome. Therefore, graphviz unconditionally required
     that package. This is unwanted on systems where X11 is not
     installed.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <literal>graphviz</literal> package now only pulls in
     <literal>graphviz-gnome</literal> if X11 is installed.
    </para>
    <para>
     This means that on systems without X11, the <literal>graphviz</literal>
     tools cannot create PDFs.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Packages.Modules" remap="Packages:Modules">
   <title>Modules</title>
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry><emphasis>Module Name</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry><emphasis>Content</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry><emphasis>Life Cycle</emphasis>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>Web and Scripting Module</entry>
       <entry>PHP, Python, Ruby on Rails</entry>
       <entry>3 years, ~18 months overlap</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>Legacy Module</entry>
       <entry>Sendmail, old Java, …</entry>
       <entry>3 years</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>Public Cloud Module</entry>
       <entry>Public cloud initialization code and tools</entry>
       <entry>Continuous integration</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>Toolchain Module</entry>
       <entry>GCC</entry>
       <entry>Yearly delivery</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>Advanced Systems Management Module</entry>
       <entry>cfengine, puppet and the new "machinery" tool</entry>
       <entry>Continuous integration</entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para>
    For more information about the life cycle of packages contained in
    modules, see
    <ulink url="https://scc.suse.com/docs/lifecycle/sle/12/modules"/>.
   </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320852" remap="Packages:Modules">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320852" -->
    <title>libgcrypt11 Available from the Legacy Module</title>
    <para>
     The Legacy module now provides a package for
     <literal>libgcrypt11</literal>. This enables running applications
     built on SLES 11 against <literal>libgcrypt11</literal> on SLES 12.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318935" remap="Packages:Modules">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Documentation"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318935" -->
    <title>Available Extensions and Modules</title>
    <para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension 12 SP1 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability GEO Extension 12 SP1 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        SUSE Linux Enterprise Workstation Extension 12 SP1 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        SUSE Linux Enterprise Software Development Kit 12 SP1 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Advanced Systems Management Module 12 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Containers Module 12 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Legacy Module 12 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Public Cloud Module 12 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Toolchain Module 12 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Web and Scripting Module 12 x86_64
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     For more information about Extension and Modules, see the product
     documentation and
     <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/docrep/documents/huz0a6bf9a/suse_linux_enterprise_server_12_modules_white_paper.pdf">SUSE
     Linux Enterprise Server 12 Modules</ulink>.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="TechInfo" remap="TechInfo">
  <title>Technical Information</title>
  <para>
   This section contains information about system limits, a number of
   technical changes and enhancements for the experienced user.
  </para>
<!-- bnc#483250 -->
  <para>
   When talking about CPUs, we use the following terminology:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>CPU Socket</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The visible physical entity, as it is typically mounted to a
      motherboard or an equivalent.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>CPU Core</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The (usually not visible) physical entity as reported by the CPU
      vendor.
     </para>
     <para>
      On System z this is equivalent to an IFL.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Logical CPU</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is what the Linux Kernel recognizes as a "CPU".
     </para>
     <para>
      We avoid the word "thread" (which is sometimes used), as the word
      "thread" would also become ambiguous subsequently.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Virtual CPU</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A logical CPU as seen from within a Virtual Machine.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-317893" remap="TechInfo">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Documentation,Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317893" -->
   <title>Virtualization: Network Devices Supported</title>
   <para>
    SLES 12 supports the following virtualized network drivers:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Full virtualization: Intel e1000
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Full virtualization: Realtek 8139
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Paravirtualized: QEMU Virtualized NIC Card (virtio, KVM only)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-317892" remap="TechInfo">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Documentation,Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317892" -->
   <title>Virtualization: Devices Supported for Booting</title>
   <para>
    SLE12 support VM guest to boot from:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Parallel ATA (PATA/IDE)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Advanced Host Controller Interface (AHCI)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Floppy Disk Drive (FDD)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      virtio-blk
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      virtio-scsi
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Preboot eXecution Environment (PXE) ROMs (for supported Network
      Interface Cards)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Boot from <literal>USB</literal> and <literal>PCI pass-through</literal>
    devices are not supported.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-317891" remap="TechInfo">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Documentation,Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317891" -->
   <title>Virtualization: Supported Disks Formats and Protocols</title>
   <para>
    The following disk formats support read-write access (RW):
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>raw</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>qed</literal> (KVM only)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>qcow2</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The following disk formats support read-only access (RO):
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>vmdk</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>vpc</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>vhd</literal> / <literal>vhdx</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The following protocols can be used for read-only access (RO) to images:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>http</literal>, <literal>https</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>ftp</literal>, <literal>ftps</literal>,
      <literal>tftp</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    When using Xen, the <literal>qed</literal> format will not be displayed
    as a selectable storage in <literal>virt-manager</literal>.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Parameter Unprivileged SG_IO (unpriv_sgio) Is Not Supported</title>
    <para>
     The parameter for unprivileged SG_IO (<literal>unpriv_sgio</literal>)
     depends on non-standard kernel patches that are not included in the
     SLES 12 kernel. Trying to attach a disk using this parameter will
     result in an error.
    </para>
   </note>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  <section id="TechInfo.Kernel">
   <title>Kernel Limits</title>
   <para>
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/server/technical-information/#Kernel"/>
   </para>
   <para>
    This table summarizes the various limits which exist in our recent
    kernels and utilities (if related) for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12.
   </para>
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="4">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3"/>
     <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4"/>
     <thead>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 12 (3.12)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry><emphasis>x86_64</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry><emphasis>s390x</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry><emphasis>ppc64le</emphasis>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         CPU bits
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         max. # Logical CPUs
        </para>
       </entry>
<!-- FATE#316883 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         8192
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256
        </para>
       </entry>
<!-- FATE#315438 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         2048
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         max. RAM (theoretical / certified)
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         &gt; 1 PiB/64 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         10 TiB/256 GiB
        </para>
       </entry>
<!-- FATE#315439 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         1 PiB/64 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         max. user-/kernelspace
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         128 TiB/128 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         φ/φ
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         2 TiB/2 EiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
<!-- bnc#708969 -->
        <para>
         max. swap space
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="c2" nameend="c4">
        <para>
         up to 29 * 64 GB (x86_64) or 30 * 64 GB (other architectures)
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         max. # processes
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="c2" nameend="c4">
        <para>
         1048576
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         max. # threads per process
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="c2" nameend="c4">
        <para>
         Maximum limit depends on memory and other parameters (Tested with
         more than 120000).
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         max. size per block device
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="c2" nameend="c4">
        <para>
         and up to 8 EiB on all 64-bit architectures
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
<!-- bnc#550958 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         FD_SETSIZE
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="c2" nameend="c4">
        <para>
         1024
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para/>
  </section>
  <section id="TechInfo.KVM">
   <title>KVM Limits</title>
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <thead>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 12 GA Virtual Machine (VM)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry><emphasis>Limits</emphasis>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Max VMs per host
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         unlimited (total number of virtual CPUs in all guests being no
         greater than 8 times the number of CPU cores in the host)
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Virtual CPUs per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
<!-- bsc#921171 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         160
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Memory per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         4 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Virtual Block Devices per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         20 virtio-blk, 4 IDE
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of Network Card per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         8
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para>
    Virtual Host Server (VHS) limits are identical to SUSE Linux Enterprise
    Server.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="TechInfo.XEN">
   <title>Xen Limits</title>
   <para>
    Since SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 SP2, we removed the 32-bit
    hypervisor as a virtualization host. 32-bit virtual guests are not
    affected and are fully supported with the provided 64-bit hypervisor.
   </para>
<!-- bnc#732995 -->
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <thead>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 12 GA Virtual Machine (VM)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry><emphasis>Limits</emphasis>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum VMs per host
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Virtual CPUs per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Memory per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         16 GiB x86_32, 511 GiB x86_64
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Max Virtual Block Devices per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         100 PV, 100 FV with PV drivers, 4 FV (Emulated IDE)
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <thead>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 12 GA Virtual Host Server (VHS)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry><emphasis>Limits</emphasis>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Physical CPUs
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Virtual CPUs
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Physical Memory
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         5 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Dom0 Physical Memory
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         500 GiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Block Devices
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         12,000 SCSI logical units
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum iSCSI Devices
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         128
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Network Cards
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         8
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum VMs per CPU Core
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         8
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum VMs per VHS
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Virtual Network Cards
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64 across all VMs in the system
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para>
    In Xen 4.4, the hypervisor bundled with SUSE Linux Enterprise
    Server 12, Dom0 is able to see and handle a maximum of 512 logical
    CPUs. The hypervisor itself, however, can access up to logical 256
    logical CPUs and schedule those for the VMs.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For more information about acronyms please refer to the official
     Virtualization Documentation.
    </para>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PV: Para Virtualization
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      FV: Full Virtualization
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="TechInfo.Filesystems" remap="TechInfo:Filesystems">
   <title>File Systems</title>
   <para>
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/server/technical-information/#FileSystem"/>
   </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316562" remap="TechInfo:Filesystems">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316562" -->
    <title>Protection of Hard Links and Symbolic Links Enabled by Default</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> A long-standing class of security issues are
     time-of-check/time-of-use races of symbolic links and hard links, most
     commonly seen in world-writable directories like
     </emphasis><literal>/tmp</literal><emphasis>. The common method of
     exploitation of this flaw is to cross privilege boundaries when
     following a given symbolic link or hard link. That is, having a root
     process follow a link created by another user. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Additionally, on systems without separated partitions,
     unauthorized users could "pin" vulnerable setuid/setgid files against
     being upgraded by the administrator by creating hard links to them or
     linking to special files.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In <literal>/usr/lib/sysctl.d/50-default.conf</literal>, this behavior
     can now be adjusted using the options
     <literal>fs.protected_hardlinks</literal> and
     <literal>fs.protected_symlinks</literal>:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When set to <literal>0</literal>, links can be followed
       unrestrictedly.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When set to <literal>1</literal>, links are permitted to be followed
       only when outside a sticky world-writable directory matches, or when
       the uid of the link and follower match, or when the directory owner
       matches the link's owner.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     SUSE now sets this to <literal>1</literal> by default.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316463" remap="TechInfo:Filesystems">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Filesystems"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316463" -->
    <title>Btrfs: Compression Support</title>
    <para>
     On-the-fly compression is now supported with Btrfs. It can be turned on
     through mount-time options passed to the filesystem. See the Btrfs
     section in mount(8) manual page for details.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section id="TechInfo.Filesystems.Comparison">
    <title>Comparison of Supported File Systems</title>
    <para>
     SUSE Linux Enterprise was the first enterprise Linux distribution to
     support journaling file systems and logical volume managers back in
     2000. Later we introduced xfs to Linux, which today is seen as the
     primary work horse for large-scale file systems, systems with heavy
     load and multiple parallel read- and write-operations. With SUSE Linux
     Enterprise 12 we are going the next step of innovation and are using
     the Copy on Write file system btrfs as the default for the operating
     system, to support system snapshots and rollback.
    </para>
    <para>
<!-- bnc#903673: use ascii symbols -->
     <quote>+</quote>: supported; <quote>-</quote>: unsupported.
    </para>
    <informaltable frame="all">
     <tgroup cols="6">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
      <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3"/>
      <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4"/>
      <colspec colnum="5" colname="c5"/>
      <colspec colnum="6" colname="c6"/>
      <thead>
       <row rowsep="1">
        <entry><emphasis>Feature</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry><emphasis>Btrfs</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry><emphasis>XFS</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry><emphasis>Ext4</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry><emphasis>Reiserfs</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry><emphasis>OCFS 2 **</emphasis>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Data/Metadata Journaling
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          - / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
        <entry>
         <para>
          - / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          - / +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Journal internal/external
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Offline extend/shrink
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          - / -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Online extend/shrink
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / -
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Inode-Allocation-Map
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          B-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          B+-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          table
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          u. B*-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          table
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Sparse Files
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Tail Packing
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Defrag
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          ExtAttr / ACLs
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Quotas
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Dump/Restore
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          -
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry/>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Blocksize default
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry namest="c2" nameend="c6">
         <para>
          4KiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          max. Filesystemsize [1]
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          8 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 TiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          4 PiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          max. Filesize [1]
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          8 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          4 PiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Support Status
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE HA
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
           
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry namest="c2" nameend="c6">
         <para>
          * Btrfs is copy-on-write file system. Rather than journaling
          changes before writing them in-place, it writes them to a new
          location, then links it in. Until the last write, the new changes
          are not "committed". Due to the nature of the filesystem, quotas
          are implemented based on subvolumes ("qgroups"). The blocksize
          default varies with different host architectures. 64KiB is used on
          ppc64le, 4KiB on most other systems. The actual size used can be
          checked with the command "getconf PAGE_SIZE".
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
           
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry namest="c2" nameend="c6">
         <para>
          ** OCFS2 is fully supported as part of the SUSE Linux Enterprise
          High Availability Extension.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
           
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry namest="c2" nameend="c6">
         <para>
          *** Reiserfs is supported for existing filesystems, the creation
          of new reiserfs file systems is discouraged.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
     The maximum file size above can be larger than the file system's actual
     size due to usage of sparse blocks. Note that unless a file system
     comes with large file support (LFS), the maximum file size on a 32-bit
     system is 2 GB (2^31 bytes). Currently all of our standard file systems
     (including ext3 and ReiserFS) have LFS, which gives a maximum file size
     of 2^63 bytes in theory. The numbers in the above tables assume that
     the file systems are using 4 KiB block size. When using different block
     sizes, the results are different, but 4 KiB reflects the most common
     standard.
    </para>
    <para>
     In this document: 1024 Bytes = 1 KiB; 1024 KiB = 1 MiB; 1024 MiB = 1
     GiB; 1024 GiB = 1 TiB; 1024 TiB = 1 PiB; 1024 PiB = 1 EiB. See also
     <ulink url="http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
<!-- bnc#608543 and bnc#574572 -->
     NFSv4 with IPv6 is only supported for the client side. A NFSv4 server
     with IPv6 is not supported.
    </para>
    <para>
<!-- bnc#606288 -->
     This version of Samba delivers integration with Windows 7 Active
     Directory Domains. In addition we provide the clustered version of
     Samba as part of SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability 11 SP3.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Supported Btrfs Features</title>
    <para>
     The following table lists supported and unsupported Btrfs features
     across multiple SLES versions.
    </para>
    <para>
     <simplelist>
      <member><emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> supported</member>
      <member><emphasis role="bold">–</emphasis> unsupported</member>
     </simplelist>
    </para>
<!-- Table according to bsc#979501, this attachment:
  https://bugzilla.suse.com/attachment.cgi?id=687340 -->
    <informaltable>
     <tgroup cols="4">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="feature" colwidth="32*"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="11SP4" colwidth="17*"/>
      <colspec colnum="3" colname="12GA" colwidth="17*"/>
      <colspec colnum="4" colname="12SP1" colwidth="17*"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
<!-- Remove unsupported OS's. -->
        <entry>Feature</entry>
        <entry>SLES 11 SP4</entry>
        <entry>SLES 12 GA</entry>
        <entry>SLES 12 SP1</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>Copy on Write</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Snapshots/Subvolumes</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Metadata Integrity</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Data Integrity</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Online Metadata Scrubbing</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Automatic Defragmentation</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Manual Defragmentation</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>In-band Deduplication</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Out-of-band Deduplication</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Quota Groups</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Metadata Duplication</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Multiple Devices</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 0</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 1</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 10</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 5</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 6</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Hot Add/Remove</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Device Replace</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Seeding Devices</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Compression</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Big Metadata Blocks</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Skinny Metadata</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Send Without File Data</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Send/Receive</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Inode Cache</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Fallocate with Hole Punch</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
   </section>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- Legal notice copied from SLED release notes, mge@novell.com, 2010-05-07 -->
<!-- Legal notice updated, to smell more like SUSE -->
 <section id="Legal">
  <title>Legal Notices</title>
  <para>
   SUSE makes no representations or warranties with respect to the contents
   or use of this documentation, and specifically disclaims any express or
   implied warranties of merchantability or fitness for any particular
   purpose. Further, SUSE reserves the right to revise this publication and
   to make changes to its content, at any time, without the obligation to
   notify any person or entity of such revisions or changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Further, SUSE makes no representations or warranties with respect to any
   software, and specifically disclaims any express or implied warranties of
   merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose. Further, SUSE
   reserves the right to make changes to any and all parts of SUSE software,
   at any time, without any obligation to notify any person or entity of
   such changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Any products or technical information provided under this Agreement may
   be subject to U.S. export controls and the trade laws of other countries.
   You agree to comply with all export control regulations and to obtain any
   required licenses or classifications to export, re-export, or import
   deliverables. You agree not to export or re-export to entities on the
   current U.S. export exclusion lists or to any embargoed or terrorist
   countries as specified in U.S. export laws. You agree to not use
   deliverables for prohibited nuclear, missile, or chemical/biological
   weaponry end uses. Refer to
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> for more information on
   exporting SUSE software. SUSE assumes no responsibility for your failure
   to obtain any necessary export approvals.
  </para>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?>
   SUSE LLC. This release notes document is licensed under a Creative
   Commons Attribution-NoDerivs 3.0 United States License (CC-BY-ND-3.0 US,
   <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/us/"/>).
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE has intellectual property rights relating to technology embodied in
   the product that is described in this document. In particular, and
   without limitation, these intellectual property rights may include one or
   more of the U.S. patents listed at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> and one or more
   additional patents or pending patent applications in the U.S. and other
   countries.
  </para>
  <para>
   For SUSE trademarks, see SUSE Trademark and Service Mark list
   (<ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/>). All third-party
   trademarks are the property of their respective owners.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Colophon</title>
  <para>
   Thanks for using SUSE Linux Enterprise Server in your business.
  </para>
  <para>
   The SUSE Linux Enterprise Server Team.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
