<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
<?dbsuse-bugtracker url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi"
    product="SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability 12 SP5"
    component="Release Notes"
    assignee="lukas.kucharczyk@suse.com" ?>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension</productname>
  <productnumber>12 SP5</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension is a suite of
    clustering technologies that enable enterprises to implement highly
    available Linux clusters and eliminate single points of failure. This
    document gives an overview of features of SUSE Linux Enterprise High
    Availability Extension and their limitations. Some sections do not apply
    to a particular architecture or product, this is explicitly marked.
   </para>

   <para>
    Manuals can be found in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of the
    installation media, or in the directory
    <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> on the installed system (if
    installed).
   </para>
<!-- vvv FIXME! REMOVE AFTER RELEASE
   <para>
    This product will be released in December 2019.
   </para>
 FIXME! REMOVE AFTER RELEASE -->
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension</title>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension is an affordable,
   integrated suite of robust open source clustering technologies that
   enable enterprises to implement highly available Linux clusters and
   eliminate single points of failure.
  </para>
  <para>
   Used with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, it helps firms maintain business
   continuity, protect data integrity, and reduce unplanned downtime for
   their mission-critical Linux workloads.
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension provides all of the
   essential monitoring, messaging, and cluster resource management
   functionality of proprietary third-party solutions, but at a more
   affordable price, making it accessible to a wider range of enterprises.
  </para>
  <para>
   It is optimized to work with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, and its tight
   integration ensures customers have the most robust, secure, and up to
   date high availability solution. Based on an innovative, highly flexible
   policy engine, it supports a wide range of clustering scenarios.
  </para>
  <para>
   With static or stateless content, the High Availability cluster can be
   used without a cluster file system. This includes web-services with
   static content as well as printing systems or communication systems like
   proxies that do not need to recover data.
  </para>
  <para>
   Finally, its open source license minimizes the risk of vendor lock-in,
   and its adherence to open standards encourages interoperability with
   industry standard tools and technologies.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Intro.New">
  <title>What Is New?</title>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
    Cluster File System
     </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GFS2 cluster file system with read/write support, to complement the
      SUSE recommended OCFS2 cluster file system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Load balancer
     </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      HAProxy as layer 4 load balancer added, to complement the Linux
      virtual server load balancer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
      History Explorer
     </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Hawk history explorer now includes off-line analysis capabilities.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     Resource Agents
     </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Resource agents got multiple updates, including a resource agent to
      handle SCSI reservations
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   Make sure to also review the release notes for the base product, SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP5 which are published at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SUSE-SLES/12-SP5/"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To find out what is new in the Geo clustering option for the SUSE Linux
   Enterprise High Availability Extension 12 SP5, see
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SLE-HA/12-SP5-GEO/"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Support">
  <title>Support Statement for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension 12 SP5</title>
  <para>
   Support requires an appropriate subscription from SUSE. For more
   information, see <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/server/"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   A Geo Clustering for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension
   subscription is needed to receive support and maintenance to run
   geographical clustering scenarios, including manual and automated setups.
  </para>
  <para>
   Support for the DRBD storage replication is independent of the cluster
   scenario and included as part of the SUSE Linux Enterprise High
   Availability Extension product and does not require the addition of a Geo
   Clustering for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension
   subscription.
  </para>
  <para>
   General Support Statement
  </para>
  <para>
   The following definitions apply:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     L1: Installation and problem determination - technical support designed
     to provide compatibility information, installation and configuration
     assistance, usage support, on-going maintenance and basic
     troubleshooting. Level 1 Support is not intended to correct product
     defect errors.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     L2: Reproduction of problem isolation - technical support designed to
     duplicate customer problems, isolate problem areas and potential
     issues, and provide resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1
     Support.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     L3: Code Debugging and problem resolution - technical support designed
     to resolve complex problems by engaging engineering in patch provision,
     resolution of product defects which have been identified by Level 2
     Support.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   SUSE will only support the usage of original (unchanged or not
   recompiled) packages.
  </para>
  <section id="Intro.Support.General" remap="Intro:Support:General">
   <title>Support Information for Specific Packages</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325726" remap="Intro:Support:General">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325726" -->
    <title>softdog Is Now Supported as a Watchdog Service</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> In the past, </emphasis><literal>softdog</literal><emphasis>
     was not supported as a watchdog service because it is a software-based
     watchdog, however, it has proved to be reliable and usable in
     mission-critical HA deployments. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In SLE HA, <literal>softdog</literal> is supported by SUSE for HA
     deployments. However, it is important to notice that some limitations
     still apply. For more information, see the documentation at
     <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha-12/html/SLE-HA-install-quick/index.html#sec-ha-inst-quick-sbd-setup"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Intro.Support.Techpreviews" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews">
  <title>Technology Previews</title>
  <para>
   Technology previews are packages, stacks, or features delivered by SUSE
   which are not supported. They may be functionally incomplete, unstable or
   in other ways not suitable for production use. They are included for your
   convenience and give you a chance to test new technologies within an
   enterprise environment.
  </para>
  <para>
   Whether a technology preview becomes a fully supported technology later
   depends on customer and market feedback. Technology previews can be
   dropped at any time and SUSE does not commit to providing a supported
   version of such technologies in the future.
  </para>
  <para>
   Give your SUSE representative feedback, including your experience and use
   case.
  </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-324044" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324044" -->
   <title>SCSI Locking on Multipath With mpathpersist Resource Agent</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis> In previous versions, the
    </emphasis><literal>sg_persist</literal><emphasis> resource agent only
    deals with the SCSI device directly and could not handle multipath
    devices. </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    As a technology preview, the <literal>mpathpersist</literal> resource
    agent now has a new functionality that allows for HA clusters that have
    a SCSI locking mechanism on top of multipath.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.HA.Resources" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:HA:Resources">
  <title>Resources and Resource Agents</title>
  <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-326697" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:HA:Resources">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326697" -->
   <title>The aws-vpc-ip-move Resource Agent is now available upstream and is provided by the resource-agents package</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis> The </emphasis><literal>aws-vpc-ip-move</literal><emphasis>
    resource agent was originally created by SUSE and has been maintained
    internally while we worked to integrate it into the ClusterLabs project.
    As ClusterLabs has accepted the contribution, SUSE will maintain and
    ship the upstream version. </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    The contents of the package <literal>aws-vpc-ip-move</literal> were
    merged into the <literal>resource-agents</literal> packages, and a
    symbolic link was provided for the old SUSE-specific resource agent
    location to guarantee backward compatibility. During upgrade, the
    <literal>aws-vpc-ip-move</literal> package will be uninstalled and the
    <literal>resource-agents</literal> package will be installed to provide
    the latest version of the same resource agent.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the new version of the <literal>aws-vpc-ip-move</literal> resource
    agent, the parameter <literal>address</literal> has been renamed to
    <literal>ip</literal>. For compatibility, the parameter
    <literal>address</literal> is still available but deprecated. Therefore,
    we recommend adjusting your configuration to use the new parameter name
    <literal>ip</literal>.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="Miscellaneous">
  <title>Miscellaneous</title>
  <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-327929" remap="Miscellaneous">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327929" -->
   <title>fence_vmware_soap has been replaced with fence_vmware_rest</title>
   <para>
    The fence agent for VMWare over SOAP API (<literal>fence_vmware_soap</literal>) is no longer available in SLE HA.
    Use the fence agent for VMware REST API (<literal>fence_vmware_rest</literal>) instead.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="Sourcecode">
  <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
<!-- msvec and legal (ciaran), 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location as the first chapter -->
  <para>
   This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
   General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the source
   code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material. The source code is
   available for download at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. Also,
   for up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
   request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Requests should be
   sent by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/> or as
   otherwise instructed at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. SUSE
   may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Feedback">
<!-- bnc#826887 -->
  <title>More Information and Feedback</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Read the READMEs on the CDs.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get detailed changelog information about a particular package from the
     RPM (where <replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable> is the name of the RPM):
    </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp <replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable>.rpm</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of CD1
     for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of
     first medium of the SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension
     media. This directory includes a PDF version of the High Availability
     Guide.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha-12/"/> contains
     additional or updated documentation for SUSE Linux Enterprise High
     Availability Extension 12 SP5.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Visit <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/"/> for the latest
     product news from SUSE and
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/> for
     additional information on the source code of SUSE Linux Enterprise
     products.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?>
   SUSE LLC.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
