<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
<?dbsuse-bugtracker url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi"
   product="SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4"
   component="Release Notes"
   assignee="sknorr@suse.com" ?>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname><phrase os="sles">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</phrase></productname>
  <productnumber>12 SP4</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
<!-- msvec and marketing, 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- new initial para -->
   <para>
    This document provides guidance and an overview to high level general
    features and updates for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4. Besides
    architecture or product-specific information, it also describes the
    capabilities and limitations of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4.
   </para>

   <para>
    General documentation can be found at:
    <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/12-SP4/"/>.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="rn.about">
  <title>About the Release Notes</title>
  <para>
   These Release Notes are identical across all architectures, and the most
   recent version is always available online at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>.
  </para>
<!-- partly: msvec and marketing, 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to before 'mustread' section... -->
<!-- moved to beginning of document again, because we now have an
  explanatory section. - sknorr-l, 2017-05-18 -->
  <para>
   Some entries may be listed twice, if they are important and belong to
   more than one section.
  </para>
  <para>
   Release notes usually only list changes that happened between two
   subsequent releases. Certain important entries from the release notes
   documents of previous product versions are repeated. To make these
   entries easier to identify, they contain a note to that effect.
  </para>
  <para>
   However, repeated entries are provided as a courtesy only. Therefore, if
   you are skipping one or more service packs, check the release notes of
   the skipped service packs as well. If you are only reading the release
   notes of the current release, you could miss important changes.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</title>
  <remark> SLE definition: general information </remark>
<!-- Marketing, Kerry Kim, 2009-02-09 -->
<!-- Changed by MgE, 2012-02-02 -->
<!-- Feedback by Robert, 2012-02-27 -->
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is a highly reliable, scalable, and secure
   server operating system, built to power mission-critical workloads in
   both physical and virtual environments. It is an affordable,
   interoperable, and manageable open source foundation. With it,
   enterprises can cost-effectively deliver core business services, enable
   secure networks, and simplify the management of their heterogeneous IT
   infrastructure, maximizing efficiency and value.
  </para>
  <para>
   The only enterprise Linux recommended by Microsoft and SAP, SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server is optimized to deliver high-performance
   mission-critical services, as well as edge of network, and web
   infrastructure workloads.
  </para>
  <section id="Intro.Interoperability">
   <title>Interoperability and Hardware Support</title>
   <para>
    Designed for interoperability, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server integrates
    into classical Unix as well as Windows environments, supports open
    standard interfaces for systems management, and has been certified for
    IPv6 compatibility.
   </para>
   <para>
    This modular, general purpose operating system runs on four processor
    architectures and is available with optional extensions that provide
    advanced capabilities for tasks such as real time computing and high
    availability clustering.
   </para>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is optimized to run as a high performing
    guest on leading hypervisors and supports an unlimited number of virtual
    machines per physical system with a single subscription, making it the
    perfect guest operating system for virtual computing.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Lifecycle">
   <title>Support and Life Cycle</title>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is backed by award-winning support from
    SUSE, an established technology leader with a proven history of
    delivering enterprise-quality support services.
   </para>
<!-- bnc#821338, bnc#828478, bnc#882262 -->
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 has a 13-year life cycle, with 10 years
    of General Support and 3 years of Extended Support. The current version
    (SP4) will be fully maintained and supported until 6 months after the
    release of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP5.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you need additional time to design, validate and test your upgrade
    plans, Long Term Service Pack Support can extend the support you get an
    additional 12 to 36 months in twelve month increments, providing a total
    of 3 to 5 years of support on any given service pack.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, check our Support Policy page
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/policy.html"/> or the Long Term
    Service Pack Support Page
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/programs/long-term-service-pack-support.html"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.New" remap="Intro:New">
   <title>What Is New?</title>
   <remark> Marketing POV. </remark>
   <remark> ** Update information : link to severity ratings documentation ** Installation : change,
    new kernel, compatibility ** features : features description (not technical) ** System update :
    link to the documentation (not just the tittle) ** Update related notes : specific change to
    focus on.
    BNC#898123
   </remark>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 introduces many innovative changes
    compared to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11. Here are some of the
    highlights:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Robustness on administrative errors and improved management
      capabilities with full system rollback based on Btrfs as the default
      file system for the operating system partition and the Snapper
      technology of SUSE.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      An overhaul of the installer introduces a new workflow that allows you
      to register your system and receive all available maintenance updates
      as part of the installation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Server Modules offer a choice of supplemental
      packages, ranging from tools for Web Development and Scripting,
      through a Cloud Management module, all the way to a sneak preview of
      upcoming management tooling called Advanced Systems Management.
      Modules are part of your SUSE Linux Enterprise Server subscription,
      are technically delivered as online repositories, and differ from the
      base of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server only by their life cycle. For
      more information about modules, see <xref linkend="Intro.Module"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      New core technologies like systemd (replacing the time-honored System
      V-based init process) and Wicked (introducing a modern, dynamic
      network configuration infrastructure).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The open-source database system MariaDB is fully supported now.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Support for open-vm-tools together with VMware for better integration
      into VMware-based hypervisor environments.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Linux Containers are integrated into the virtualization management
      infrastructure (libvirt). Docker is provided as a fully supported
      technology. For more details, see
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/promo/sle/docker/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Support for the AArch64 architecture (64-bit ARMv8) and the 64-bit
      Little-Endian variant of the IBM POWER architecture. Additionally, we
      continue to support the Intel 64/AMD64 and IBM Z architectures.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GNOME 3.20 gives users a modern desktop environment with a choice of
      several different look and feel options, including a special
      <emphasis>SUSE Linux Enterprise Classic</emphasis> mode for easier
      migration from earlier SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop environments.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For users wishing to use the full range of productivity applications
      of a Desktop with their SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, we are now
      offering SUSE Linux Enterprise Workstation Extension (requires a SUSE
      Linux Enterprise Desktop subscription).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Integration with the new SUSE Customer Center, the new central web
      portal from SUSE to manage Subscriptions, Entitlements, and provide
      access to Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!-- FATE#312947 -->
   <remark> This is Read Me First information. </remark>
   <para>
    If you are upgrading from a previous SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
    release, you should review at least the following sections:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="Intro.Support"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="InstUpgrade.Upgrade"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="TechInfo"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326969" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326969" -->
    <title>NV-DIMM Support</title>
    <para>
     SLES 12-SP4 / SLES15 supports persistent memory (NV-DIMM) technologies,
     such as Intel AEP, on certified hardware and for certified ISV
     applications, specifically in memory databases, in cooperation with
     SUSE's hardware and software partners.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Documentation">
   <title>Documentation and Other Information</title>
   <para/>
   <section>
    <title>Available on the Product Media</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Read the READMEs on the media.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Get the detailed change log information about a particular package
       from the RPM (where <filename>&lt;FILENAME&gt;.rpm</filename> is the
       name of the RPM):
      </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp &lt;FILENAME&gt;.rpm</screen>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
       media for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated
       packages.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of
       the media of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4. This directory
       includes PDF versions of the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4
       Installation Quick Start and Deployment Guides. Documentation (if
       installed) is available below the
       <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> directory of an installed
       system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Externally Provided Documentation</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/12-SP4/"/> contains
       additional or updated documentation for SUSE Linux Enterprise
       Server 12 SP4.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find a collection of White Papers in the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
       Resource Library at
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/server/resource-library"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Sourcecode">
   <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
<!-- msvec and legal (ciaran), 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location as the first section -->
   <para>
    This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
    General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the
    source code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material. The source
    code is available for download at
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>.
    Also, for up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
    request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Requests should be
    sent by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/> or
    as otherwise instructed at
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. SUSE
    may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</title>
   <para>
    To receive support, you need an appropriate subscription with SUSE. For
    more information, see
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/server/services-and-support/"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The following definitions apply:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
<!-- Now using http://support.novell.com/products/server/supported_packages/
  -->
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L1</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem determination, which means technical support designed to
       provide compatibility information, usage support, ongoing
       maintenance, information gathering and basic troubleshooting using
       available documentation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L2</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem isolation, which means technical support designed to analyze
       data, reproduce customer problems, isolate problem area and provide a
       resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1 or alternatively
       prepare for Level 3.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L3</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem resolution, which means technical support designed to resolve
       problems by engaging engineering to resolve product defects which
       have been identified by Level 2 Support.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    For contracted customers and partners, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
    SP4 and its Modules are delivered with L3 support for all packages,
    except the following:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Technology Previews
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      sound, graphics, fonts and artwork
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      packages that require an additional customer contract, see
      <xref linkend="Intro.Support.External"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      packages provided as part of the Software Development Kit (SDK)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    SUSE will only support the usage of original (that is, unchanged and
    un-recompiled) packages.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Support.General">
   <title>General Support</title>
   <para>
    To learn about supported kernel, virtualization, and file system
    features, as well as supported Java versions, see
    <xref linkend="TechInfo"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
<!-- see fate#316990 -->
  <section id="Intro.Support.External" remap="Intro:Support:External">
   <title>Software Requiring Specific Contracts</title>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316990" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Software Requiring Specific Contracts</title -->
   <para>
    The following packages require additional support contracts to be
    obtained by the customer in order to receive full support:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PostgreSQL Database
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      LibreOffice
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Support.Techpreviews.Overview">
   <title>Technology Previews</title>
   <remark> ** clear statement of TP (no support) ** Title of the TP ** full description of the TP
    ** link to official documentation (external) ** link to SUSE's documentation </remark>
<!-- bnc#662712 -->
   <para>
    Technology previews are packages, stacks, or features delivered by SUSE
    which are not supported. They may be functionally incomplete, unstable
    or in other ways not suitable for production use. They are included for
    your convenience and give you a chance to test new technologies within
    an enterprise environment.
   </para>
   <para>
    Whether a technology preview becomes a fully supported technology later
    depends on customer and market feedback. Technology previews can be
    dropped at any time and SUSE does not commit to providing a supported
    version of such technologies in the future.
   </para>
   <para>
    Give your SUSE representative feedback, including your experience and
    use case.
   </para>
   <section id="Intro.Support.Techpreviews.x86_64" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews:x86_64">
    <title>Technology Previews for AMD64/Intel 64 64-Bit (x86_64)</title>
    <para/>
    <section role="notoc" id="jsc-SLE-11270">
     <title>KVM Nested Virtualization</title>
     <para>
      KVM Nested Virtualization is available in SLE 12 SP4 as a technology
      preview. For more information, see
      <ulink
      url="https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/latest/virt/kvm/nested-vmx.html">the
      Linux kernel documentation</ulink>.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-325555" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews:x86_64">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325555" -->
     <title>Support for AMD Secure Encrypted Virtualization</title>
     <para>
      As a technology preview, SLE 12 SP4 now supports AMD Secure Encrypted
      Virtualization (SEV). SEV integrates main memory encryption
      capabilities (SME) with the existing AMD-V virtualization architecture
      to support encrypted virtual machines. Encrypting virtual machines
      helps protect them from physical threats and other virtual machines or
      even the hypervisor itself. SEV represents a new approach to security
      that is particularly suited to cloud computing where virtual machines
      need not fully trust the hypervisor and administrator of their host
      system. As with SME, no application software modifications are
      required to support SEV.
     </para>
     <para>
      See also <xref linkend="fate-325554"/>
<!--the note about SME-->
      .
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.ModuleExtensionRelated">
   <title>Modules, Extensions, and Related Products</title>
   <para>
    This section comprises information about modules and extensions for SUSE
    Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4. Modules and extensions add parts or
    functionality to the system.
   </para>
   <section id="Intro.Module">
    <title>Available Modules</title>
    <para>
     Modules are fully supported parts of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server with
     a different life cycle and update timeline. They are a set of packages,
     have a clearly defined scope and are delivered via an online channel
     only. Release notes for modules are contained in this document.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following modules are available for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
     SP4:
    </para>
    <informaltable>
     <tgroup cols="3">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="name" colwidth="40*"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="content" colwidth="50*"/>
      <colspec colnum="3" colname="cycle" colwidth="25*"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry>Name</entry>
        <entry>Content</entry>
        <entry>Life Cycle</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>Advanced Systems Management Module</entry>
        <entry>CFEngine, Puppet, Salt and the Machinery tool</entry>
        <entry>Frequent releases</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Containers Module</entry>
        <entry>Docker, tools, prepackaged images</entry>
        <entry>Frequent releases</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>HPC Module</entry>
        <entry>Tools and libraries related to High Performance Computing (HPC)</entry>
        <entry>Frequent releases</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Legacy Module<emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry><literal>ksh</literal>
        </entry>
        <entry>No updates, supported through March 2022</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Public Cloud Module</entry>
        <entry>Public cloud initialization code and tools</entry>
        <entry>Frequent releases</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>SUSE Cloud Application Platform Tools</entry>
        <entry>Tools to interact with the SUSE Cloud Application Platform 1.0 </entry>
        <entry>Frequent releases</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Toolchain Module</entry>
        <entry>GNU Compiler Collection (GCC)</entry>
        <entry>Yearly delivery</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Web and Scripting Module</entry>
        <entry>PHP, Python, Ruby on Rails</entry>
        <entry>3 years, ~18 months overlap</entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis> Module is not available for the
     AArch64 architecture.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information about the life cycle of packages contained in
     modules, see
     <ulink url="https://scc.suse.com/docs/lifecycle/sle/12/modules"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section id="Intro.Extension">
    <title>Available Extensions</title>
    <para>
     Extensions add extra functionality to the system and require their own
     registration key, usually at additional cost. Extensions are delivered
     via an online channel or physical media. In many cases, extensions have
     their own release notes documents that are available from
     <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following extensions are available for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
     12 SP4:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Linux Enterprise Live Patching:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/live-patching"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/highavailability"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Geo Clustering for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/highavailability/geo-clustering"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Linux Enterprise Real Time:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/realtime"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Linux Enterprise Workstation Extension:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/workstation-extension"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Additionally, there are the following extensions which are not covered
     by SUSE support agreements, available at no additional cost and without
     an extra registration key:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Package Hub: <ulink url="https://packagehub.suse.com/"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Linux Enterprise Software Development Kit
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section id="Intro.Derived_Products">
    <title>Derived and Related Products</title>
    <remark> Marketing POV. </remark>
    <para>
     This sections lists derived and related products. In many cases, these
     products have their own release notes documents that are available from
     <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Enterprise Storage:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-enterprise-storage"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/desktop"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE Manager:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-manager"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SUSE OpenStack Cloud:
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-openstack-cloud"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Certification">
   <title>Security, Standards, and Certification</title>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 has been submitted to the
    certification bodies for:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/">Common Criteria
      Certification</ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      FIPS 140-2 validation, see:
      <ulink url="http://csrc.nist.gov/groups/STM/cmvp/documents/140-1/140InProcess.pdf"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For more information about certification, see
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/certificates.html"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- ============================================================== -->
<!-- =============== Technical Part Starts Here =================== -->
<!-- ============================================================== -->
 <section id="InstUpgrade">
  <title>Installation and Upgrade</title>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server can be deployed in several ways:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Physical machine
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Virtual host
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Virtual machine
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     System containers
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Application containers
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <section id="InstUpgrade.Upgrade" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
   <title>Upgrade-Related Notes</title>
   <para>
    This section includes upgrade-related information for SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server 12 SP4. For information about general preparations and
    supported upgrade methods and paths, see the documentation at
    <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/12-SP4/html/SLES-all/cha-update-sle.html"/>.
   </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326970" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
<!-- sort_key="1"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326970" -->
    <title>Upgrading to PostgreSQL 10</title>
    <para>
     If you are using PostgreSQL, make sure to upgrade to PostgreSQL 10
     before upgrading to SLES 12 SP4. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="fate-325659"/>
<!--the section about PostgreSQL-->
     .
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326567" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326567" -->
    <title>Product Registration Changes for HPC Customers</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>For SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, there was a High Performance
     Computing subscription named "SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for HPC"
     (SLES for HPC). With SLE 15, this subscription does not exist anymore
     and has been replaced. The equivalent subscription is named "SUSE Linux
     Enterprise High Performance Computing" (SLE-HPC) and requires a
     different license key. Because of this requirement, a SLES for HPC 12
     system will by default upgrade to a regular "SUSE Linux Enterprise
     Server".</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     To properly upgrade a SLES for HPC system to a SLE-HPC, the system
     needs to be converted to SLE-HPC first. SUSE provides a tool to
     simplify this conversion by performing the product conversion and
     switch to the SLE-HPC subscription. However, the tool does not perform
     the upgrade itself.
    </para>
    <para>
     When run without extra parameters, the script assumes that the SLES for
     HPC subscription is valid and not expired. If the subscription has
     expired, you need to provide a valid registration key for SLE-HPC.
    </para>
    <para>
     The script reads the current set of registered modules and extensions
     and after the system has been converted to SLE-HPC, it tries to add
     them again.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Providing a Registration Key to the Conversion Script</title>
     <para>
      The script cannot restore the previous registration state if the
      supplied registration key is incorrect or invalid.
     </para>
    </important>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To install the script, run <literal>zypper in
       switch_sles_sle-hpc</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Execute the script from the command line as <literal>root</literal>:
      </para>
<screen>switch_sles_sle-hpc -e &lt;REGISTRATION_EMAIL&gt; -r &lt;NEW_REGISTRATION_KEY&gt;</screen>
      <para>
       The parameters <literal>-e</literal> and <literal>-r</literal> are
       only required if the previous registration has expired, otherwise
       they are optional. To run the script in batch mode, add the option
       <literal>-y</literal>. It answers all questions with
       <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     For more information, see the man page
     <literal>switch_sles_sle-hpc(8)</literal> and
     <literal>README.SUSE</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>For More Information</title>
   <para>
    For more information, see
    <xref linkend="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent"/> and the sections
    relating to your respective hardware architecture.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- Arch Independent -->
 <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent">
  <title>Architecture Independent Information</title>
  <remark> This is highly technical * Know issues categorized ** full description of the problem **
   how to reproduce the issue ** link to Bugzilla number ** command line change/configuration change
   ** work around if available
  </remark>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to all architectures supported by
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4.
  </para>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Development">
   <title>Development</title>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326788">
    <title><package>librdkafka</package> Has Been Added</title>
    <para>
     <package>librdkafka</package> version 0.11.6 has been added.
     <package>librdkafka</package> is a C library implementation of the Apache
     Kafka protocol, providing Producer, Consumer and Admin clients. It was
     designed with message delivery reliability and high performance in mind.
     For more information, see <ulink
     url="https://github.com/edenhill/librdkafka"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Kernel" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
   <title>Kernel</title>
   <para/>
   <section role="notoc" id="jsc-SLE-22593">
    <title>Unprivileged eBPF usage has been disabled</title>
    <para>
      A large amount of security issues was found and fixed in the Extended
      Berkeley Packet Filter (eBPF) code. To reduce the attack surface, its
      usage has been restricted to privileged users only.
    </para>
    <para>
     Privileged users include <literal>root</literal>. Programs with the
     <literal>CAP_BPF</literal> capability in the newer versions of the Linux
     kernel can still use eBPF as-is.
    </para>
    <para>
     To check the privileged state, you can check the value of the
     <literal>/proc/sys/kernel/unprivileged_bpf_disabled</literal>
     parameter. Value of 0 means "unprivileged enable", and value of 2 means
     "only privileged users enabled".
    </para>
    <para>
     This setting can be changed by the <literal>root</literal> user:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       to enable it temporarily for all users by running the command
       <literal>sysctl kernel.unprivileged_bpf_disabled=0</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       to enable it permanently by adding
       <literal>kernel.unprivileged_bpf_disabled=0</literal>
       to the
       <literal>/etc/sysctl.conf</literal>
       file.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325647" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325647" -->
    <title>Support for SAP HANA Workloads on Intel Optane DC Memory</title>
    <para>
     SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 and SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
     for SAP Applications 12 SP4 add support for Intel Optane DC memory.
     This enables SAP workloads, such as SAP HANA to benefit from persistent
     memory in the future to shorten start times of the system and provide
     better overall system stability. Currently, configurations up to 12 TB
     of NVDIMMs plus 3 TB of regular DIMMS of supported memory and 4 socket
     machines have been tested. Additional configurations will be tested
     over time.
    </para>
    <para>
     From a file system perspective, the XFS file system is supported for
     the NVDIMMs, with SAP HANA running in DAX mode. SUSE intends to keep
     the leading position as technology provider, working closely with SAP
     on future developments.
    </para>
    <para>
     If there are <literal>pmem</literal> namespaces, these need to be
     destroyed before the installation. To mount persistent memory directly
     on boot, we recommend adding the <literal>nofail</literal> mount option
     in <literal>/etc/fstab</literal> as it can take a long time for the
     <literal>/dev/pmem</literal> devices to become usable.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example:
    </para>
<screen>/dev/pmem0    /mnt/pmem0    xfs    dax,nofail    0  0
/dev/pmem1    /mnt/pmem1    xfs    dax,nofail    0  0</screen>
    <para>
     Namespaces need to be created individually. That means, you need to
     execute the following command for each namespace you want to create:
    </para>
<screen>ndctl create-namespace --mode=fsdax --map=dev</screen>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325368" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325368" -->
    <title>Device Error Prevention Enabled (CONFIG_IO_STRICT_DEVMEM)</title>
    <para>
     The kernel build option <literal>CONFIG_IO_STRICT_DEVMEM</literal> has
     been enabled in the SLE kernel to prevent device errors. This option
     disables tampering with device state while a kernel driver is using the
     device.
    </para>
    <para>
     Unfortunately, some vendor tools currently use such functionality. If
     you depend on such a tool, make sure to set the kernel boot parameter
     <literal>iomem=relaxed</literal>. Among others, this affects several
     firmware flash tools for POWER9 machines.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Security" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
   <title>Security</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326412" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326412" -->
    <title>Support for YubiKey and Nitrokey using the U2F frameworks.</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Some applications require stronger authentication methods,
     including second factor authentication using physical
     tokens.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Support for YubiKey and Nitrokey is now shipped in the form of
     libraries, PAM modules and CLI and UI utilities.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325802" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325802" -->
    <title>su Does Not Preserve the Value of PATH</title>
    <para>
     For security reasons, the <literal>su</literal> command does not
     preserve the value of the environment variable <literal>PATH</literal>
     any more by default. To return to the behavior from SLE 12, open the
     file <literal>/etc/default/su</literal> and change the option
     <literal>ALWAYS_SET_PATH</literal> to <literal>no</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325336" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325336" -->
    <title>Support for TLS 1.3 in OpenSSL 1.1.1</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>TLS 1.3 is a new version of the Transport Layer Security
     protocol with some major differences and improvements over the
     established TLS 1.2. This new protocol version is only available in
     OpenSSL 1.1.1 or later. This new version is not binary-compatible with
     the default version of OpenSSL in SLE 12 SP4 (OpenSSL 1.0), and has
     known differences in the API that require making adjustments before
     applications can benefit from the changes.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     OpenSSL 1.1.1 with support for TLSv1.3 is shipped as an option. In SLE
     12 SP4, the libraries can be loaded into the same binary image along
     with OpenSSL 1.0 with symbol versioning enabled. To take advantage of
     this new protocol option, applications need to be built with OpenSSL
     1.1.1 explicitly.
    </para>
    <para>
     OpenSSL 1.0 remains the default for system libraries, services and
     tools.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Network" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
   <title>Networking</title>
   <para/>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325525">
    <title>NFS Client Support For NFSv4.2 Has Been Enabled</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>CONFIG_NFS_V4_2</literal> configuration option has been enabled.
     This option enables support for minor version 2 of the NFSv4 protocol in the kernel's NFS client.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326795" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326795" -->
    <title>Intel* Omni-Path Architecture (OPA) host software</title>
    <para>
     Intel Omni-Path Architecture (OPA) host software is fully supported in
     SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4. Intel OPA provides Host Fabric
     Interface (HFI) hardware with initialization and setup for high
     performance data transfers (high bandwidth, high message rate, low
     latency) between compute and I/O nodes in a clustered environment.
    </para>
    <para>
     For information about installing Intel Omni-Path Architecture
     documentation, see the documentation from Intel at
     <ulink url="https://www.intel.com/content/dam/support/us/en/documents/network-and-i-o/fabric-products/Intel_OP_Software_SLES_12_4_RN_K34561.pdf"/>
     (link may not yet be active during the prerelease phase of SLES 12
     SP4).
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->

   <section role="notoc" id="jsc-SLE-11183">
    <title>New GeoIP Database Sources</title>
    <para>
     The GeoIP databases allow approximately geo-locating users by their IP
     address.
     In the past, the company MaxMind made such data available for free in
     its GeoLite Legacy databases.
     On January 2, 2019, MaxMind discontinued the GeoLite Legacy databases,
     now offering only the newer GeoLite2 databases for download.
     To comply with new data protection regulation, since December 30, 2019,
     GeoLite2 database users are required to comply with an additional usage
     license.
     This change means users now need to register for a MaxMind account and
     obtain a license key to download GeoLite2 databases.
     For more information about these changes, see the
     <ulink url="https://blog.maxmind.com/2019/12/18/significant-changes-to-accessing-and-using-geolite2-databases/">MaxMind blog</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
     SLES includes the <package>GeoIP</package> package of tools that are only compatible with
     GeoLite Legacy databases.
     As an update for SLES 12 SP4, we introduce the following new
     packages to deal with the changes to the GeoLite service:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>geoipupdate</command>:
       The official Maxmind tool for downloading GeoLite2 databases.
       To use this tool, set up the configuration file with your MaxMind
       account details.
       This configuration file can also be generated on the Maxmind web page.
       For more information, see
       <ulink url="https://dev.maxmind.com/geoip/geoip2/geolite2/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>geolite2legacy</command>:
       A script for converting GeoLite2 CSV data to the GeoLite Legacy format.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>geoipupdate-legacy</command>:
       A convenience script that downloads GeoLite2 data, converts it to the
       GeoLite Legacy format, and stores it in <filename>/var/lib/GeoIP</filename>.
       With this script, applications developed for use with the legacy
       <command>geoip-fetch</command> tool will continue to work.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>

  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.SystemsManagement" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
   <title>Systems Management</title>
   <para/>
   <section role="notoc" id="jsc-SLE-12830">
    <title>Salt Has Been Updated to Version 3000</title>
    <para>
     Salt has been upgraded to upstream version 3000, plus a number of
     patches, backports and enhancements by SUSE. In particular,
     CVE-2020-11651 and CVE-2020-11652 fixes are included in our release.
    </para>
    <para>
     As part of this upgrade, cryptography is now managed by the
     Python-M2Crypto library (which is itself based on the well-known OpenSSL
     library).
    </para>
    <para>
     We intend to regularly upgrade Salt to more recent versions.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more details about changes in your manually-created Salt states, see
     the <ulink url="https://docs.saltstack.com/en/latest/topics/releases/3000.html">Salt 3000 upstream release notes</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Salt 3000 is the last version of Salt which will support the old syntax
     of the <literal>cmd.run</literal> module.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-323175" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323175" -->
    <title>The YaST Module for SSH Server Configuration Has Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The YaST module for configuring an SSH server which was
     present in SLE 11, is not a part of SLE 12. It does not have any direct
     successor.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The module <emphasis>SSH Server</emphasis> only supported configuring a
     small subset of all SSH server capabilities. Therefore, the
     functionality of the module can be replaced by using a combination of 2
     YaST modules: The <emphasis>/etc/sysconfig Editor</emphasis> and the
     <emphasis>Services Manager</emphasis>. This also applies to system
     configuration via AutoYaST.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Storage" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
   <title>Storage</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-327156" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327156" -->
    <title>NVMe Multipath Handling</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The default state for multipath of NVMe differs for SUSE
     Linux Enterprise 12 and 15.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>In SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, multipath is off by default. In
     SUSE Linux Enterprise 15, multipath is on by default.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     If the new default behavior does not work in your case, you can
     override it with the kernel command-line option
     <literal>LIBSTORAGE_MULTIPATH_AUTOSTART=ON</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     With multipath activated, the device numbering is independent of
     physical slots.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
</section>
<section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Misc">
<title>Miscellaneous</title>
<section role="notoc" id="jsc-SLE-24988" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Misc">
 <title>Enriched system visibility in the SUSE Customer Center (SCC)</title>
 <para>
  SUSE is committed to helping provide better insights into the consumption
  of SUSE subscriptions regardless of where they are running or how they
  are managed; physical or virtual, on-prem or in the cloud, connected to SCC
  or Repository Mirroring Tool (RMT), or managed by SUSE Manager. To help you identify or filter out
  systems in SCC that are no longer running or decommissioned, SUSEConnect
  now features a daily “ping”, which will update system information
  automatically.
 </para>
 <para>
  For more details see the documentation at <ulink url="https://susedoc.github.io/doc-unversioned/main/single-html/SLE-suseconnect-tracking/" />.
 </para>
</section>
</section>
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.x86_64" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64">
  <title>AMD64/Intel 64 (x86_64) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to the version of SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server 12 SP4 for the AMD64/Intel 64 architectures.
  </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325554" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325554" -->
   <title>Support for AMD Memory Encryption</title>
   <para>
    To provide protection against physical attacks on a system, AMD SME can
    provide full or partial memory encryption depending on the use case, on
    AMD family 17h CPU processors. Full memory encryption means all DRAM
    contents are encrypted using random keys. This provides strong
    protection against cold boot, DRAM interface snooping and similar types
    of attacks. This technology is especially prominent for systems equipped
    with NVDIMMs whose contents remain intact after powering down the
    system.
   </para>
   <para>
    Memory encryption support is present in SLE 15 kernels but not enabled
    by default. To enable it on compatible hardware (AMD family 17h CPU,
    with proper BIOS/UEFI support), supply the boot option
    <literal>mem_encrypt=on</literal>.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  <section id="InfraPackArch.x86_64.System" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64:System">
   <title>System and Vendor Specific Information</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-327794" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64:System">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327794" -->
    <title>Intel Optane DC Persistent Memory Operating Modes</title>
    <para>
     With SLE 15 SP1, Intel Optane DIMMs can be used in different modes on
     YES-certified platforms:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In App Direct Mode, the Intel Optane memory is used as fast
       persistent storage, an alternative to SSDs and NVMe devices. Data is
       persistent: It is kept when the system is powered off.
      </para>
      <para>
       App Direct Mode has been supported since SLE 12 SP4.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In Memory Mode, the Intel Optane memory serves as a cost-effective,
       high-capacity alternative to DRAM. In this mode, separate DRAM DIMMs
       act as a cache for the most frequently-accessed data while the Optane
       DIMMs memory provide large memory capacity. However, compared with
       DRAM-only systems, this mode is slower under random access workloads.
       If you run applications without Optane-specific enhancements that
       take advantage of this mode, memory performance may decrease. Data is
       <emphasis>not</emphasis> persistent: It is lost when the system is
       powered off.
      </para>
      <para>
       Memory Mode has been supported since SLE 15 SP1
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In Mixed Mode, the Intel Optane memory is partitioned, so it can
       serve in both modes simultaneously.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mixed Mode has been supported since SLE 15 SP1.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Not all certified platforms support all modes mentioned
     above.</emphasis> Direct hardware-related questions at your hardware
     partner. SUSE works with all major hardware vendors to make use of
     Intel Optane a perfect experience on the OS- and open-source
     infrastructure level.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-324726" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64:System">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="TPM/TCG"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324726" -->
    <title>TPM 2.0 Software Stack Has Been Updated</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The upstream projects for Intel's TPM 2.0 Software Stack have
     introduced major changes to the project structure. Notably, the
     resource manager daemon has been replaced by a new implementation that
     fixes stability and security issues.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The packaging has been adjusted to the upstream changes. The previous
     resource manager daemon, <literal>resourcemgr</literal>, which was
     previously part of the <literal>tpm2-0-tss</literal> package has been
     dropped. The new package <literal>tpm2.0-abrmd</literal> provides the
     new resource manager implementation (<literal>tpm2-abrmd</literal> /
     <literal>tabrmd</literal>).
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.Power" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
  <title>POWER (ppc64le) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to the version of SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server 12 SP4 for the POWER architecture.
  </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-327576" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327576" -->
   <title>Support for ibmvnic Networking Driver</title>
   <para>
    The kernel device driver <literal>ibmvnic</literal> provides support for
    vNIC (virtual Network Interface Controller) which is a PowerVM virtual
    networking technology that delivers enterprise capabilities and
    simplifies network management on IBM POWER systems. It is an efficient
    high-performance technology.
   </para>
   <para>
    When combined with SR-IOV NIC, it provides bandwidth control Quality of
    Service (QoS) capabilities at the virtual NIC level. vNIC significantly
    reduces virtualization overhead resulting in lower latencies and fewer
    server resources (CPU, memory) required for network virtualization.
   </para>
   <para>
    For a detailed support statement of ibmvnic in SLES, see
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/kb/doc/?id=7023703"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325306" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325306" -->
   <title>Reduced Memory Usage When Booting FADump Capture Kernel</title>
   <para>
    One of the primary issues with Firmware Assisted Dump (FADump) on IBM
    POWER systems is that it needs a large amount of memory to be reserved.
    On large systems with terabytes of memory, this reservation can be
    significant.
   </para>
   <para>
    Normally, the preserved memory is filtered to extract only relevant
    areas using the <literal>makedumpfile</literal> tool. While the tool
    allows determining what needs to be part of the dump and what memory to
    filter out, the default is to capture only kernel data and exclude
    everything else.
   </para>
   <para>
    We take advantage of this default and the Linux kernel's Contiguous
    Memory Allocator (CMA) to fundamentally change the memory reservation
    model for FADump: Instead of setting aside a significant chunk of memory
    that cannot otherwise be used, the feature uses CMA instead. It reserves
    a significant chunk of memory that the kernel is prevented from using
    (due to <literal>MIGRATE_CMA</literal>), but applications are free to
    use it. With this, FADump will still be able to accurately capture all
    of the kernel memory and most of the user-space memory except for the
    user pages that are part of the CMA region reserved for FADump.
   </para>
   <para>
    To disable this feature, pass the kernel parameter
    <literal>fadump=nocma</literal> instead of <literal>fadump=on</literal>. This ensures that the memory reserved for FADump is not used by
    applications. This option may be useful in scenarios where you prefer to
    also capture application data in the dump file.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325177" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325177" -->
   <title>SDT Markers in Select Applications and Libraries</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis> SDT markers are static tracepoints included in the source
    code that expose certain information deemed useful by the
    application/library developers for various purposes including debugging
    and performance monitoring. Tools such as
    </emphasis><literal>perf</literal><emphasis> and
    </emphasis><literal>systemtap</literal><emphasis> can be used to record
    data provided at these tracepoints, and for subsequent processing.
    </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    In SLES 12 SP4, certain userspace applications and libraries (for
    example, <literal>glibc</literal>) are built with SDT markers enabled.
    This enhances the serviceability tooling.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-324950" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324950" -->
   <title>Support for POWER9 PMU Events Has Been Added to the perf Tool</title>
   <para>
    When executed on a POWER9 system, the <literal>perf</literal> tool now
    supports listing or specifying POWER9 PMU events by name.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-324949" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324949" -->
   <title>Support for POWER9 24x7 Counters Has Been Added</title>
   <para>
    SLES 12 SP4 adds support for the new version of the hypervisor API which
    is used to access 24x7 performance counters on POWER9 systems.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-321458" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321458" -->
   <title>OProfile Support for POWER9</title>
   <para>
    The OProfile package has been updated to include support for POWER9
    processors.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-321457" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321457" -->
   <title>Support for POWER9 Has Been Added to LibPFM</title>
   <para>
    The LibPFM package has been updated to include support for POWER9
    processors.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-321456" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321456" -->
   <title>Support for POWER9 Has Been Added to PAPI</title>
   <para>
    PAPI package updated to include support for POWER9 processors.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="bsc-1136157">
   <title>Speed of <literal>ibmveth</literal> Interface Not Reported Accurately</title>
   <para>
    The <literal>ibmveth</literal> interface is a paravirtualized interface.
    When communicating between LPARs within the same system, the interface's
    speed is limited only by the system's CPU and memory bandwidth.
    When the virtual Ethernet is bridged to a physical network, the
    interface's speed is limited by the speed of that physical network.
   </para>
   <para>
    Unfortunately, the <literal>ibmveth</literal> driver has no way of
    determining automatically whether it is bridged to a physical network
    and what the speed of that link is.
    <literal>ibmveth</literal> therefore reports its speed as a fixed value
    of 1 Gb/s which in many cases will be inaccurate.
    To determine the actual speed of the interface, use a benchmark.
    Using <command>ethtool</command>, you can then set a more accurate
    displayed speed.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ">
  <title>IBM Z (s390x) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to the version of SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server 12 SP4 for the IBM Z architecture. For more
   information, see
   <ulink url="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/linux390/documentation_suse.html"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   IBM zEnterprise 196 (z196) and IBM zEnterprise 114 (z114) are in the
   following referred to as z196 and z114.
  </para>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Hardware" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Hardware">
   <title>Hardware</title>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
<!-- sort_key="1"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324089" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]IBM z14 and Additional z13 Hardware Instructions in GLIBC</title -->
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The addition of IBM z14 hardware instructions and an expanded set of
      IBM z13 hardware instructions in glibc enables improved performance
      and hardware support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The LLVM compiler supports IBM z14 instructions for improved
      performance.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      OpenSSL (1.1), <literal>ibmca</literal>, and
      <literal>libica</literal> support IBM z14 instructions for
      AES-GCM-based encryption of data in flight.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      KVM guests can now use CPU features, including CPACF functions, that
      were introduced with IBM z14.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With z14, the hardware provides an indication of the configuration
      level of SIE, for example LPAR or KVM. IBM z14 sample configurations
      help to analyze and optimize KVM performance.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>libica</literal> supports hardware acceleration for the SHA3
      algorithm (CPACF MSA6) using CPACF hardware in IBM z14 machines.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      CPU-MF Hardware Counters are added for IBM z13 and z13s. You can now
      access counters from the MT-diagnostic counter set that is available
      with IBM z13. You can also specify z13 specific counters using their
      symbolic event names and obtain counter descriptions with the lscpumf
      utility.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Support for the True Random Number Generator (TRNG, CPACF MSA7) in IBM
      z14 machines via CPACF. This improves the availability of random data
      in the kernel entropy pool.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!-- sort_key="2"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325014" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Support for IBM z14 Instructions in LLVM</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325018" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]AES_GCM Encryption Enhancements in openssl, ibmca and libica</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325013" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]CPU Model for IBM z14</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325011" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]CPUMF Basic Sample Configuration Level Indication</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324999" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Support for SHA3 Algorithm Hardware Acceleration in libica</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Linux Kernel"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324995" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Add CPU_MF Hardware Counters for IBM z13/z13s</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324104" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Support for True Random Number Generator (TRNG)</title -->
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Virtualization" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
   <title>Virtualization</title>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
<!-- sort_key="1"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325874" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]KVM: CPU Model z14 ZR1</title -->
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      KVM guests can exploit the new hardware features of the new CPU model
      IBM z14 ZR1.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Machine checks caused by failing KVM guests are now targeted at the
      KVM virtual server instead of the KVM hypervisor, thus making the
      hypervisor more resilient.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      TLB Purge Enhancements are supported under KVM. This improves
      performance for KVM guests, in particular when subject to memory
      pressure.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Store Hypervisor Information (STHYI) from LPAR is available in KVM.
      Non-privileged user-space applications running on KVM can retrieve
      hypervisor capacity data through the LPAR if not provided by the Linux
      kernel.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Guarded Storage Facility is supported for improved performance of all
      Java workloads on KVM virtual servers.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Standard network boot setups can be used to deploy KVM guests.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The script <literal>kvm_stat</literal> was formerly a part of QEMU.
      However, it moved into the kernel tree upstream. To account for the
      change in the upstream project, in SLES 12 SP4, the script is now
      available from the new package <literal>kvm_stat</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>LOADPARM</literal> and <literal>BOOTPROG</literal> are fully
      supported. A boot menu selection is available during IPL, for example,
      to recover from a defective KVM guest operating system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Keyless Guests are supported for performance gains through improved
      memory handling for workloads running on Linux.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The IBM Call Home feature is enabled for KVM.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325734" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Robust Machine Check Handling</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325309" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Support for TLB Purge Enhancements</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325038" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Store Hypervisor Information (STHYI) for LPAR</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325027" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Support for Guarded Storage Facility</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325026" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Network Boot Base Enablement</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325017" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]New kvm_stat Package from Kernel Tree</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325016" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Full LOADPARM/BOOTPROG Support</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325015" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Keyless Guest Support</title -->
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323774" -->
<!-- title>[NOTITLE]Report Distro KVM Using Call Home</title -->
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Network" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
   <title>Network</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325041" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325041" -->
    <title>Shared Memory Communications - Direct (SMC-Direct)</title>
    <para>
     SMC-direct can be used via a new socket family and the existing tooling
     via TCP handshake. A preload library can be used to enable applications
     to use the new socket family transparently.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325008" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325008" -->
    <title>Exploitation of Shared Memory Communications (SMC-R) is now Supported</title>
    <para>
     The technology preview flag is removed for SMC-R, that enables
     RDMA-capable network interface cards (RNICs) to offer RDMA over
     Converged Ethernet (RoCE).
    </para>
    <para>
     Its usage is enabled by a collection of tools (smc-tools).
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325006" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325006" -->
    <title>Support for SET VNIC_CHARS in qeth</title>
    <para>
     qeth now supports <literal>SET VNIC_CHARS</literal>. You can configure
     MAC address flooding, learning, forwarding, and takeover behavior for
     HiperSockets devices.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Security" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
   <title>Security</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326343" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326343" -->
    <title>dm-crypt with Protected Keys - Change Master Key Tool</title>
    <para>
     Manage LUKS2 encryption keys for protected key cryptography if the
     master key of the associated Crypto Express adapter is changed.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325632" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325632" -->
    <title>Support Architectural Limit of Crypto Adapters in zcrypt Device Driver</title>
    <para>
     The crypto device driver now supports the theoretical maximum of 255
     adapters.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325173" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325173" -->
    <title>Protected Key dm-crypt Key Management Tool</title>
    <para>
     Protected key crypto for dm-crypt disks in plain format can be used
     without a dependency on cryptsetup support for LUKS(2) with protected
     keys. A key management tool as part of the s390-tools enables to manage
     a key repository allowing to associate secure keys with disk partitions
     or logical volumes.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325028" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325028" -->
    <title>libica: Use TRNG to Seed DRBG (Crypto)</title>
    <para>
     Improved generation of high (pseudo) quality random numbers via
     <literal>libica</literal> DRBG especially to generate safe random keys
     by use of the PRNO-TRNG instruction.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325020" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325020" -->
    <title>Elliptic Curve Support for Crypto</title>
    <para>
     The strategic elliptic curve asymmetric cryptography that provides
     strong security with shorter keys is now supported by Crypto Express
     function offloads with <literal>opencryptoki</literal>,
     <literal>libica</literal>, <literal>icatoken</literal> and
     <literal>openssl-ibmca</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-324997" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324997" -->
    <title>Support for the CEX6S Crypto Card</title>
    <para>
     The CEX6S crypto card is fully supported.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-324080" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324080" -->
    <title>In-Kernel Cryptography: GCM Enhancements</title>
    <para>
     Kernel services like IPSec now exploit IBM z14 cryptography hardware
     for the AES-GCM cipher.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-322024" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322024" -->
    <title>Enhanced OpenSSL Support for PKCS#11 Engine</title>
    <para>
     With the version update to 1.0.2, the PKCS#11 can also be linked as a
     module.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.RAS" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
   <title>Reliability, Availability, Serviceability (RAS)</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325002" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325002" -->
    <title>Support for DASD Block Layer Discard</title>
    <para>
     SLES 12 SP4 includes support for the Linux discard function that
     releases unused space on z/VM VDISKs.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Performance" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
   <title>Performance</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326341" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326341" -->
    <title>Performance Counters for IBM z14 (CPUMF)</title>
    <para>
     The performance counters of the IBM z14 are supported and can be
     handled and displayed with the perf tool for optimized performance
     tuning.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325005" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325005" -->
    <title>Guest Kernel Support to Avoid Unnecessary TLB Purges</title>
    <para>
     The Linux kernel now tags pages that are not used as part of a page
     table, so that the hypervisor can avoid unnecessary purging of guest
     TLB (translation lookaside buffer) entries.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-324086" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324086" -->
    <title>Kernel Interface for the Guarded Storage Facility Added to Improve Java Performance</title>
    <para>
     Optimized Java processes improve performance for many Java
     applications.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-324085" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324085" -->
    <title>Single Increment Assignment of Memory</title>
    <para>
     A new option for the “Attach Storage Element” SCLP command to speed
     up memory hotplug is available.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.SystemZ.Misc">
<!-- entries from SP1 RNs -->
   <title>Miscellaneous</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319951" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Misc">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="zSeries"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319951" -->
    <title>Deprecated DMSVSMA Functionality Has Been Removed from snIPL</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The DMSVSMA RPC protocol was only used to remote access
     machines running z/VM versions that are now out of maintenance. snIPL's
     support for this protocol was deprecated beginning with SLES 12
     SP1.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     snIPL's support for remote access to z/VM hosts via the DMSVSMA RPC
     protocol has now been removed.
    </para>
    <para>
     We recommend using SMAPI to remotely access z/VM hosts instead which is
     provided by supported z/VM 5.4, and z/VM 6.x versions. For information
     about setting up your z/VM system for API access, see <emphasis>z/VM
     Systems Management Application Programming, SC24-6234</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.AArch64" remap="InfraPackArch:AArch64">
  <title>ARM 64-Bit (AArch64) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to the version of SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server 12 SP4 for the AArch64 architecture.
  </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325653" remap="InfraPackArch:AArch64">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325653" -->
   <title>Boot and Driver Enablement for Raspberry Pi</title>
   <para>
    Bootloaders and a supported microSD card image of SUSE Linux Enterprise
    Server for ARM 12 SP4 for the Raspberry Pi are available. The template
    of the SUSE Linux image is available as profile "RaspberryPi" in the
    package <literal>kiwi-templates-SLES12-JeOS</literal> to derive custom
    appliances.
   </para>
   <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Expansion Boards</bridgehead>
   <para>
    The Raspberry Pi 3 Model B/B+ offers a 40-pin General Purpose I/O
    connector, with multiple software-configurable functions such as UART,
    I²C and SPI. This pin mux configuration along with any external devices
    attached to the pins is defined in the Device Tree which is passed by
    the bootloader to the kernel.
   </para>
   <para>
    SUSE does not currently provide support for any particular HATs or other
    expansion boards attached to the 40-pin GPIO connector. However, insofar
    as drivers for pin functions and for attached chipsets are included in
    SUSE Linux Enterprise, they can be used. SUSE does not provide support
    for making changes to the Device Tree, but successful changes will not
    affect the support status of the operating system itself. Be aware that
    errors in the Device Tree can stop the system from booting successfully
    or can even damage the hardware.
   </para>
   <para>
    The bootloader and firmware in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 now
    support Device Tree Overlays. The new recommended way of configuring
    GPIO pins is to create a file <literal>extraconfig.txt</literal> on the
    FAT volume (<literal>/boot/efi/extraconfig.txt</literal> in the SUSE
    image) with a line <literal>dtoverlay=filename-without-.dtbo</literal>
    per Overlay. For more information about the syntax, see the
    documentation by the Raspberry Pi Foundation.
   </para>
   <para>
    As a side effect, no separate <literal>/boot</literal> partition is
    needed anymore. This allows booting Btrfs snapshots in the SUSE image.
   </para>
   <para>
    If not already shipped in the <literal>/boot/efi/overlays/</literal>
    directory (<literal>raspberrypi-firmware-dt</literal> package),
    <literal>.dtbo</literal> files can be obtained from the manufacturer of
    the HAT or compiled from self-authored sources.
   </para>
   <bridgehead renderas="sect5">For More Information</bridgehead>
   <para>
    For more information, see the SUSE Best Practices documentation for the
    Raspberry Pi at
    <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sbp/all/html/SLES12SP3-rpiquick/index.html"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320679" remap="InfraPackArch:AArch64">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320679" -->
   <title>Toolchain Module Enabled in Default Installation</title>
   <tip role="compact">
    <para>
     This entry has appeared in a previous release notes document.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
    <emphasis> The system compiler (</emphasis><literal>gcc4.8</literal><emphasis>) is not supported on the
    AArch64 architecture. To work around this issue, you previously had to
    enable the Toolchain module manually and use the GCC version from that
    module. </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    On AArch64, the Toolchain Module is now automatically pre-selected after
    registering SLES during installation. This makes the latest SLE
    compilers available on all installations. You now only need to make sure
    to also use that compiler.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>When Using AutoYaST, Make Sure to Enable Toolchain Module</title>
    <para>
     Be aware that when using AutoYaST to install, you have to explicitly
     add the Toolchain module into the XML installation profile.
    </para>
   </important>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="Packages">
  <title>Packages and Functionality Changes</title>
  <para>
   This section comprises changes to packages, such as additions, updates,
   removals and changes to the package layout of software. It also contains
   information about modules available for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. For
   information about changes to package management tools, such as Zypper or
   RPM, see
   <xref linkend="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.SystemsManagement"/>.
  </para>
  <section id="Packages.Update" remap="Packages:Update">
   <title>Updated Packages</title>
   <remark> *** Description of the new package with direct link to the official website *** version
    comparison table from previous SP/product *** Bugs fixed since previous SP/Product (link to
    Bugzilla) *** Enhancements request (link to Fate number) *** link to the official documentation
    *** link to the SUSE's documentation *** Security fixes (link to CVE or SUSE's security web
    site), link to PIF *** Changelog diff (all other information non relative to security/fate/bugs) </remark>
   <para/>

   <section id="jsc-SLE-11159">
    <title>Xorg Server Has Been Updated to Version 1.19.6-4.3.1</title>
    <para>
    SLES 12 SP4 now includes version 1.19.6-4.3.1 of these two
    packages:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>xorg-x11-server</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>xorg-x11-server-extra</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The previous version was 7.6_1.15.2-36.21.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section id="jsc-SLE-11177">
    <title>Git Has Been Updated to Version 2.26.2</title>
    <para>
     SLES 12 SP4 now includes version 2.26.2 of the version control
     Git. This version of Git supports the SHA256 cipher.
    </para>
    <para>
     Refer to the
     <ulink url="https://github.com/git/git/blob/master/Documentation/RelNotes/2.26.0.txt">git Release Notes</ulink> for more detailed information.
    </para>
    <para>
     This update fixes the following security vulnerabilities:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2017-15298" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2018-11233" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2018-11235" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2018-17456" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1348" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1349" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1350" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1351" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1352" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1353" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1354" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1387" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-19604" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2020-11008" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2020-5260" />
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-327121" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327121" -->
    <title>LibreOffice Has Been Updated to Version 6.4.4.2</title>
    <para>
     LibreOffice has been updated to version 6.4.4.2. For
     information about major changes, see the LibreOffice 6.4.4.2 release notes
     at <ulink url="https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/ReleaseNotes/6.4"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325757" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325757" -->
    <title>KIWI Has Been Updated to 9.15.3</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>There was a widening gap between the KIWI version shipped in
     previous SLE 12 service packs and the upstream version of
     KIWI.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In SLE 12 SP4, KIWI has been updated to version 9.15.3, the same
     version that was also shipped in SLE 15 GA. Version 9 of KIWI is a
     complete rewrite of the software that, while keeping general
     compatibility, also includes many new features. This update also fixes
     several bugs related to building JeOS. Given the newer codestream, this
     update also simplifies support of the tool.
    </para>
    <para>
     For a comparison between KIWI 7 and KIWI 9, see
     <ulink url="https://opensource.suse.com/kiwi/overview/legacy_kiwi.html"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325659" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325659" -->
    <title>PostgreSQL Has Been Upgraded to Version 10</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>SLES 12 SP4 and SLES 15 ship with PostgreSQL 10 by default.
     To enable an upgrade path for customers, SLE 12 SP3 now includes
     PostgreSQL 10 in addition to PostgreSQL 9.6 (the version that was
     originally shipped).</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>To upgrade a PostgreSQL server installation from an older
     version, the database files need to be converted to the new
     version.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>PostgreSQL Upgrade Needs to Be Performed Before Upgrade to New SLES Version</title>
     <para>
      Neither SLES 12 SP4 nor SLES 15 include PostgreSQL 9.6. However,
      availability of PostgreSQL 9.6 is a requirement for performing the
      database upgrade to the PostgreSQL 10 format. Therefore, you must
      upgrade the database to the PostgreSQL 10 format before upgrading to
      the desired new SLES version.
     </para>
    </important>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Major New Features</bridgehead>
    <para>
     The following major new features are included in PostgreSQL 10:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Logical replication: a publish/subscribe framework for distributing
       data
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Declarative table partitioning: convenience in dividing your data
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Improved query parallelism: speed up analyses
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Quorum commit for synchronous replication: distribute data with
       confidence
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SCRAM-SHA-256 authentication: more secure data access
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     PostgreSQL 10 also brings an important change to the versioning scheme
     that is used for PostgreSQL: It now follows the format
     <emphasis>major.minor</emphasis>. This means that minor releases of
     PostgreSQL 10 are for example 10.1, 10.2, ... and the next major
     release will be 11. Previously, both the parts of the version number
     were significant for the major version. For example, PostgreSQL 9.3 and
     PostgreSQL 9.4 were different major versions.
    </para>
    <para>
     For the full PostgreSQL 10 release notes, see
     <ulink url="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/10/release-10.html">https://www.postgresql.org/docs/10/release-10.html</ulink>.
    </para>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Upgrading</bridgehead>
    <para>
     Before starting the migration, make sure the following preconditions
     are fulfilled:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The packages of your current PostgreSQL version must have been
       upgraded to their latest maintenance update.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The packages of the new PostgreSQL major version need to be
       installed. For SLE 12, this means installing
       <literal>postgresql10-server</literal> and all the packages it
       depends on. Because <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> is contained in the
       package <literal>postgresql10-contrib</literal>, this package must
       be installed as well, at least until the migration is done.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Unless <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> is used in link mode, the server
       must have enough free disk space to temporarily hold a copy of the
       database files. If the database instance was installed in the default
       location, the needed space in megabytes can be determined by running
       the following command as <literal>root</literal>: <literal>du -hs
       /var/lib/pgsql/data</literal>. If there is little disk space
       available, run the command <literal>VACUUM FULL</literal> SQL command
       on each database in the PostgreSQL instance that you want to migrate.
       This command can take very long.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     Upstream documentation about <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> including
     step-by-step instructions for performing a database migration can be
     found locally at
     <literal>file:///usr/share/doc/packages/postgresql10/html/pgupgrade.html</literal>
     (if the <literal>postgresql10-docs</literal> package is installed), or
     online at
     <ulink url="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/10/pgupgrade.html">https://www.postgresql.org/docs/10/pgupgrade.html</ulink>. The online documentation explains how you can install PostgreSQL from
     the upstream sources (which is not necessary on SLE) and also uses
     other directory names (<literal>/usr/local</literal> instead of the
     <literal>update-alternatives</literal> based path as described above).
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-323756" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323756" -->
    <title>MariaDB Has Been Upgraded to 10.2</title>
    <para>
     The MariaDB packages have been upgraded to the 10.2 series that brings
     many new features and bug fixes.
    </para>
    <para>
     The list of major changes for 10.2 series can be found at
     <ulink url="https://mariadb.com/kb/en/library/changes-improvements-in-mariadb-102/"/>. The update to the new MariaDB version generally does not cause
     issues. However, there are the following notable incompatible changes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       InnoDB is now the default storage engine.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Some options have updated default values.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Some options have been removed/renamed.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For more information about upgrading, see the upgrade notes at
     <ulink url="https://mariadb.com/kb/en/library/upgrading-from-mariadb-100-to-mariadb-101/"/>
     and
     <ulink url="https://mariadb.com/kb/en/library/upgrading-from-mariadb-101-to-mariadb-102/"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Apart from the changes in MariaDB Server itself, there are also
     packaging changes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All configuration snippets placed in <literal>my.cnf.d</literal> were
       merged to <literal>my.cnf</literal> file (omit
       <literal>default_plugins.cnf</literal> as all configuration here was
       commented out).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       By default, MariaDB will not listen for TCP/IP connections.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The list of binaries was changed:
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The <literal>mytop</literal> utility was removed and it is
          packaged separately
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The following binaries were added: <literal>mariabackup</literal>, <literal>mbstream</literal>,
          <literal>myrocks_hotbackup</literal>, <literal>sst_dump</literal>, <literal>mysql_ldb</literal>, etc.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       systemd services were renamed from <literal>mysql.service</literal>
       to <literal>mariadb.service</literal>. A <literal>mysql</literal>
       alias is still provided for the backward compatibility.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Packages.Deprecated" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
   <title>Removed and Deprecated Functionality</title>
   <remark>
    ** Why this choice?
    ** How to handle this deprecation in your system
    ** specific case (LTSS etc.)
   </remark>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-323093" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323093" -->
    <title>libcgroup1 Removed From SLE 12 SP4 and Later</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> Most functionality of
     </emphasis><literal>libcgroup1</literal><emphasis> is also provided by
     systemd. In fact, the cgroup handling of
     </emphasis><literal>libcgroup1</literal><emphasis> can conflict with
     that of systemd. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with SLE 12 SP4, <literal>libcgroup1</literal> has been
     removed. Migrate to the equivalent functionality in systemd.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information, see
     <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/kb/doc/?id=7018741"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Packages.Packaging" remap="Packages:Packaging">
   <title>Changes in Packaging and Delivery</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-326857" remap="Packages:Packaging">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326857" -->
    <title>MPI Implementations Identify in mpi-selector's list Command By Name Only</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> Previously, the MPI implementations
     </emphasis><literal>openmpi</literal><emphasis>,
     </emphasis><literal>mvapich2</literal><emphasis>, and
     </emphasis><literal>mpich</literal><emphasis> (and their variants) were
     configured to identify themselves with their name and exact version in
     </emphasis><literal>mpi-selector --list</literal><emphasis>. However,
     this behavior created a package upgrade issue where newly updated MPI
     packages would not be registered automatically. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     As part of a maintenance update to SLE, the registration issue was
     fixed by making the packages identify only by their name but not their
     exact version number in <literal>mpi-selector --list</literal>. As
     this functionality was never meant as a way to support multiple
     versions of the same MPI implementation side by side, this should not
     cause practical issues.
    </para>
    <para>
     Note that as an exception from the rule, it continues to be possible to
     install all available major versions of openMPI side by side (those can
     be, depending on the operating system version and installed extensions,
     <literal>openmpi</literal>, <literal>openmpi2</literal>, and
     <literal>openmpi3</literal>).
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->

   <section role="notoc" id="bsc-1143465">
    <title>Kernel Firmware Only Shipped as Part of the <package>kernel-firmware</package> Package</title>
    <para>
     In past releases, the <package>kernel-default</package> package used to
     contain firmware for in-kernel drivers.
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with SLES 12 SP3, such firmware is now delivered as part of the
     package <package>kernel-firmware</package>.
    </para>
   </section>

  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="TechInfo">
  <title>Technical Information</title>
  <para>
   This section contains information about system limits, a number of
   technical changes and enhancements for the experienced user.
  </para>
<!-- bnc#483250 -->
  <para>
   When talking about CPUs, we use the following terminology:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>CPU Socket</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The visible physical entity, as it is typically mounted to a
      motherboard or an equivalent.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>CPU Core</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The (usually not visible) physical entity as reported by the CPU
      vendor.
     </para>
     <para>
      On IBM Z, this is equivalent to an IFL.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Logical CPU</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is what the Linux Kernel recognizes as a "CPU".
     </para>
     <para>
      We avoid the word "thread" (which is sometimes used), as the word
      "thread" would also become ambiguous subsequently.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Virtual CPU</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A logical CPU as seen from within a Virtual Machine.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <section id="TechInfo.Kernel">
   <title>Kernel Limits</title>
   <para>
    This table summarizes the various limits which exist in our recent
    kernels and utilities (if related) for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
    SP4.
   </para>
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="5">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="feature"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="x86-64"/>
     <colspec colnum="3" colname="z"/>
     <colspec colnum="4" colname="power"/>
     <colspec colnum="5" colname="aarch64"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 12 SP4 (Linux 4.12)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry>AMD64/Intel 64 (x86_64)</entry>
       <entry>IBM Z (s390x)</entry>
       <entry>POWER (ppc64le)</entry>
<!-- AArch64 for SLES 12 SP2 values per bsc#988955. -->
       <entry>AArch64 (ARMv8)</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         CPU bits
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of logical CPUs
        </para>
       </entry>
<!-- FATE#316883 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         8192
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256
        </para>
       </entry>
<!-- FATE#315438 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         2048
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         128
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum amount of RAM (theoretical/certified)
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         &gt; 1 PiB/64 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         10 TiB/256 GiB
        </para>
       </entry>
<!-- FATE#315439 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         1 PiB/64 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256 TiB/n.a.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum amount of user space/kernel space
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         128 TiB/128 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         n.a.
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         512 TiB <superscript>1</superscript>/2 EiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256 TiB/128 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
<!-- bnc#708969 -->
        <para>
         Maximum amount of swap space
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         Up to 29 * 64 GB (x86_64) or 30 * 64 GB (other architectures)
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of processes
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         1048576
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of threads per process
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         Upper limit depends on memory and other parameters (tested with
         more than 120,000)<superscript>2</superscript>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum size per block device
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         Up to 8 EiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
<!-- bnc#550958 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         FD_SETSIZE
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         1024
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>1</superscript></emphasis> By
    default, the userspace memory limit on the POWER architecture is
    128 TiB. However, you can explicitly request mmaps up to 512 TiB.
   </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>2</superscript></emphasis> The total
    number of all processes and all threads on a system may not be higher
    than the <quote>maximum number of processes</quote>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="TechInfo.KVM">
   <title>KVM Limits</title>
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 12 SP4 Virtual Machine (VM)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry>Limits</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum VMs per host
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Unlimited (total number of virtual CPUs in all guests being no
         greater than 8 times the number of CPU cores in the host)
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Virtual CPUs per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         288
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum Memory per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         4 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para>
    Virtual Host Server (VHS) limits are identical to those of SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="TechInfo.XEN">
   <title>Xen Limits</title>
   <para>
    Since SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 SP2, we removed the 32-bit
    hypervisor as a virtualization host. 32-bit virtual guests are not
    affected and are fully supported with the provided 64-bit hypervisor.
   </para>
<!-- bnc#732995 -->
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 12 SP4 Virtual Machine (VM)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry>Limits</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of virtual CPUs per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         FV: 128; PV: 512
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum amount of memory per VM
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         x86-64: 2 TiB; x86: 16 GiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 12 SP4 Virtual Host Server (VHS)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry>Limits</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of physical CPUs
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         1024
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of virtual CPUs
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Unlimited (total number of virtual CPUs in all guests must be no
         greater than 8 times the number of CPU cores in the host)
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum amount of physical memory
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         16 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum amount of Dom0 physical memory
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         500 GiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of block devices
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         12,000 SCSI logical units
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
<!-- FIXME: The legends we use across these tables are very differently
 formatted. Unify. - sknorr, 2016-07-14 -->
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>PV:</title>
      <para>
       Paravirtualization
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>FV:</title>
      <para>
       Full virtualization
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For more information about acronyms, see the virtualization
    documentation provided at
    <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/12-SP4/"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
<!-- bsc#1135799 -->
    AMD Rome-based CPUs are not supported by Xen on SLES 12 SP4. These CPUs
    are only supported by SLES 12 SP5 and higher.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="TechInfo.Filesystems">
   <title>File Systems</title>
   <section id="TechInfo.Filesystems.Comparison">
    <title>Comparison of Supported File Systems</title>
    <para>
     SUSE Linux Enterprise was the first enterprise Linux distribution to
     support journaling file systems and logical volume managers back in
     2000. Later, we introduced XFS to Linux, which today is seen as the
     primary work horse for large-scale file systems, systems with heavy
     load and multiple parallel reading and writing operations. With SUSE
     Linux Enterprise 12, we went the next step of innovation and started
     using the copy-on-write file system Btrfs as the default for the
     operating system, to support system snapshots and rollback.
    </para>
    <para>
<!-- bnc#903673: use ascii symbols -->
     <simplelist>
      <member><emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> supported</member>
      <member><emphasis role="bold">–</emphasis> unsupported</member>
     </simplelist>
    </para>
    <informaltable frame="all">
     <tgroup cols="6">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="28*"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="18*"/>
      <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="18*"/>
      <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4" colwidth="18*"/>
      <colspec colnum="5" colname="c5" colwidth="18*"/>
      <colspec colnum="6" colname="c6" colwidth="18*"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry>Feature</entry>
        <entry>Btrfs</entry>
        <entry>XFS</entry>
        <entry>Ext4</entry>
        <entry>OCFS 2 <superscript>1</superscript>
        </entry>
        <entry>ReiserFS <superscript>2</superscript>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Support in products
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE HA
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Data/metadata journaling
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A <superscript>3</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Journal internal/external
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A <superscript>3</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Journal checksumming
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A <superscript>3</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Subvolumes
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Offline extend/shrink
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / – <superscript>4</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Online extend/shrink
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Inode allocation map
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          B-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          B+-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          table
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          B-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          u. B*-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Sparse files
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Tail packing
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Small files stored inline
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + (in metadata)
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + (in inode)
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + (in inode)
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + (in metadata)
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Defragmentation
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
<!-- FIXME: Plans to add defragmentation for OCFS 2, ask again. -
         sknorr, 2017-10-27 -->
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Extended file attributes/ACLs
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          User/group quotas
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Project quotas
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Subvolume quotas
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
<!-- All fs's can dump/restore metadata, but not all can
         dump/restore actual data (via Goldwyn Rodrigues). - sknorr,
         2017-10-26 -->
         <para>
          Data dump/restore
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Block size default
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry namest="c2" nameend="c6">
         <para>
          4 KiB <superscript>5</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum file system size
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          8 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          4 PiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 TiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum file size
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          8 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          4 PiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
<!-- FIXME: Better make these footnotes? Need to check compatibility of the
 yast XSL stylesheet first. - sknorr, 2016-07-14 -->
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>1</superscript></emphasis> OCFS 2 is
     fully supported as part of the SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability
     Extension.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>2</superscript></emphasis> ReiserFS
     is supported for existing file systems. The creation of new ReiserFS
     file systems is discouraged.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>3</superscript></emphasis> Btrfs is
     a copy-on-write file system. Instead of journaling changes before
     writing them in-place, it writes them to a new location and then links
     the new location in. Until the last write, the changes are not
     <quote>committed</quote>. Because of the nature of the file system,
     quotas are implemented based on subvolumes
     (<literal>qgroups</literal>).
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>4</superscript></emphasis> To extend
     an OCFS 2 file system, the cluster must be online but the file system
     itself must be unmounted.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>5</superscript></emphasis> The block
     size default varies with different host architectures. 64 KiB is used
     on POWER, 4 KiB on other systems. The actual size used can be checked
     with the command <command>getconf
     <replaceable>PAGE_SIZE</replaceable></command>.
    </para>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Additional Notes</bridgehead>
    <para>
     Maximum file size above can be larger than the file system's actual
     size because of the use of sparse blocks. All standard file systems on
     SUSE Linux Enterprise Server have LFS, which gives a maximum file size
     of 2<superscript>63</superscript> bytes in theory.
    </para>
    <para>
     The numbers in the above table assume that the file systems are using a
     4 KiB block size which is the most common standard. When using
     different block sizes, the results are different.
    </para>
    <para>
     In this document: 1024 Bytes = 1 KiB; 1024 KiB = 1 MiB; 1024 MiB =
     1 GiB; 1024 GiB = 1 TiB; 1024 TiB = 1 PiB; 1024 PiB = 1 EiB. See
     also <ulink url="http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
<!-- bnc#608543 and bnc#574572 -->
     NFSv4 with IPv6 is only supported for the client side. An NFSv4 server
     with IPv6 is not supported.
    </para>
    <para>
<!-- bnc#606288 -->
     The version of Samba shipped with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4
     delivers integration with Windows Active Directory domains. In
     addition, we provide the clustered version of Samba as part of SUSE
     Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension 12 SP4.
    </para>
    <para>
<!-- bsc#1073261 -->
     Some file system features are available in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
     12 SP4 but are not supported by SUSE. By default, the file system
     drivers in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 will refuse mounting
     file systems that use unsupported features (in particular, in
     read-write mode). To enable unsupported features, set the module
     parameter <literal>allow_unsupported=1</literal> in
     <filename>/etc/modprobe.d</filename> or write the value
     <literal>1</literal> to
     <filename>/sys/module/<replaceable>MODULE_NAME</replaceable>/parameters/allow_unsupported</filename>.
     However, note that setting this option will render your kernel and thus
     your system unsupported.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section id="TechInfo.Filesystems.Btrfs">
    <title>Supported Btrfs Features</title>
    <para>
     The following table lists supported and unsupported Btrfs features
     across multiple SLES versions.
    </para>
    <para>
     <simplelist>
      <member><emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> supported</member>
      <member><emphasis role="bold">–</emphasis> unsupported</member>
     </simplelist>
    </para>
<!-- Table according to bsc#979501, this attachment:
  https://bugzilla.suse.com/attachment.cgi?id=687340 -->
    <informaltable>
     <tgroup cols="5">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="feature" colwidth="6.5cm"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="11SP4" colwidth="*"/>
      <colspec colnum="3" colname="12SP3" colwidth="*"/>
      <colspec colnum="4" colname="12SP4" colwidth="*"/>
      <colspec colnum="5" colname="15GA" colwidth="*"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
<!-- Remove unsupported OS's. -->
        <entry>Feature</entry>
        <entry>SLES 11 SP4</entry>
        <entry>SLES 12 SP3</entry>
        <entry>SLES 12 SP4</entry>
        <entry>SLES 15 GA</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>Copy on Write</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Snapshots/Subvolumes</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Metadata Integrity</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Data Integrity</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Online Metadata Scrubbing</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Automatic Defragmentation</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Manual Defragmentation</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>In-band Deduplication</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Out-of-band Deduplication</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Quota Groups</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Metadata Duplication</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Multiple Devices</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 0</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 1</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 10</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 5</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 6</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Hot Add/Remove</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Device Replace</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Seeding Devices</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Compression</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Big Metadata Blocks</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Skinny Metadata</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Send Without File Data</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Send/Receive</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Inode Cache</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Fallocate with Hole Punch</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="TechInfo.Java">
   <title>Supported Java Versions</title>
   <para>
    The following table lists Java implementations available in SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server 12 SP4:
   </para>
   <informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="4">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3"/>
     <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>Name (Package Name)</entry>
       <entry>Version</entry>
       <entry>Part of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</entry>
       <entry>Support</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>OpenJDK (<package>java-1_8_0-openjdk</package>)</entry>
       <entry>1.8.0</entry>
       <entry>SLES</entry>
       <entry>SUSE, L3</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>OpenJDK (<package>java-1_7_0-openjdk</package>)</entry>
       <entry>1.7.0</entry>
       <entry>SLES</entry>
       <entry>SUSE, L3</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>IBM Java (<package>java-1_8_0-ibm</package>)</entry>
       <entry>1.8.0</entry>
       <entry>SLES</entry>
       <entry>External only</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>IBM Java (<package>java-1_7_1-ibm</package>)</entry>
       <entry>1.7.1</entry>
       <entry>SLES</entry>
       <entry>External only</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>IBM Java (<package>java-1_6_0-ibm</package>)</entry>
       <entry>1.6.0</entry>
       <entry>Legacy Module</entry>
       <entry>External only</entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- Legal notice copied from SLED release notes, mge@novell.com, 2010-05-07 -->
<!-- Legal notice updated, to smell more like SUSE -->
 <section id="Legal">
  <title>Legal Notices</title>
  <para>
   SUSE makes no representations or warranties with respect to the contents
   or use of this documentation, and specifically disclaims any express or
   implied warranties of merchantability or fitness for any particular
   purpose. Further, SUSE reserves the right to revise this publication and
   to make changes to its content, at any time, without the obligation to
   notify any person or entity of such revisions or changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Further, SUSE makes no representations or warranties with respect to any
   software, and specifically disclaims any express or implied warranties of
   merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose. Further, SUSE
   reserves the right to make changes to any and all parts of SUSE software,
   at any time, without any obligation to notify any person or entity of
   such changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Any products or technical information provided under this Agreement may
   be subject to U.S. export controls and the trade laws of other countries.
   You agree to comply with all export control regulations and to obtain any
   required licenses or classifications to export, re-export, or import
   deliverables. You agree not to export or re-export to entities on the
   current U.S. export exclusion lists or to any embargoed or terrorist
   countries as specified in U.S. export laws. You agree to not use
   deliverables for prohibited nuclear, missile, or chemical/biological
   weaponry end uses. Refer to
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> for more information on
   exporting SUSE software. SUSE assumes no responsibility for your failure
   to obtain any necessary export approvals.
  </para>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?>
   SUSE LLC. This release notes document is licensed under a Creative
   Commons Attribution-NoDerivs 3.0 United States License (CC-BY-ND-3.0 US,
   <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/us/"/>).
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE has intellectual property rights relating to technology embodied in
   the product that is described in this document. In particular, and
   without limitation, these intellectual property rights may include one or
   more of the U.S. patents listed at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> and one or more
   additional patents or pending patent applications in the U.S. and other
   countries.
  </para>
  <para>
   For SUSE trademarks, see SUSE Trademark and Service Mark list
   (<ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/>). All third-party
   trademarks are the property of their respective owners.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
