<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "release-notes.ent">
<!ENTITY rnotes "Release Notes">
<!ENTITY rversion "@VERSION@">
<!ENTITY yast "YaST">
<!ENTITY autoyast "AutoYaST">
<!ENTITY suse "SUSE">
<!ENTITY suse-version "12">
<!ENTITY spversion "1">
<!ENTITY opensuse "open&suse;">
<!ENTITY suselinux "&suse; Linux">
<!ENTITY sle "&suse; Linux Enterprise">
<!ENTITY sled "&sle; Desktop">
<!ENTITY sles "&sle; Server">
<!ENTITY sleha "&suselinux; Enterprise High Availability Extension">
<!ENTITY slehag "Geo Clustering for &suselinux; Enterprise High Availability">
<!ENTITY ha-guide "High Availability Guide">
<!ENTITY sdk "Software Development Kit">
<!ENTITY slesdk "&suselinux; Enterprise &sdk;">
]>
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension</productname>
  <productnumber>12 SP1</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension is a suite of
    clustering technologies that enable enterprises to implement highly
    available Linux clusters and eliminate single points of failure. This
    document gives an overview of features of SUSE Linux Enterprise High
    Availability Extension and their limitations. Some sections do not apply
    to a particular architecture or product, this is explicitly marked.
   </para>

   <para>
    Manuals can be found in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of the
    installation media, or in the directory
    <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> on the installed system (if
    installed).
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension</title>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension is an affordable,
   integrated suite of robust open source clustering technologies that
   enable enterprises to implement highly available Linux clusters and
   eliminate single points of failure.
  </para>
  <para>
   Used with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, it helps firms maintain business
   continuity, protect data integrity, and reduce unplanned downtime for
   their mission-critical Linux workloads.
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension provides all of the
   essential monitoring, messaging, and cluster resource management
   functionality of proprietary third-party solutions, but at a more
   affordable price, making it accessible to a wider range of enterprises.
  </para>
  <para>
   It is optimized to work with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, and its tight
   integration ensures customers have the most robust, secure, and up to
   date high availability solution. Based on an innovative, highly flexible
   policy engine, it supports a wide range of clustering scenarios.
  </para>
  <para>
   With static or stateless content, the High Availability cluster can be
   used without a cluster file system. This includes web-services with
   static content as well as printing systems or communication systems like
   proxies that do not need to recover data.
  </para>
  <para>
   Finally, its open source license minimizes the risk of vendor lock-in,
   and it's adherence to open standards encourages interoperability with
   industry standard tools and technologies.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Intro.New">
  <title>What's New?</title>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
    Cluster File System
     </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GFS2 cluster file system with read/write support, to complement the
      SUSE recommended OCFS2 cluster file system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
      Load balancer
     </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      HAProxy as layer 4 load balancer added, to complement the Linux
      virtual server load balancer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
      History Explorer
     </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      HAWK history explorer now includes off-line analysis capabilities.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     Resource Agents
     </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Resource agents got multiple updates, including a resource agent to
      handle SCSI reservations
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   See
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SLE-HA/12-SP1-GEO/">https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SLE-HA/12-SP1-GEO/</ulink>
   for what is new in the Geo clustering option for the SUSE Linux
   Enterprise High Availability Extension 12 SP1.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Features">
  <title>Features and Versions</title>
  <para>
   This section includes an overview of some of the major features and new
   functionality provided by SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability
   Extension 12 SP1.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent">
  <title>New Features and Known Issues</title>
  <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-318281" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318281" -->
   <title>New User Interface for Hawk</title>
   <para>
    Hawk has been redesigned to be more intuitive and easier to use.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Kernel_Modules" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel_Modules">
   <title>Kernel Modules</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318321" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel_Modules">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318321" -->
    <title>IPVS Support for iptables -m</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> Setting up Linux Virtual Server (LVS) in combination with
     SMTP did not work due to missing </emphasis><literal>iptables -m
     ipvs</literal><emphasis> support. IPVS (IP Virtual Server) is used for
     Linux Virtual Server. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The <literal>iptables</literal> package has been updated to a higher
     version and now includes the match support of iptables. To make it
     work, you need the probe kernel module <literal>xt_ipvs</literal>. It
     is provided by the respective <literal>cluster-network-*</literal>
     package.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.SystemsManagement" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
   <title>Systems Management</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318483" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318483" -->
    <title>Hawk now validates parameter values as they are entered in wizards.</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The wizards could be difficult to fill in as they provided
     minimal information about valid parameter values.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Wizards now validate parameter values on the fly. They also display
     extended documentation about all parameters which includes showing the
     default value for the parameter (if any).
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318482" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318482" -->
    <title>Wizards in crmsh and Hawk Are More Powerful</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The wizards in Hawk were able to make cluster configuration
     changes, but not configure the resources themselves.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In the new Hawk (package <literal>hawk2</literal> ), the wizards
     include steps to install packages, set up default configuration files
     and ensure that requirements are met as part of applying the cluster
     configuration changes.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318319" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318319" -->
    <title>Resource Tags Can Now Be Edited with Hawk</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Tagging resources is a new feature in Pacemaker. Editing and
     viewing them has been possible using the command line, but not from the
     Hawk UI.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The new Hawk (package <literal>hawk2</literal> ) enables creating and
     editing resource tags.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318291" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318291" -->
    <title>Improved History Explorer in Hawk</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The history explorer is a very powerful feature, but the user
     interface needed improvement.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Reports now have a description page showing a list of important node
     events and resource events, making it easy to see what has happened at
     a glance. The interface has been redesigned to provide more feedback as
     to which transition is being viewed. Navigation is simplified by the
     buttons <emphasis>Previous Transition</emphasis> and <emphasis>Next
     Transition</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318290" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318290" -->
    <title>Log of Commands in Hawk</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The step from using Hawk to using the command line tools can
     be a challenge.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In Hawk, there is now a screen <emphasis>Command Log</emphasis> that
     displays all the corresponding <literal>crm</literal> commands that
     Hawk runs behind the scene. This makes it easy to see the corresponding
     <literal>crm</literal> command to an action in the user interface.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-318211" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318211" -->
    <title>New and Improved Cluster Configuration Wizards in crmsh and Hawk</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> The wizards in Hawk were not usable from the command line,
     and </emphasis><literal>crmsh</literal><emphasis> had its own form of
     wizards that were implemented differently than in Hawk. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The wizards are now shared between <literal>crmsh</literal> and Hawk.
     <literal>crmsh</literal> is able to apply the old XML wizards for Hawk,
     and Hawk is able to run the new configuration script style wizards the
     same as <literal>crmsh</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Performance" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
   <title>Performance Related Information</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317940" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317940" -->
    <title>DRBD Initial Synchronization Is Now Faster</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> With huge devices, the initial full synchronization took a
     lot of time even if no real data has to be synchronized. Most of the
     time, the command </emphasis><literal>drbdadm new-current-uuid
     --clear-bitmap &lt;resource&gt;</literal><emphasis> can be used to
     simply skip it, then make sure the data is consistent on file system
     level. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>For some corner cases, users still need to do a full
     synchronization. This will take a long time, especially in an
     environment with low network bandwidth.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     We now supply another method to zero out devices on both sides instead
     of doing a full synchronization from one node to the other. This helps
     when the network speed becomes the bottleneck of the synchronization.
     After the exchange of packets to the other node, the device on both
     sides will start to zero out locally.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information, see the documentation at
     <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sle-ha-12/book_sleha/data/sec_ha_drbd_configure.html#sec_ha_drbd_configure_init">https://www.suse.com/documentation/sle-ha-12/book_sleha/data/sec_ha_drbd_configure.html#sec_ha_drbd_configure_init</ulink>.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Support">
  <title>Support Statement for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension 12 SP1</title>
  <para>
   Support requires an appropriate subscription from Novell; for more
   information, see <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/server/"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   A Geo Clustering for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension
   subscription is needed to receive support and maintenance to run
   geographical clustering scenarios, including manual and automated setups.
  </para>
  <para>
   Support for the DRBD storage replication is independent of the cluster
   scenario and included as part of the SUSE Linux Enterprise High
   Availability Extension product and does not require the addition of a Geo
   Clustering for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension
   subscription.
  </para>
  <para>
   General Support Statement
  </para>
  <para>
   The following definitions apply:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     L1: Installation and problem determination - technical support designed
     to provide compatibility information, installation and configuration
     assistance, usage support, on-going maintenance and basic
     troubleshooting. Level 1 Support is not intended to correct product
     defect errors.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     L2: Reproduction of problem isolation - technical support designed to
     duplicate customer problems, isolate problem areas and potential
     issues, and provide resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1
     Support.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     L3: Code Debugging and problem resolution - technical support designed
     to resolve complex problems by engaging engineering in patch provision,
     resolution of product defects which have been identified by Level 2
     Support.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Novell will only support the usage of original (unchanged or not
   recompiled) packages.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Sourcecode">
  <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
<!-- msvec and legal (ciaran), 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location as the first chapter -->
  <para>
   This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
   General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the source
   code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material. The source code is
   available for download at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. Also,
   for up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
   request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Requests should be
   sent by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/> or as
   otherwise instructed at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. SUSE
   may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Feedback">
<!-- bnc#826887 -->
  <title>More Information and Feedback</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Read the READMEs on the CDs.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get detailed changelog information about a particular package from the
     RPM:
    </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp &lt;FILENAME&gt;.rpm</screen>
    <para>
     &lt;FILENAME&gt;. is the name of the RPM.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of CD1
     for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of CD1
     of the SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension CDs. This
     directory includes a PDF version of the High Availability Guide.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/"/> contains additional
     or updated documentation for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability
     Extension 12 SP1.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Visit <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/"/> for the latest
     product news from SUSE and
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/> for
     additional information on the source code of SUSE Linux Enterprise
     products.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2015 SUSE LLC.
  </para>
  <para>
   Thanks for using SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension in
   your business.
  </para>
  <para>
   The SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension Team.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
