<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
<?dbsuse-bugtracker url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi" product="Beta SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 15 SP1" component="Maintenance" assignee="lukas.kucharczyk@suse.com" ?>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications</productname>
  <productnumber>15 SP1</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>

  <abstract>
<!-- msvec and marketing, 2013-05-13 -->
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications combines SLES and
    SLE HA with additional software specifically meant to simplify running
    and managing SAP applications. This document provides an overview of
    high-level general features, capabilities, and limitations of SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 15 SP1 and important product
    updates.
   </para>

   <para condition="beta;pre">
    This product will be released in June 2019. The latest version of these
    release notes is always available at
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>. Drafts of the general
    documentation can be found at
    <ulink url="https://susedoc.github.io/#slesforsap"/>.
   </para>

   <para condition="maintained">
    These release notes are updated periodically. The latest version is
    always available at <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>.
    General documentation can be found at:
    <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sles-sap/15-SP1"/>.
   </para>

   <para condition="unmaintained">
    The support period for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications
    15 SP1 has ended. To keep systems secure and supported, upgrade to a
    current SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications version.
    Before starting the upgrade, make sure to apply all maintenance updates.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>

 <section id="rn.about">
  <title>About the Release Notes</title>
  <para>
   The most recent version of the Release Notes is available online at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   These Release Notes are identical across all supported architectures.
  </para>
  <para>
   Entries can be listed multiple times if they are important and belong to
   multiple sections.
  </para>
  <para>
   Release notes usually only list changes that happened between two
   subsequent releases. Certain important entries from the release notes
   documents of previous product versions may be repeated. To make such
   entries easier to identify, they contain a note to that effect.
  </para>
  <para>
   Repeated entries are provided as a courtesy only. Therefore, if you are
   skipping one or more service packs, check the release notes of the
   skipped service packs as well. If you are only reading the release notes
   of the current release, you could miss important changes.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications</title>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications is the leading Linux
   platform for SAP HANA, SAP NetWeaver, and SAP S/4HANA applications that
   provides optimized performance, reduced downtime, and faster SAP
   landscape deployments. It includes features to secure SAP HANA systems
   and ease the transition to SAP S/4HANA for systems administrators. SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications combines SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server and its SLE HA with additional software specifically
   meant to simplify running and managing SAP applications.
  </para>
<!-- FIXME: We're unfortunately (mis)using the ID Intro.New for another
 section currently. Probably a good idea to stop doing that at some point. -->
<section id="Intro.New">
  <title>What Is New?</title>

  <para>
   SLES for SAP 15 SP1 introduces many innovative changes compared to
   SLES for SAP 15 GA. The most important changes are listed below:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <!-- see: jsc#SLE-4044 -->
     <title>SAP HANA-SR Wizard Can Be Used in Unattended Mode</title>
     <para>
      For more information, see <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sles-sap/15-SP1/single-html/SLES4SAP-guide/#sec-s4s-hana-cluster-wizard-semiautomatic"/>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <!-- <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Feature 2:</title>
     <para>
      It is great!
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem> -->
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
  <section id="Intro.Important">
   <title>Important Sections of This Document</title>
   <para>
    If you are upgrading from a previous SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for
    SAP Applications release, you should review at least the following
    sections:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="Intro.Support"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="Intro.Additional">
   <title>Additional Release Notes Documents</title>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications also includes the
    software selection of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server and SUSE Linux
    Enterprise High Availability Extension.
   </para>
   <para>
    Make sure to review the release notes for both products in addition to
    this document:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Server:
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SUSE-SLES/15-SP1/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension:
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SLE-HA/15-SP1/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="Intro.Lifecycle">
   <title>Support and Life Cycle</title>
<!-- This is highly product-specific, make sure to adapt! -->
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications is backed by
    award-winning support from SUSE, an established technology leader with a
    proven history of delivering enterprise-quality support services.
   </para>
<!-- FIXME: Are these values all correct? - sknorr, 2018-09-28 -->
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 15 has a 13-year life
    cycle, with 10 years of General Support and 3 years of Extended
    Support. SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications comes
    Extended Service Pack Overlay Support by default, this means the current
    version (SP1) will be fully maintained and supported until 3.5 years
    after the release of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
    Applications 15 SP2.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you need additional time to design, validate and test your upgrade
    plans, Long Term Service Pack Support (LTSS) can extend the support you
    get by an additional 12 to 36 months in 12-month increments, providing a
    total of 3 to 5 years of support on any given Service Pack.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The support policy at
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/policy.html"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Long Term Service Pack Support page at
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/programs/long-term-service-pack-support.html"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="Intro.Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications</title>
   <para>
    To receive support, you need an appropriate subscription with SUSE. For
    more information, see
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/support/programs/subscriptions/?id=SUSE_Linux_Enterprise_Server_for_SAP_Applications"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The following definitions apply:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L1</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem determination, which means technical support designed to
       provide compatibility information, usage support, ongoing
       maintenance, information gathering and basic troubleshooting using
       available documentation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L2</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem isolation, which means technical support designed to analyze
       data, reproduce customer problems, isolate problem area and provide a
       resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1 or prepare for
       Level 3.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L3</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem resolution, which means technical support designed to resolve
       problems by engaging engineering to resolve product defects which
       have been identified by Level 2 Support.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    For contracted customers and partners, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for
    SAP Applications 15 SP1 is delivered with L3 support for all packages,
    except for the following:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Technology Previews
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Sound, graphics, fonts and artwork
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Packages that require an additional customer contract
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    SUSE will only support the usage of original packages. That is, packages
    that are unchanged and not recompiled.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section id="tech-previews">
   <title>Technology Previews</title>
   <para>
    Technology previews are packages, stacks, or features delivered by SUSE
    which are not supported. They may be functionally incomplete, unstable or
    in other ways not suitable for production use. They are included for your
    convenience and give you a chance to test new technologies within an
    enterprise environment.
   </para>
   <para>
    Whether a technology preview becomes a fully supported technology later
    depends on customer and market feedback. Technology previews can be dropped
    at any time and SUSE does not commit to providing a supported version of
    such technologies in the future.
   </para>
   <para>
    Give your SUSE representative feedback about technology previews, including
    your experience and use case.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section id="Intro.Documentation">
   <title>Documentation and Other Information</title>
   <para/>
   <section id="Intro.Documentation.Media">
    <title>On the Product Medium</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For general product information, see the file
       <filename>README</filename> <phrase condition="beta">and the file
       <filename>README.BETA</filename></phrase> in the top level of the
       product medium.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For a chronological log of all changes made to updated packages, see
       the file <filename>ChangeLog</filename> in the top level of the
       product medium.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Detailed change log information about a particular package is
       available using RPM:
      </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp <replaceable>FILE_NAME.rpm</replaceable></screen>
      <para>
       (Replace <replaceable>FILE_NAME.rpm</replaceable> with the name of
       the RPM.)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For more information, see the directory <filename>docu</filename> of
       the product medium of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
       Applications 15 SP1.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section id="Intro.Documentation.External">
    <title>Externally Provided Documentation</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sles-sap/15-SP1"/>
       contains additional or updated documentation for SUSE Linux
       Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 15 SP1.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find a collection of White Papers in the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
       for SAP Applications Resource Library at
       <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap/#resources"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
 </section>

<!-- There is no 12 version of the "Features" category, so we are using
 Intro.New as a catch-all. - sknorr, 2016-09-12 -->

 <section id="InfraPackArch.Power" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
  <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications for POWER</title>
  <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-327774" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327774" -->
   <title>On POWER, the Minimum Certified Revision of SAP HANA 2.0 SPS04 Is Revision 41</title>
   <para>
    On SLES for SAP 15 SP1 for POWER, the minimum certified revision of SAP
    HANA 2.0 SPS04 is revision 41. For earlier revisions of SAP HANA 2.0
    SPS04, there is a compatibility issue.
   </para>
   <para>
    However, this issue does not affect other versions of SAP HANA, such as
    version SAP HANA 2.0 SPS03, which is supported.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>

 <section id="Changes">
  <title>New Features, Changes &amp; Fixes</title>
  <section role="notoc" id="bsc-1197511">
   <title>SAP native systemd support</title>
   <para>
    In the past for Linux the systemV init service <literal>sapinit</literal>
    was starting the SAP Host Agent and all the <literal>sapstartsrv</literal>
    processes listed in
    <literal>/usr/sap/sapservices</literal>. A real systemd integration was not
    available.
   </para>
   <para>
    Now the native integration of SAP Host Agent is started via the
    <literal>saphostagent.service</literal> unit. Adaptations to the
    <literal>saphostagent.service</literal> unit must be done by adding a
    so-called drop-in file.
   </para>
   <para>
    For any native integrated SAP instance a systemd unit with name schema
    <literal>&lt;SID&gt;_&lt;INO&gt;</literal> (for example,
    <literal>SAPEN1_10</literal>) is added. Adaptations should be done using a
    drop-in file. It is highly recommended to still use the
    <literal>sapcontrol</literal>
    functions which guarantees also the functionality of cluster integration
    like the <literal>sap-suse-cluster-connector</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Before you start your new installation or update to the native systemd
    integration, make sure you update the resource agent packages to the newest
    available versions. The native SAP systemd integration is supported starting
    with the following package versions for SLES for SAP Applications 15:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>resource-agents 4.3.0184.6ee15eb2-4.60.1</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>sapstartsrv-resource-agents
     0.9.0+git.1645795466.55a8cca-1.12.1</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>SAPHanaSR 0.155.0</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>SAPHanaSR-ScaleOut 0.181.0</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For details please refer to the manual pages
    <literal>ocf_suse_SAPStartSrv(7)</literal>,
    <literal>SAPHanaSR(7)</literal>, and
    <literal>SAPHanaSR-ScaleOut(7)</literal>.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Packages.New" remap="Packages:New">
  <title>Added Packages</title>
  <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325727" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325727" -->
   <title>Package insserv-compat Has Been Added to SAP Application Server Base Pattern</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis>SAP applications depend on the
    </emphasis><literal>sapinit</literal><emphasis> System V script. Other
    third-party software not yet updated to include systemd unit scripts may
    also depend on System V init scripts. On its own, systemd does not
    support System V init scripts anymore.</emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    The package <literal>insserv-compat</literal> adds compatibility with
    System V init scripts to systemd and can be used both SAP and non-SAP
    applications. This package is now also included in the <emphasis>SAP
    Applications Server Base</emphasis> pattern.
   </para>
   <para>
    That way, <literal>insserv-compat</literal> will provide System V
    compatibility until SAP and other third parties fully adopt systemd unit
    scripts.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>

 <section id="Sourcecode">
  <title>Obtaining Source Code</title>
  <para>
   This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
   General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the source
   code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material.
   The source code is available for download at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/download/sle-sap/"/> on Medium 2.
   For up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon request,
   SUSE will mail a copy of the source code.
   Send requests by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/>.
   SUSE may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section id="Legal">
  <title>Legal Notices</title>
  <para>
   SUSE makes no representations or warranties with regard to the contents
   or use of this documentation, and specifically disclaims any express or
   implied warranties of merchantability or fitness for any particular
   purpose. Further, SUSE reserves the right to revise this publication and
   to make changes to its content, at any time, without the obligation to
   notify any person or entity of such revisions or changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Further, SUSE makes no representations or warranties with regard to any
   software, and specifically disclaims any express or implied warranties of
   merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose. Further, SUSE
   reserves the right to make changes to any and all parts of SUSE software,
   at any time, without any obligation to notify any person or entity of
   such changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Any products or technical information provided under this Agreement may
   be subject to U.S. export controls and the trade laws of other countries.
   You agree to comply with all export control regulations and to obtain any
   required licenses or classifications to export, re-export, or import
   deliverables. You agree not to export or re-export to entities on the
   current U.S. export exclusion lists or to any embargoed or terrorist
   countries as specified in U.S. export laws. You agree to not use
   deliverables for prohibited nuclear, missile, or chemical/biological
   weaponry end uses. Refer to
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> for more information
   on exporting SUSE software. SUSE assumes no responsibility for your
   failure to obtain any necessary export approvals.
  </para>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?> SUSE LLC.
  </para>

  <para>
   This release notes document is licensed under a Creative Commons
   Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License (CC-BY-ND-4.0). You
   should have received a copy of the license along with this document. If
   not, see <ulink url="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE has intellectual property rights relating to technology embodied in
   the product that is described in this document. In particular, and
   without limitation, these intellectual property rights may include one or
   more of the U.S. patents listed at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> and one or more
   additional patents or pending patent applications in the U.S. and other
   countries.
  </para>
  <para>
   For SUSE trademarks, see SUSE Trademark and Service Mark list
   (<ulink url="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/>). All third-party
   trademarks are the property of their respective owners.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
