<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "release-notes.ent" >
%myents;
]>


<section>
 <title>Network</title>
 <para />
 <para>CHECKIT:SLE11.3</para>
 <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
   <term>
     IPv6 Improvements
   </term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     &sles; has successfully completed the USGv6 test program designated
    by NIST that provides a proof of compliance to IPv6 specifications
    outlined in current industry standards for common network products.
   </para>
   <para>
    Being IPv6 Consortium Member and Contributor Novell/SUSE have worked
    successfully with University of New Hampshire InterOperability
    Laboratory (UNH-IOL) to verify compliance to IPv6
    specifications. The UNH-IOL offers ISO/IEC 17025 accredited testing
    designed specifically for the USGv6 test program. The devices that
    have successfully completed the USGv6 testing at the UNH-IOL by
    December 2012 are &sles; 11 SP2.  Testing for
    subsequent releases of &sles; is in progress,
    and current and future results will be listed at
    <ulink url="http://www.iol.unh.edu/services/testing/ipv6/usgv6tested.php?company=105&amp;type=#eqplist"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    &sles; can be installed in an IPv6 environment and run IPv6
    applications. When installing via network, do not forget to boot
    with "<literal>ipv6=1</literal>" (accept v4 and v6) or
    "<literal>ipv6only=1</literal>" (only v6) on the kernel command
    line. For more information, see the Deployment Guide and also <xref
    linkend="TechInfo.IPv6"/>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term>
     10G Networking Capabilities
   </term>
  <listitem>
   <para/>
  </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>
     OFED 1.5
   </term>
  <listitem>
   <para/>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term>
    traceroute 1.2
   </term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Support for traceroute over TCP.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term>
    FCoE
   </term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    FCoE is an implementation of the Fibre Channel over Ethernet working
    draft. Fibre Channel over Ethernet is the encapsulation of Fibre
    Channel frames in Ethernet packets.  It allows users with a FCF
    (Fibre Channel over Ethernet Forwarder) to access their existing
    Fibre Channel storage using an Ethernet adapter. When leveraging
    DCB's PFC technology to provide a loss-less environment, FCoE can
    run SAN and LAN traffic over the same link.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>

   <term>
    Data Center Bridging (DCB)
   </term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Data Center Bridging (DCB) is a collection of Ethernet enhancements
    designed to allow network traffic with differing requirements (e.g.,
    highly reliable, no drops vs. best effort vs. low latency) to
    operate and coexist on Ethernet. Current DCB features are:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Enhanced Transmission Selection</emphasis> (aka
      <emphasis>Priority Grouping</emphasis>) to provide a framework for
      assigning bandwidth guarantees to traffic classes.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Priority-based Flow Control (PFC)</emphasis> provides a
      flow control mechanism which can work independently for each
      802.1p priority.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Congestion Notification</emphasis> provides a mechanism
      for end-to-end congestion control for protocols, which do not have
      built-in congestion management.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
</section>
