<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl" type="text/xml" title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-rn.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <info>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
  <productnumber>15 SP1</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <!-- msvec and marketing, 2013-05-13 -->
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is a modern, modular operating system for both
    multimodal and traditional IT. This document provides an overview of
    high-level general features, capabilities, and limitations of SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server 15 SP1 and important product updates.
   </para>

   <para condition="beta;pre">
    This product will be released in June 2019. The latest version of these
    release notes is always available at
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>. Drafts of the
    general documentation can be found at
    <link xlink:href="https://susedoc.github.io/doc-sle/develop"/>.
   </para>

   <para condition="maintained">
    These release notes are updated periodically. The latest version is always
    available at <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>.
    General documentation can be found at:
    <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/"/>.
   </para>

   <para condition="unmaintained">
    The support period for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1 has ended. To
    keep systems secure and supported, upgrade to a current SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server version. Before starting the upgrade, make sure to apply
    all maintenance updates.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <section xml:id="rn-about">
  <title>About the Release Notes</title>
  <para>
   The most recent version of the Release Notes is available online at
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   These Release Notes are identical across all supported architectures.
  </para>
  <para>
   Entries can be listed multiple times if they are important and belong to
   multiple sections.
  </para>
  <para>
   Release notes usually only list changes that happened between two subsequent
   releases. Certain important entries from the release notes documents of
   previous product versions may be repeated. To make such entries easier to
   identify, they contain a note to that effect.
  </para>
  <para>
   Repeated entries are provided as a courtesy only. Therefore, if you are
   skipping one or more service packs, check the release notes of the skipped
   service packs as well. If you are only reading the release notes of the
   current release, you could miss important changes.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="Intro">
  <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</title>
  <remark> SLE definition: general information </remark>
  <!-- bsc#1099635 -->
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1 is a multimodal operating system that
   paves the way for IT transformation in the software-defined era. The modern
   and modular OS helps simplify multimodal IT, makes traditional IT
   infrastructure efficient and provides an engaging platform for developers.
   As a result, you can easily deploy and transition business-critical
   workloads across on-premise and public cloud environments.
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1, with its multimodal design, helps
   organizations transform their IT landscape by bridging traditional and
   software-defined infrastructure.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Interoperability">
   <title>Interoperability and Hardware Support</title>
   <para>
    Designed for interoperability, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server integrates into
    classical Unix and Windows environments, supports open standard interfaces
    for systems management, and has been certified for IPv6 compatibility.
   </para>
   <para>
    This modular, general purpose operating system runs on four processor
    architectures and is available with optional extensions that provide
    advanced capabilities for tasks such as real time computing and high
    availability clustering.
   </para>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is optimized to run as a high performing guest
    on leading hypervisors and supports an unlimited number of virtual machines
    per physical system with a single subscription. This makes it the perfect
    guest operating system for virtual computing.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Intro-New" remap="Intro:New">
   <title>What Is New?</title>
   <remark> Marketing POV. </remark>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 introduces many innovative changes compared
    to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12. The most important changes are listed
    below.
   </para>
   <!-- Original version for SLES 15 came in via FATE#324493 -->
   <para>
    Changes to the installation and the module system:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Unified installer:</title>
      <para>
       All SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 products can be installed by the same
       unified installer media. For information about available modules, see
       <xref linkend="Intro-Module"/>.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Installation without network using Packages media:</title>
      <para>
       To install without network connection, all necessary packages are
       available on the Packages medium. This medium consists of directories
       with module repositories which need to be added manually as needed. RMT
       (Repository Mirroring Tool) and SUSE Manager provide additional options
       for disconnected or managed installation.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Migration from openSUSE Leap to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server:</title>
      <para>
       Starting with SLE 15, we support migrating from openSUSE Leap 15 to SUSE
       Linux Enterprise Server 15. Even if you decide to start out with the
       free community distribution you can later easily upgrade to a
       distribution with enterprise-class support.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Extended package search:</title>
      <para>
       Use the new Zypper command <command>zypper search-packages</command> to
       search across all SUSE repositories available for your product even if
       they are not yet enabled. This functionality makes it easier for
       administrators and system architects to find the software packages
       needed. To do so, it leverages the SUSE Customer Center.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Software Development Kit:</title>
      <para>
       With SLE 15, the Software Development Kit is now integrated into the
       products. Development packages are packaged alongside regular packages.
       In addition, the <emphasis>Development Tools</emphasis> module contains
       the tools for development.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>RMT replaces SMT:</title>
      <para>
       SMT (Subscription Management Tool) has been removed. Instead, RMT
       (Repository Mirroring Tool) now allows mirroring SUSE repositories and
       custom repositories. You can then register systems directly with RMT. In
       environments with tightened security, RMT can also proxy other RMT
       servers. If you are planning to migrate SLE 12 clients to version 15,
       RMT is the supported product to handle such migrations. If you still
       need to use SMT for these migrations, beware that the migrated clients
       will have <emphasis>all</emphasis> installation modules enabled.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Major updates to the software selection:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Salt:</title>
      <para>
       SLE 15 SP1 can be managed via salt to help integration into up-to-date
       management solutions, such as SUSE Manager.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para/>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Python 3:</title>
      <para>
       As the first enterprise distribution, SLE 15 offers full support for
       Python 3 development in addition to Python 2.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para/>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Directory Server:</title>
      <para>
       389 Directory Server replaces OpenLDAP to provide a sustainable
       directory service.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <!-- FIXME: This may become true later on. - sknorr, 2017-10-20 -->
  <!--<section id="Intro-Certification">
   <title>Security, Standards, and Certification</title>
   <para>&product; &this-version; has been submitted to the certification bodies for:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Common Criteria Certification, see
   <ulink url="https://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/"/>
   </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   FIPS 140-2 validation, see
   <ulink url="http://csrc.nist.gov/groups/STM/cmvp/documents/140-1/140InProcess.pdf"/>
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
   For more information about certification, see
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/security/certificates.html"/>.
   </para>
   </section> -->
  <section xml:id="Intro-Important">
   <title>Important Sections of This Document</title>
   <para>
    If you are upgrading from a previous SUSE Linux Enterprise Server release,
    you should review at least the following sections:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="Intro-Support"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="InstUpgrade-Upgrade"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="TechInfo"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Lifecycle">
   <title>Support and Life Cycle</title>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is backed by award-winning support from SUSE,
    an established technology leader with a proven history of delivering
    enterprise-quality support services.
   </para>
   <!-- bnc#821338, bnc#828478, bnc#882262 -->
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 has a 13-year life cycle, with 10 years of
    General Support and 3 years of Extended Support. The current version (SP1)
    will be fully maintained and supported until 6 months after the release of
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP2.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you need additional time to design, validate and test your upgrade
    plans, Long Term Service Pack Support can extend the support duration. You
    can buy an additional 12 to 36 months in twelve month increments. This
    means, you receive a total of 3 to 5 years of support per Service Pack.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, check our Support Policy page
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/policy.html"/> or the Long
    Term Service Pack Support Page
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/programs/long-term-service-pack-support.html"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</title>
   <para>
    To receive support, you need an appropriate subscription with SUSE. For
    more information, see
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/programs/subscriptions/?id=SUSE_Linux_Enterprise_Server"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The following definitions apply:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L1</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem determination, which means technical support designed to provide
       compatibility information, usage support, ongoing maintenance,
       information gathering and basic troubleshooting using available
       documentation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L2</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem isolation, which means technical support designed to analyze
       data, reproduce customer problems, isolate problem area and provide a
       resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1 or prepare for Level 3.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>L3</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Problem resolution, which means technical support designed to resolve
       problems by engaging engineering to resolve product defects which have
       been identified by Level 2 Support.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    For contracted customers and partners, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1
    and its modules are delivered with L3 support for all packages, except for
    the following:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Technology Previews
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Sound, graphics, fonts and artwork
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Packages that require an additional customer contract
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Some packages shipped as part of the module <emphasis>Workstation
      Extension</emphasis> are L2-supported only
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Packages with names ending in <package>-devel</package> (containing
      header files and similar developer resources) will only be supported
      together with their main packages.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    SUSE will only support the usage of original packages. That is, packages
    that are unchanged and not recompiled.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Support-General">
   <title>General Support</title>
   <para>
    To learn about supported kernel, virtualization, and file system features,
    as well as supported Java versions, see <xref linkend="TechInfo"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Support-External">
   <title>Software Requiring Specific Contracts</title>
   <para>
    Certain software delivered as part of SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 SP1 may
    require an external contract. Check the support status of individual
    packages using the RPM metadata that can be viewed with
    <literal>rpm</literal>, <literal>zypper</literal>, or YaST.
   </para>
   <para>
    Major packages and groups of packages affected by this are:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PostgreSQL (all versions, including all subpackages)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Intro-License-AGPL">
   <title>Software Under GNU AGPL</title>
   <!-- see jsc#SLE-7191-->
   <para>
    SLES 15 SP1 (and the SLE modules) includes the following software that is
    shipped <emphasis>only</emphasis> under a GNU AGPL software license:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Ghostscript (including subpackages)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    SLES 15 SP1 (and the SLE modules) includes the following software that is
    shipped under multiple licenses that include a GNU AGPL software license:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      ArgyllCMS
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>cloud-init</command>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      MySpell dictionaries and LightProof
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <!-- see fate#316990 -->
  <section xml:id="Intro-Documentation">
   <title>Documentation and Other Information</title>
   <para/>
   <!-- Rethink use of the word media here. There is just one installation
    medium. - sknorr, 2017-10-20 -->
   <section xml:id="Intro-Documentation-Media">
    <title>Available on the Product Media</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Read the READMEs on the media.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Get the detailed change log information about a particular package from
       the RPM (where <filename>&lt;FILENAME&gt;.rpm</filename> is the name of
       the RPM):
      </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp &lt;FILENAME&gt;.rpm</screen>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
       media for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated
       packages.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of the
       media of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1. This directory includes
       PDF versions of the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1 Installation
       Quick Start Guide.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="Intro-Documentation-External">
    <title>Online Documentation</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For the most up-to-date version of the documentation for SUSE Linux
       Enterprise Server 15 SP1, see
       <phrase condition="beta;pre"><link xlink:href="https://susedoc.github.io/doc-sle/develop"/>
       (draft
       version)</phrase><phrase condition="maintained;unmaintained"><link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/"/></phrase>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find a collection of White Papers in the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
       Resource Library at
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/server/resource-library"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="Intro-ModuleExtensionRelated">
  <title>Modules, Extensions, and Related Products</title>
  <para>
   This section comprises information about modules and extensions for SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1. Modules and extensions add parts or
   functionality to the system.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Module">
   <title>Modules in the SLE 15 SP1 Product Line</title>
   <para>
    The SLE 15 SP1 product line is made up of modules that contain software
    packages. Each module has a clearly defined scope. Modules differ in their
    life cycles and update timelines.
   </para>
   <para>
    The modules available within the product line based on SUSE Linux
    Enterprise 15 SP1 at the release of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1 are
    listed in the Modules and Extensions Quick Start at
    <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/html/SLES-all/art-modules.html"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Not all SLE modules are available with a subscription for SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server 15 SP1 itself (see the column <emphasis>Available
    for</emphasis>).
   </para>
   <para>
    For information about the availability of individual packages within
    modules, see <link xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/packages"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Extension">
   <title>Available Extensions</title>
   <para>
    Extensions add extra functionality to the system and require their own
    registration key, usually at additional cost. Usually, extensions have
    their own release notes documents that are available from
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The following extensions are available for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15
    SP1:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Live Patching:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/live-patching"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/highavailability"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Workstation Extension:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/workstation-extension"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    <!-- FIXME: list with a single item. - sknorr, 2017-10-20 -->
    Additionally, there is the following extension which is not covered by SUSE
    support agreements, available at no additional cost and without an extra
    registration key:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Package Hub: <link xlink:href="https://packagehub.suse.com/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Derived-Products">
   <title>Derived and Related Products</title>
   <remark> Marketing POV. </remark>
   <para>
    This sections lists derived and related products. Usually, these products
    have their own release notes documents that are available from
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE JeOS: <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/server/jeos"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/desktop"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise for High-Performance Computing:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/server/hpc"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Real Time:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/realtime"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Manager:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-manager"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
 </section>
 <!-- ============================================================== -->
 <!-- =============== Technical Part Starts Here =================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================== -->
 <section xml:id="Intro-Support-Techpreviews-Overview">
  <title>Technology Previews</title>
  <para>
   Technology previews are packages, stacks, or features delivered by SUSE
   which are not supported. They may be functionally incomplete, unstable or in
   other ways not suitable for production use. They are included for your
   convenience and give you a chance to test new technologies within an
   enterprise environment.
  </para>
  <para>
   Whether a technology preview becomes a fully supported technology later
   depends on customer and market feedback. Technology previews can be dropped
   at any time and SUSE does not commit to providing a supported version of
   such technologies in the future.
  </para>
  <para>
   Give your SUSE representative feedback about technology previews, including
   your experience and use case.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="Intro-Support-Techpreviews">
   <title>Technology Previews for All Architectures</title>
   <para/>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="bsc-1176440">
    <title><literal>schedutil</literal></title>
    <para>
     <literal>schedutil</literal> is a CPU frequency scaling governor that
     makes decisions based on the utilization data provided by the scheduler,
     as opposed to other governors that use CPU idle time, such as
     <literal>ondemand</literal>. It was introduced in the Linux kernel version
     4.7. However, it is only viable for production use together with an
     optimization called <literal>util_est</literal> (short for "utilization
     estimation") that makes it much more responsive. This optimization is only
     available in Linux kernel version 4.17 and newer. For this reason it is
     only offered as technology preview in SLE 15 SP1.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3251">
    <title>Active Directory Domain Controller Support</title>
    <para>
     Support for the Active Directory (AD) Domain Controller (DC) has been
     added. Note that the Samba DC can only handle a subset of AD environments.
    </para>
    <para>
     The list of related packages:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       samba-dsdb-modules
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       samba-ad-dc
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       python-tdb
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       python-tevent
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       samba-python
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="bsc-1144071" role="notoc">
    <title>Using Atomic Updates With the System Role Transactional Server</title>
    <para>
     As a technology preview, the installer supports the system role
     <emphasis>Transactional Server</emphasis>. This system role features an
     update system that applies updates atomically (as a single operation) and
     makes them easy to revert should that become necessary. These features are
     based on the package management tools that all other SUSE and openSUSE
     distributions also rely on. This means that the vast majority of RPM
     packages that work with other system roles of SLES 15 SP1 also work with
     the system role <emphasis>Transactional Server</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information, see the documentation at
     <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/html/SLES-all/cha-transactional-updates.html"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <!--<section id="Intro-Support-Techpreviews-AArch64">
   <title>Technology Previews for AArch64 (ARMv8)</title>
   <para/>
   </section>-->
  <section xml:id="Intro-Support-Techpreviews-x86-64">
   <title>Technology Previews for AMD64/Intel 64 64-Bit (x86_64)</title>
   <para/>
   <section xml:id="jsc-SLE-11271" role="notoc">
    <title>Nested Virtualization in KVM</title>
    <para>
     As a technology preview, KVM in SLES 15 SP1 supports nested
     virtualization, that is, KVM guests running within other KVM guests.
     Nested virtualization has advantages in scenarios such as the following:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For managing own virtual machines directly with your hypervisor of
       choice in cloud environments.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For enabling the live migration of hypervisors and their guest virtual
       machines as a single entity.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For software development and testing.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
  <!--<section id="Intro-Support-Techpreviews-SystemZ">
   <title>Technology Previews for &ibmz; (s390x)</title>
   <para/>
   </section>-->
  <!--<section id="Intro-Support-Techpreviews-Power">
   <title>Technology Previews for POWER (ppc64le)</title>
   <para/>
   </section>-->
 </section>
 <section xml:id="InstUpgrade">
  <title>Installation and Upgrade</title>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Server can be deployed in several ways:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Physical machine
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Virtual host
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Virtual machine
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     System containers
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Application containers
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <section xml:id="InstUpgrade-Installation" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
   <title>Installation</title>
   <para>
    This section includes information related to the initial installation of
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Installation Documentation</title>
    <para>
     The following release notes contain additional notes regarding the
     installation of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. However, they do not
     document the installation procedure itself.
    </para>
    <para>
     For installation documentation, see <citetitle>Deployment
     Guide</citetitle> at
     <phrase condition="maintained;unmaintained"><link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1//singlehtml/book_sle_deployment/book_sle_deployment.html"/></phrase><phrase condition="beta;pre"><link xlink:href="https://susedoc.github.io/doc-sle/develop/SLES-deployment/html/"/>
     (draft version)</phrase>.
    </para>
   </important>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327902" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327902" -->
    <title>Intel Rapid Storage Controller: NVMe Drive Is Not Accessible in UEFI Mode</title>
    <para>
     On a machine equipped with an Intel Rapid Storage Controller, an NVMe
     drive and at least one other hard drive, the NVMe device is not visible in
     EFI boot mode. It is only visible in legacy boot mode, but cannot be
     accessed in the installed system.
    </para>
    <para>
     The Intel Rapid Storage Controller has RAID enabled by default. This
     setting is not supported with this device on Linux. Switch to
     <literal>AHCI</literal> in the EFI settings for SATA to be able to access
     the NVMe drive during the installation and in the installed system.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327899" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327899" -->
    <title>Installing on a System Combining Multipath with RAID</title>
    <para>
     An installation on a system combining multipath with RAID stops with the
     error message "Unexpected situation found in the system".
    </para>
    <para>
     If you use a setup combining multipath with RAID and the installer does
     not detect your setup correctly, try the boot option
     <literal>autoassembly=0</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327755" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327755" -->
    <title>JeOS Images for Hyper-V and VMware Are Now Compressed</title>
    <para>
     We are providing different virtual disk images for JeOS, using the
     <literal>.qcow2</literal>, <literal>.vhdx</literal>, and
     <literal>.vmdk</literal> file formats respectively for KVM, Xen,
     OpenStack, Hyper-V, and VMware environments. All JeOS images are setting
     up the same disk size (24 GB) for the JeOS system but due to the nature of
     the different file formats, the size of the JeOS images were different.
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with SLE 15 SP1, the JeOS images for Hyper-V and VMware using the
     <literal>.vhdx</literal> and <literal>.vmdk</literal> file formats
     respectively are now compressed with the LZMA2 compression algorithm by
     default. Therefore, we are now delivering these images in a
     <literal>.xz</literal> file format, so you need to decompress the image
     before using them in your Hyper-V or VMware environment, for example,
     using the <literal>unxz</literal> command.
    </para>
    <para>
     The other JeOS images will remain uncompressed because the
     <literal>.qcow2</literal> format already optimize the size of the images.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325541" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325541" -->
    <title>CD/DVD Repositories Will Be Disabled After Installation</title>
    <para>
     In previous versions of SLE, enabled CD/DVD repositories would block
     upgrades if the media was removed after installation.
    </para>
    <para>
     CD/DVD repositories are now set to disabled when the installation process
     is finished.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InstUpgrade-Upgrade" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
   <title>Upgrade-Related Notes</title>
   <para>
    This section includes upgrade-related information for SUSE Linux Enterprise
    Server 15 SP1.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Upgrade Documentation</title>
    <para>
     The following release notes contain additional notes regarding the upgrade
     of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. However, they do not document the upgrade
     procedure itself.
    </para>
    <para>
     For upgrade documentation, see
     <phrase condition="maintained;unmaintained"><link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1//singlehtml/book_sle_upgrade/book_sle_upgrade.html"/></phrase><phrase condition="beta;pre"><link xlink:href="https://susedoc.github.io/doc-sle/develop/SLES-upgrade/html/"/>
     (draft version)</phrase>.
    </para>
   </important>
   <section xml:id="bsc-1178261">
    <title>Differences Between AutoYaST Profiles in SLE 12 and 15</title>
    <para>
     Significant changes in SLE 15 required changes in AutoYaST. If you want to
     reuse existing SLE 12 profiles with SLE 15, you need to adjust them as
     documented in
     <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP2/html/SLES-all/appendix-ay-12vs15.html"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326567" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326567" -->
    <title>Product Registration Changes for HPC Customers</title>
    <tip role="compact">
     <para>
      This entry has appeared in a previous release notes document.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
     For SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, there was a High Performance Computing
     subscription named "SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for HPC" (SLES for HPC).
     With SLE 15, this subscription does not exist anymore and has been
     replaced. The equivalent subscription is named "SUSE Linux Enterprise High
     Performance Computing" (SLE-HPC) and requires a different license key.
     Because of this requirement, a SLES for HPC 12 system will by default
     upgrade to a regular "SUSE Linux Enterprise Server".
    </para>
    <para>
     To properly upgrade a SLES for HPC system to a SLE-HPC, the system needs
     to be converted to SLE-HPC first. SUSE provides a tool to simplify this
     conversion by performing the product conversion and switch to the SLE-HPC
     subscription. However, the tool does not perform the upgrade itself.
    </para>
    <para>
     When run without extra parameters, the script assumes that the SLES for
     HPC subscription is valid and not expired. If the subscription has
     expired, you need to provide a valid registration key for SLE-HPC.
    </para>
    <para>
     The script reads the current set of registered modules and extensions and
     after the system has been converted to SLE-HPC, it tries to add them
     again.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Providing a Registration Key to the Conversion Script</title>
     <para>
      The script cannot restore the previous registration state if the supplied
      registration key is incorrect or invalid.
     </para>
    </important>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To install the script, run <literal>zypper in
       switch_sles_sle-hpc</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Execute the script from the command line as <literal>root</literal>:
      </para>
<screen>switch_sles_sle-hpc -e &lt;REGISTRATION_EMAIL&gt; -r &lt;NEW_REGISTRATION_KEY&gt;</screen>
      <para>
       The parameters <literal>-e</literal> and <literal>-r</literal> are only
       required if the previous registration has expired, otherwise they are
       optional. To run the script in batch mode, add the option
       <literal>-y</literal>. It answers all questions with
       <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     For more information, see the man page
     <literal>switch_sles_sle-hpc(8)</literal> and
     <literal>README.SUSE</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325293" remap="InstUpgrade:Upgrade">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325293" -->
    <title>Modules That Are Automatically Selected During Upgrade</title>
    <para>
     When upgrading to SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 from a previous version, all
     modules in SLE 15 were activated by default. This behavior has changed in
     SLE 15 SP1, where only selected modules are activated automatically.
    </para>
    <para>
     Depending on the SLE product, different modules are activated
     automatically upon upgrade.
    </para>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Upgrade from SLES 11/12 to SLES 15 SP1 or Higher</bridgehead>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Base System Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Desktop Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Legacy Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Server Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Web &amp; Scripting Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Development Tools Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Upgrade from SLED 12 to SLED 15 SP1 or Higher</bridgehead>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Base System Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Workstation Extension
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Desktop Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Upgrade from SLES-SAP 11/12 to SLES-SAP 15 SP1 or Higher</bridgehead>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       High Availability Extension
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Base System Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Desktop Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SAP Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Server Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Legacy Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Upgrade from SLES 12 or SLE-HPC 12 to SLE-HPC 15 SP1 or Higher</bridgehead>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Base System Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Desktop Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       HPC Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Server Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Development Tools Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Web an Scripting Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Legacy Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Upgrade from SLE-RT 12 to SLE-RT 15 SP1 or Higher</bridgehead>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Base System Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Desktop Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Real Time Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Server Applications Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Development Tools Module
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InstUpgrade-More">
   <title>For More Information</title>
   <para>
    For more information, see <xref linkend="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent"/>
    and the sections relating to your respective hardware architecture.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <!-- Arch Independent -->
 <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent">
  <title>Architecture Independent Information</title>
  <remark> This is highly technical * Know issues categorized ** full description of the problem **
   how to reproduce the issue ** link to Bugzilla number ** command line change/configuration change
   ** work around if available
  </remark>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to all architectures supported by SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Kernel" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
   <title>Kernel</title>
   <para />
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-22593">
    <title>Unprivileged eBPF usage has been disabled</title>
    <para>
      A large amount of security issues was found and fixed in the Extended
      Berkeley Packet Filter (eBPF) code. To reduce the attack surface, its
      usage has been restricted to privileged users only.
    </para>
    <para>
     Privileged users include <literal>root</literal>. Programs with the
     <literal>CAP_BPF</literal> capability in the newer versions of the Linux
     kernel can still use eBPF as-is.
    </para>
    <para>
     To check the privileged state, you can check the value of the
     <literal>/proc/sys/kernel/unprivileged_bpf_disabled</literal>
     parameter. Value of 0 means "unprivileged enable", and value of 2 means
     "only privileged users enabled".
    </para>
    <para>
     This setting can be changed by the <literal>root</literal> user:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       to enable it temporarily for all users by running the command
       <literal>sysctl kernel.unprivileged_bpf_disabled=0</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       to enable it permanently by adding
       <literal>kernel.unprivileged_bpf_disabled=0</literal>
       to the
       <literal>/etc/sysctl.conf</literal>
       file.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327900" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327900" -->
    <title>Device Error Prevention Enabled (CONFIG_IO_STRICT_DEVMEM)</title>
    <para>
     With SLE 15, the kernel build option
     <literal>CONFIG_IO_STRICT_DEVMEM</literal> has been enabled to prevent
     device errors. This option disables tampering with device state while a
     kernel driver is using the device.
    </para>
    <para>
     Unfortunately, some vendor tools currently use such functionality. If you
     depend on such a tool, make sure to set the kernel boot parameter
     <literal>iomem=relaxed</literal>. Among others, this affects several
     firmware flash tools for POWER9 machines.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326981" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326981" -->
    <title>IOMMU Passthrough Is Now Default on All Architectures</title>
    <para>
     Passthrough mode provides improved I/O performance, especially for
     high-speed devices, because DMA remapping is not needed for the host
     (bare-metal or hypervisor).
    </para>
    <para>
     IOMMU passthrough is now enabled by default in SUSE Linux Enterprise
     products. Therefore, you no longer need to add <literal>iommu=pt</literal>
     (Intel 64/AMD64) or <literal>iommu.passthrough=on</literal> (AArch64) on
     the kernel command line. To disable passthrough mode, use
     <literal>iommu=nopt</literal> (Intel 64/AMD64) or
     <literal>iommu.passthrough=off</literal> (AArch64), respectively.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326705" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326705" -->
    <title>The Driver i40evf Has Been Renamed to iavf</title>
    <para>
     Starting with SLE 15 SP1, the module name of the Intel Ethernet Adaptive
     Virtual Function driver changes from <literal>i40evf</literal> to
     <literal>iavf</literal>. This new naming is consistent with the mainline
     Linux kernel and also helps better convey its status as the universal
     Virtual Function driver for multiple product lines.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326308" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Memory Management"; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326308" -->
    <title>New sysctl Option to Configure NUMA Statistics</title>
    <para>
     Generating NUMA page allocator statistics can create considerable
     overhead.
    </para>
    <para>
     To allow avoiding this overhead under certain circumstances, the sysctl
     option <literal>vm.numa_stat</literal> has been added. By default, it is
     set to <literal>1</literal>, meaning NUMA page allocator statistics will
     be generated.
    </para>
    <para>
     For workloads where it is desirable to remove the overhead of these
     statistics, such as high-speed networking, disable the NUMA page allocator
     statistics by setting <literal>vm.numa_stat</literal> to
     <literal>0</literal>. The statistics in <literal>/proc/vmstat</literal>,
     such as <literal>numa_hit</literal> and <literal>numa_miss</literal> will
     then be reset to <literal>0</literal> and stop increasing, until the
     functionality is enabled again.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Security" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
   <title>Security</title>
   <para />
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-17083" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
    <title><literal>sudo</literal> has been updated</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>sudo</literal> package has been updated to the version 1.8.27.
     Among others, there are the following notable changes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>PAM account management modules and BSD authentication approval modules
      are now run even when no password is required.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>The LDAP and SSS back-ends now use the same rule evaluation code as the
      <literal>sudoers</literal> file backend.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>On systems using PAM, <literal>sudo</literal> now ignores the
      <literal>PAM_NEW_AUTHTOK_REQD</literal> and
      <literal>PAM_AUTHTOK_EXPIRED</literal> errors from PAM account management
      if authentication is disabled for the user.</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326986" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326986" -->
    <title>LUKS2 Support for pam_mount</title>
    <para>
     The pam_mount tool now supports the handling of LUKS2 encrypted volumes
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="bsc-1174679">
    <title>Seccheck Scripts Controlled by systemd Timers</title>
    <para>
     In SLE 15 GA, <command>seccheck</command> scripts were run from cron.
     Starting with SLE 15 SP1 seccheck scripts are not run from cron, but are
     controlled with systemd timers. (Also see the updated
     <command>seccheck</command> documentation at
     <link
      xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/html/SLES-all/cha-security-protection.html#sec-sec-prot-general-seccheck" />).
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Network" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
   <title>Networking</title>
   <para />
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-4261">
    <title>firewalld not Available on the OpenStack JeOS Image</title>
    <para>
     Having a firewall inside an instance is unnecessary and confusing in an
     OpenStack environment because OpenStack provides security and network
     capabilities on a different level. For example, it uses security groups
     which block any incoming connection (including ICMP, UDP, and TCP) by
     default. The OpenStack Administrator needs to explicitly enable ICMP and
     TCP via the security groups configuration to ping and SSH into an
     instance.
    </para>
    <para>
     The official OpenStack recommendation for Linux-based images is to disable
     any firewalls inside the image (see
     <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/image-guide/openstack-images.html" />).
     Therefore the firewalld package has been removed from OpenStack JeOS
     images.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-16552">
    <title>389 Directory Server Is the Primary LDAP Server, the OpenLDAP Server Is Deprecated</title>
    <para>
     The OpenLDAP server (package <package>openldap2</package>, part of the
     <emphasis>Legacy</emphasis> SLE module) is deprecated and will be removed
     from SLES 15 SP4. The OpenLDAP client libraries are widely used for LDAP
     integrations and and are compatible with 389 Directory Server. Hence, the
     OpenLDAP client libraries and command-line tools will continue to be
     supported on SLES 15 to provide an easier transition for customers that
     currently use the OpenLDAP Server.
    </para>
    <para>
     To replace OpenLDAP server, SLES includes 389 Directory Server. 389
     Directory Server (package <package>389-ds</package>) is a fully-featured
     LDAPv3-compliant server suited for modern environments and for very large
     LDAP deployments. 389 Directory Server also comes with command-line tools
     of its own.
    </para>
    <para>
     For information about setting up and upgrading to 389 Directory Server,
     see the
     <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles-15/html/SLES-all/cha-security-ldap.html">SLES 15
     Security Guide, chapter LDAP&mdash;A Directory Service</link>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327898" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327898" -->
    <title>Intel* Omni-Path Architecture (OPA) Host Software</title>
    <para>
     Intel Omni-Path Architecture (OPA) host software is fully supported in
     SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1. Intel OPA provides Host Fabric
     Interface (HFI) hardware with initialization and setup for high
     performance data transfers (high bandwidth, high message rate, low
     latency) between compute and I/O nodes in a clustered environment.
    </para>
    <para>
     For documentation about installing Intel Omni-Path Architecture, see
     <link
      xlink:href="https://www.intel.com/content/dam/support/us/en/documents/network-and-i-o/fabric-products/Intel_OP_Software_SLES_15_1_RN_K51384.pdf" />.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325872" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325872" -->
    <title>resolv.conf Is Now Located in /run</title>
    <para>
     Starting with SLE 15 SP1, both Wicked and NetworkManager will write the
     file <literal>resolv.conf</literal> into the <literal>/run</literal>
     directory instead of in <literal>/etc</literal>.
     <literal>/etc/resolv.conf</literal> will still exist as a symbolic link.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-324447" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324447" -->
    <title>OpenID Authentication Module for Apache2</title>
    <para>
     With <literal>mod_auth_openidc</literal> a certified OpenID authentication
     module has been added for Apache2.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-11184">
    <title>New GeoIP Database Sources</title>
    <para>
     The GeoIP database allows approximately geo-locating users by their IP
     address. In the past, the company MaxMind made such data available for
     free in its GeoLite Legacy databases. On January 2, 2019, MaxMind
     discontinued the GeoLite Legacy databases, now offering only the newer
     GeoLite2 databases for download. To comply with new data protection
     regulation, since December 30, 2019, GeoLite2 database users are required
     to comply with an additional usage license. This change means users now
     need to register for a MaxMind account and obtain a license key to
     download GeoLite2 databases. For more information about these changes, see
     the
     <link xlink:href="https://blog.maxmind.com/2019/12/18/significant-changes-to-accessing-and-using-geolite2-databases/">MaxMind
     blog</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
     SLES includes the <package>GeoIP</package> package of tools that are only
     compatible with GeoLite Legacy databases. As an update to SLES 15 SP1, we
     introduce the following new packages to deal with the changes to the
     GeoLite service:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>libmaxminddb</command>: A library for working with the GeoLite2
       format.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>geoipupdate</command>: The official Maxmind tool for
       downloading GeoLite2 databases. To use this tool, set up the
       configuration file with your MaxMind account details. This configuration
       file can also be generated on the Maxmind web page. For more
       information, see
       <link xlink:href="https://dev.maxmind.com/geoip/geoip2/geolite2/" />.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>geolite2legacy</command>: A script for converting GeoLite2 CSV
       data to the GeoLite Legacy format.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>geoipupdate-legacy</command>: A convenience script that
       downloads GeoLite2 data, converts it to the GeoLite Legacy format, and
       stores it in <filename>/var/lib/GeoIP</filename>. With this script,
       applications developed for use with the legacy
       <command>geoip-fetch</command> tool will continue to work.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The following SLES packages use GeoIP data in the GeoLite2 format:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <package>bind</package>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <package>nginx</package>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <package>wireshark</package>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-SystemsManagement" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
   <title>Systems Management</title>
   <para />
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3443">
    <title><literal>dmidecode</literal> Has Been Updated</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>dmidecode</literal> package has been updated version 3.2.
    </para>
    <para>
     One of the changes in this update is support for SMBIOS 3.2.0. This
     includes new processor names, new socket and port connector types, new
     system slot state and property, and support for non-volatile memory
     (NVDIMM).
    </para>
    <para>
     For the full changelog, see
     <literal>/usr/share/doc/packages/dmidecode/NEWS</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3990">
    <title>Bcache Support in YaST Partitioner</title>
    <para>
     Support for the Bcache technology has been added to the YaST Partitioner.
    </para>
    <para>
     Bcache is a Linux technology that allows improving the performance of a
     big, relatively slow storage device using a faster, smaller device.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3613">
    <title>Intel DIMM Management Software Has Been Updated</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>ipmctl</literal> package has been updated to version
     01.00.00.3440. This package includes the previously separate
     <literal>safeclib</literal> package. The previously separate management
     packages <literal>ixpdimm_sw</literal> and
     <literal>invm-frameworks</literal> were obsoleted by
     <literal>ipmctl</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327756" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327756" -->
    <title>Chrony Is Now Installed by Default on JeOS and Raspberry Pi Images</title>
    <para>
     Manual correction of the system time can lead to severe problems because,
     for example, a backward leap can cause malfunction of critical
     applications. Within a network, it is usually necessary to synchronize the
     system time of all machines, but manual time adjustment is a bad approach.
    </para>
    <para>
     SLE 15 SP1 JeOS and Raspberry Pi images now include Chrony by default.
     This allow our images to follow the SLES 15 SP1 guidance to use Chrony for
     time synchronization. For more information, see
     <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/html/SLES-all/cha-ntp.html" />.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325513" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325513" -->
    <title>Zypper and the --no-recommends Option</title>
    <para>
     Due to a trend toward minimal systems, systems are increasingly installed
     with the command-line parameter <literal>--no-recommends</literal> or the
     configuration option <literal>solver.onlyRequires = true</literal> in
     <literal>/etc/zypp/zypp.conf</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Unfortunately this option also prevented the autoselection of appropriate
     driver or language supporting packages.
    </para>
    <para>
     This flaw is fixed with libzypp 17.10.2 and Zypper 1.14.18:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The use of <literal>--no-recommends</literal> should no longer affect
       the selection of driver and language supporting packages.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>zypper inr --no-recommends</literal> should add missing driver
       and language-support packages only but omit all other recommends.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-319428" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319428" -->
    <title>Support for Socket-Based Services Activation</title>
    <para>
     Systemd allows for new ways of starting services, such as the so-called
     socket-based activation. Services which are configured to be started on
     demand will not run until it is needed, for example, when a new request
     comes in.
    </para>
    <para>
     The YaST Services Manager has been extended to allow setting services to
     be started on-demand. Currently, only a subset of services supports this
     configuration. The current start mode is displayed in the column
     <emphasis>Start</emphasis> of the YaST Services Manager. In the drop-down
     box <emphasis>Start Mode</emphasis> of the YaST Services Manager, the mode
     <emphasis>On-demand</emphasis> will only be shown when it is available for
     the selected service.
    </para>
    <para>
     Additionally, the table column <emphasis>Active</emphasis> has been
     adapted to show the correct value provided by systemd.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Performance" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
   <title>Performance Related Information</title>
   <para />
   <section xml:id="jsc-SLE-6762">
    <title><literal>supportconfig</literal> filename has been changed</title>
    <para>
     The filenames generated by the <literal>supportconfig</literal> tool have
     been changed. The previously used prefix of <literal>nts_</literal> has
     been changed to <literal>scc_</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="jsc-SLE-12168">
    <title><literal>supportconfig</literal> SAP plugin has been added</title>
    <para>
     A SAP plugin for <literal>supportconfig</literal> has been added. This
     plugin collects information about SAP applications to enhance support for
     SAP customers.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326121" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326121" -->
    <title>The OProfile Package Has Been Updated</title>
    <para>
     The OProfile package has been updated with the following new features:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Updated CPU type detection for POWER9 models.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Fix for a OProfile crash when processing data collected on an exiting
       process (affects all architectures).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325696" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325696" -->
    <title>LLVM Update</title>
    <para>
     LLVM has been updated to version 7.0.1 providing several optimizations.
     Refer to
     <link xlink:href="http://releases.llvm.org/7.0.0/docs/ReleaseNotes.html" />
     for details. LLVM 5 is still shipped for compatibility reasons with the
     Legacy module.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Storage" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
   <title>Storage</title>
   <para />
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326969">
    <title>NVDIMM Support</title>
    <para>
     SLES 15 supports persistent memory (NVDIMM) technologies, such as Intel
     AEP, on certified hardware and for certified ISV applications,
     specifically in memory databases, in cooperation with SUSE's hardware and
     software partners.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327579" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327579" -->
    <title>SMB Shares Used via mount or /etc/fstab Are Now Expected to use SMB 2.1 or Higher</title>
    <para>
     The first version of the SMB network protocol, SMB1 is an old and insecure
     protocol and has been deprecated by its originator Microsoft (also see
     <link xlink:href="https://aka.ms/smb1rs3">SMBv1 is not installed by
     default</link>,
     <link xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20190227091836/https://blogs.technet.microsoft.com/filecab/2016/09/16/stop-using-smb1/">Stop
     Using SMB1</link>). For security reasons, the SLE 15 SP1 kernel has been
     changed in a way that the SMB kernel module (<literal>cifs.ko</literal> /
     <literal>mount.cifs</literal>) in a way that will break some existing
     setups: By default, the <literal>mount</literal> command on will now only
     mount SMB shares using newer protocol versions by default, namely SMB 2.1,
     SMB 3.0, or SMB 3.02.
    </para>
    <para>
     Note that this change does not affect your installed Samba server or
     <literal>smbclient</literal> programs.
    </para>
    <para>
     If possible, use an SMB 2.1 server. Depending on your SMB server, you may
     have to enable SMB 2.1 specifically:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Windows has offered SMB 2.1 support since Windows 7 and Windows Server
       2008 and it is enabled by default.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you are using a Samba server, make sure SMB 2.1 is enabled on it. To
       do so, set the global parameter <literal>server max protocol</literal>
       in <literal>/etc/samba/smb.conf</literal> to <literal>SMB2_10</literal>
       (for more possible values, see <literal>man smb.conf</literal>).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     If your SMB server does not support any of the modern SMB versions and
     cannot be upgraded or you rely on SMB1's/CIFS's Unix extensions, you can
     mount SMB1 shares even with the current kernel. To do so, explicitly
     enable them using the option <literal>vers=1.0</literal> in your
     <literal>mount</literal> command line (or in
     <literal>/etc/fstab</literal>).
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327156" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327156" -->
    <title>NVMe Multipath Handling</title>
    <para>
     The default state for multipath of NVMe differs for SUSE Linux Enterprise
     12 and 15.
    </para>
    <para>
     In SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, multipath is off by default. In SUSE Linux
     Enterprise 15, multipath is on by default.
    </para>
    <para>
     If the new default behavior does not work in your case, you can override
     it with the kernel command-line option
     <literal>LIBSTORAGE_MULTIPATH_AUTOSTART=ON</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     With multipath activated, the device numbering is independent of physical
     slots.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326479" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326479" -->
    <title>Snapper Output Highlights Mount Status of Snapshots</title>
    <para>
     Previously, <literal>snapper list</literal> did not indicate which
     snapshot was currently mounted and which would be mounted next time.
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with SLE 15 SP1, the output of <literal>snapper list</literal>
     now marks these special snapshots by appending one of the following three
     characters to the snapshot number:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>*</literal> (currently mounted and will be mounted on next
       boot)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>-</literal> (currently mounted)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>+</literal> (will be mounted on next boot)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The snapshot number is now also the first column in the output.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325774" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325774" -->
    <title>Snapper's Space-Aware Snapshot Cleanup Has Been Improved</title>
    <para>
     Previously, the space-aware cleanup of snapshots integrated in Snapper
     only looked at the disk space used by all snapshots. In certain cases,
     this narrow focus meant that the file system ran out of space anyway.
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with SLE 15 SP1, the space-aware cleanup of Snapper additionally
     looks at the free space of the file system and keeps the file system at
     least 20 % free.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-324627" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324627" -->
    <title>NFS Clients Use NFSv4.2 by Default If Supported by the Server</title>
    <para>
     NFSv4.2 is the latest revision of the NFSv4 File Service protocol. It adds
     support for file pre-allocation, "SEEK_HOLE" for efficient management of
     sparse files, and some pNFS improvements.
    </para>
    <para>
     NFSv4.2 is used by default if the server supports it. If you need to use a
     different version by default, adjust <literal>Defaultvers</literal> in
     <literal>/etc/nfsmount.conf</literal> accordingly.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-323843" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Storage">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323843" -->
    <title>Displaying Disk Space Used by Snapper Snapshots</title>
    <para>
     Previously, it was hard to calculate the disk space consumption of an
     individual Btrfs snapshot when the qgroups (quota groups) feature was
     enabled.
    </para>
    <para>
     Starting with SLE 15 SP1, Snapper shows the disk space used by individual
     snapshots when running <literal>snapper list</literal> even if Btrfs
     quotas are enabled.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Drivers">
   <title>Drivers and Hardware</title>
   <para />
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3055">
    <title>Hisilicon Hi1620 SoC Support</title>
    <para>
     Support for the Hisilicon Hi1620 SoC has been added.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3811">
    <title>Sierra Wireless EM7565 Support</title>
    <para>
     Support for the Sierra Wireless EM7565 card has been added. The Linux
     driver name for the card is <literal>libmbim</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="bsc-1122173">
    <title>Pure Userspace X Drivers Are Now Deprecated</title>
    <para>
     Starting with SLES 15 SP1, pure userspace X drivers are considered
     deprecated. In particular, this affects the virtualization-related
     <literal>qxl</literal> and <literal>vmware</literal> userspace X drivers.
     These drivers are still shipped in SLES 15 SP1, but they are no longer
     used by default.
    </para>
    <para>
     Under SLES 15 SP2 and later, only drivers with support for kernel
     mode-setting will continue to work.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Virtualization">
   <title>Virtualization</title>
   <para />
   <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Virtualization-KVM" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
    <title>KVM</title>
    <para />
    <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327889" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327889" -->
     <title>Support for AMD Secure Encrypted Virtualization (SEV)</title>
     <para>
      Having been a technology preview in the previous release, SUSE Linux
      Enterprise Server now fully supports AMD Secure Encrypted Virtualization
      (SEV). SEV integrates main memory encryption capabilities (SME) with the
      existing AMD-V virtualization architecture to support encrypted virtual
      machines. Encrypting virtual machines helps protect them from physical
      threats and other virtual machines or even the hypervisor itself. SEV
      represents a new approach to security that is particularly suited to
      cloud computing where virtual machines may not fully trust the hypervisor
      and administrator of their host system. As with SME, no application
      software modifications are required to support SEV.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327089" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327089" -->
     <title>Update to QEMU 3.1</title>
     <para>
      QEMU has been upgraded to version 3.1.
     </para>
     <para>
      A major new feature in QEMU 3.1 is support for limiting bandwidth used
      during a PostCopy migration. PostCopy means that the migrated VM will
      start running on the destination host as soon as possible. The VM's RAM
      from the source is page-faulted to the destination over time. This
      significantly reduces VM downtime compared to PreCopy, where the
      migration can take a lot of time depending on the workload and
      page-dirtying rate of the VM. Using <literal>virsh migrate
      --postcopy-bandwidth</literal>, you can now limit the bandwidth for the
      PostCopy operation.
     </para>
     <para>
      The following new features are also supported:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        translation lookaside buffer (TLB) urge enhancements
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        enhancements for NUMA CPUs
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        LUKS-encrypted qcow2 images
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        images are locked by default
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        more block devices disk information
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        usage of Cascade Lake and Icelake CPU models
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325201" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325201" -->
     <title>User Mode Instruction Prevention (UMIP) for KVM</title>
     <para>
      UMIP can prevent userspace applications from accessing system-wide
      settings. This includes the global or local descriptor tables, the
      segment selectors to the current task state and the local descriptor
      table. Hiding these system resources reduces the risk of privilege
      escalation attacks.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-324810" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324810" -->
     <title>Enable Persistent Multipath Links in KVM Guests</title>
     <para>
      After migration multipath links no longer work and cause disk access and
      I/O errors
     </para>
     <para>
      A udev rule has been added that ensures multipath links stay persistent
      after migration.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-324200" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:KVM">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324200" -->
     <title>QED Image Format Is No Longer Supported</title>
     <para>
      The QEMU virtual disk image format is no longer supported.
     </para>
     <para>
      Existing virtual disks using this format can still be accessed, but
      should be converted to a RAW or QCOW2 format when possible. Using the QED
      format for new disks is not supported.
     </para>
    </section>
    <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-4591">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324200" -->
     <title>qemu-guest-agent Will Be Installed Automatically</title>
     <para>
      The package <package>qemu-guest-agent</package> is now automatically
      installed if the YaST installer detects that it is running within a KVM
      or Xen virtual machine. The guest agent allows management applications
      running on the host OS to communicate with SLES running inside the
      virtual machine. For more information about using the guest agent, see
      the SLES Virtualization Guide at
      <link
       xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/html/SLES-all/cha-qemu-ga.html" />.
     </para>
    </section>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Virtualization-XEN" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
    <title>Xen</title>
    <para />
    <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327890" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327890" -->
     <title>Xen vNUMA topology</title>
     <para>
      vNUMA (virtual NUMA) is a memory optimization technology that makes
      virtual machine aware of the NUMA topology of the underlying physical
      server. Xen now supports defining a virtual NUMA topology for VMs,
      including specifying distances between NUMA cells.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327834" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327834" -->
     <title>AVX512 support</title>
     <para>
      For x86 CPUs we added support for neural network instructions
      (AVX512_4VNNIW) and multiply accumulation single precision
      (AVX512_4FMAPS) as subfamilies of the AVX512 instruction sets. With these
      instructions enabled in Xen for both HVM and PV guests, programs in guest
      OSes can take full advantage of these important instructions to speed up
      machine learning computing.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327833" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327833" -->
     <title>Branch Predictor Hardening</title>
     <para>
      For x86 CPUs, we added a new framework for Intel and AMD microcode
      related to Spectre mitigations as well as support for Retpoline. By
      default, Xen will pick the most appropriate mitigations based on the
      support compiled in, the microcode loaded, and the hardware details, and
      will virtualize appropriate mitigations for guests to use. Command line
      controls via the <literal>spec-ctrl</literal> command line option are
      available.
     </para>
     <para>
      Speculative Store Bypass (SP4) mitigations are also available. They
      enable guest software to protect against within-guest information leaks
      via <literal>spec-ctrl=ssbd</literal>. In addition, mitigation for Lazy
      FPU state restore (INTEL-SA-00145) is available via
      <literal>spec-ctrl=eager-fpu</literal>.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327832" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327832" -->
     <title>Performance Optimization for XPTI</title>
     <para>
      We implemented performance optimization for XPTI, Xen’s equivalent to
      KPTI (Kernel Page Table Isolation), a mitigation against Meltdown
      attacks. It is worth noting that only “classic PV” guests need XPTI
      because HVM and PVH guests cannot attack the hypervisor via Meltdown.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327831" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327831" -->
     <title>Credit2 Scheduler optimization</title>
     <para>
      Added soft-affinity support for the Credit 2 scheduler. It allows users
      to specify a preference for running a VM on a specific CPU. This enables
      NUMA aware scheduling for the Credit 2 scheduler. In addition, we added
      cap support, which allows users to set the maximum amount of CPU a VM
      will be able to consume, even if the host system has idle CPU cycles.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326237" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326237" -->
     <title>Memory Bandwidth Allocation</title>
     <para>
      In Xen we added support for Intel’s L2 Cache Allocation Technology ("Xen
      L2 CAT") which is available on certain models of (Micro) Server
      platforms. Xen L2 C provides a mechanism to partition or share the L2
      Cache among virtual machines, if such a technology is supported by the
      hardware Xen runs on. This allows users to make better use of the shared
      L2 cache depending on the VM characteristics (e.g. priority).
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-323901" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323901" -->
     <title>Xen Auto-Ballooning Disabled by Default</title>
     <para>
      In previous versions of SLES, the default memory allocation scheme of a
      Xen host was to allocate all host physical memory to Domain-0 and enable
      auto-ballooning. Memory was automatically ballooned from Domain-0 when
      starting additional domains. This behavior has always been error-prone
      and disabling it is encouraged in the <emphasis>Virtualization Best
      Practices Guide</emphasis>.
     </para>
     <para>
      Starting with SLES 15 SP1, Domain-0 auto-ballooning has been disabled by
      default. Domain-0 gets 10 percent of host physical memory plus 1 GB
      assigned. For example, on a host with 32 GB of physical memory, Domain-0
      gets 3.2GB + 1 GB = 4.2 GB of memory assigned. The use of the
      <literal>dom0_mem</literal> Xen command-line option is still supported
      and encouraged. The old behavior can be restored by setting
      <literal>dom0_mem</literal> to the host physical memory size and enabling
      the <literal>autoballoon</literal> setting in
      <literal>/etc/xen/xl.conf</literal>.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-323663" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:XEN">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323663" -->
     <title>Run XenStore in stubdom</title>
     <para>
      Since XEN 4.9 it is rather easy to configure XenStore to run in a stubdom
      instead of dom0. This has the advantage of a high dom0 load no longer
      affecting the XenStore performance. This is also one of the prerequisites
      for being able to restart dom0 without having to restart other guests.
     </para>
    </section>
    <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Virtualization-libvirt" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
    <title>libvirt</title>
    <para />
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="bsc-1116306">
     <title>Removal of Implicit <literal>cdrom</literal> Installation Source in <literal>virt-install</literal></title>
     <para>
      Previously, when the <literal>--disk</literal> parameter was used with
      <literal>device=cdrom</literal>, <literal>virt-install</literal> would
      use <literal>cdrom</literal> as the installation source if no other
      installation source was specified.
     </para>
     <para>
      In <literal>virt-manager</literal> version 2.0.0, you must use the
      <literal>--cdrom</literal> parameter instead of
      <literal>--disk</literal>.
     </para>
    </section>
    <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327896" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327896" -->
     <title>Support for QEMU's multiqueue Feature for virtio-blk</title>
     <para>
      For the benefit of I/O-heavy workloads QEMU allows to improve I/O
      throughput for virtio-blk devices with the <literal>num-queues</literal>
      parameter. This was not supported by libvirt.
     </para>
     <para>
      Support for the <literal>num-queues</literal> parameter for virtio-blk
      devices has been added to libvirt by adding the <literal>queues</literal>
      attribute for the disk driver:
     </para>
<screen>&lt;disk type='file' device='disk'&gt;
 &lt;driver name='qemu' type='qcow2' queues='4'/&gt;
 &lt;source file='/mnt/data/libvirt/images/sle15sp1.qcow2'/&gt;
 &lt;target dev='vda' bus='virtio'/&gt;
&lt;/disk&gt;</screen>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327895" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327895" -->
     <title>Support Migration of VMs with Shared Disks and directsync Caching</title>
     <para>
      Migration of VMs with shared disks was not possible when the disk caching
      mode <literal>directsync</literal> was used.
     </para>
     <para>
      Support for this feature has been added, so migration of VMs with disks
      that use directsync caching is no longer blocked.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327892" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327892" -->
     <title>Bash Completion Support for the virsh Command</title>
     <para>
      Bash completion support has been added for the virsh command. The
      complete set of options, subcommands and options for subcommands can now
      be expanded by pressing TAB in the bash shell.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327891" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327891" -->
     <title>New virsh Command: migrate-getmaxdowntime</title>
     <para>
      virsh supports a new subcommand <literal>migrate-getmaxdowntime</literal>
      that shows the maximum tolerable downtime of a domain which is being
      live-migrated to another host.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325848" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325848" -->
     <title>Support for the VM Generation ID Device</title>
     <para>
      Some classes of software can be negatively affected by virtual machine
      operations that have the effect of returning a virtual machine to an
      earlier point in time (like applying a virtual machine snapshot). One
      such class of software is cryptography, which requires a high level of
      entropy
     </para>
     <para>
      The VM generation ID (vmgenid) device is a device emulated in QEMU which
      exposes a 128-bit, cryptographically random, integer value identifier,
      referred to as a Globally Unique Identifier, or GUID. libvirt now
      supports this device, allowing users to notify the guest operating system
      when the virtual machine is executed with a different configuration (for
      example, snapshot execution or creation from a template). A guest
      operating system supporting vmgenid notices the change, and is then able
      to react as appropriate by marking its copies of distributed databases as
      dirty, re-initializing its random number generator, etc.
     </para>
     <para>
      Currently vmgenid is only supported in Windows guests. Windows guests use
      the data provided by the vmgenid device to ensure that applications that
      use Windows cryptography APIs always receive high entropy, even in the
      event of a virtual machine snapshot or similar operation.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-320928" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:libvirt">
     <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
     <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320928" -->
     <title>Open vSwitch Support</title>
     <para>
      Open vSwitch support has been added to libvirt. It is now possible to:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        define, add, or delete Open vSwitch based networks
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        define, add, or delete vlan and portgroup definitions for Open vSwitch
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Virtualization-Vagrant-SLES">
    <title>Vagrant Boxes for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</title>
    <para>
     Starting with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP5, we are providing
     official Vagrant Boxes for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for x86_64 and
     aarch64 using the VirtualBox and libvirt providers. These boxes come with
     the bare minimum of packages to reduce their size and are not registered,
     thus users need to register the boxes prior to further provisioning.
    </para>
    <para>
     These boxes are only available for direct download via SCC and must be
     manually registered with Vagrant as follows:
    </para>
<screen>vagrant box add --name SLES-15-SP1 \
SLES15-SP1-Vagrant.x86_64-15.1-libvirt-*.vagrant.libvirt.box</screen>
    <para>
     The box is then available under the name SLES-15-SP1 and can be used as
     all other Vagrant boxes:
    </para>
<screen>vagrant init SLES-15-SP1
vagrant up
vagrant ssh</screen>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Virtualization-Vagrant-aarch64">
    <title>aarch64 Support</title>
    <para>
     The Vagrant Box is also available for the aarch64 architecture using the
     libvirt provider. It has been pre-configured for the usage on SUSE Linux
     Enterprise Server on aarch64 and might not launch on other operating
     systems without additional settings. Running it on other architectures
     than aarch64 is not supported.
    </para>
    <para>
     In case the box fails to start with a libvirt error message, add the
     following to your Vagrantfile and adjust the variables according to the
     guest operating system:
    </para>
<screen>config.vm.provider :libvirt do |libvirt|
  libvirt.driver = "kvm"
  libvirt.host = 'localhost'
  libvirt.uri = 'qemu:///system'
  libvirt.host = "main"
  libvirt.features = ["apic"]
  # path to the UEFI loader for aarch64
  libvirt.loader = "/usr/share/qemu/aavmf-aarch64-code.bin"
  libvirt.video_type = "vga"
  libvirt.cpu_mode = "host-passthrough"
  libvirt.machine_type = "virt-3.1"
  # path to the qemu aarch64 emulator
  libvirt.emulator_path = "/usr/bin/qemu-system-aarch64"
end</screen>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Desktop">
   <title>Desktop</title>
   <para />
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3890">
    <title>Flatpak Has Been Updated to Major Stable Version</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>flatpak</literal> package has been updated to version 1.2.3.
     For an overview of the included changes, see these changelogs:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       https://github.com/flatpak/flatpak/releases/tag/1.2.0
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       https://github.com/flatpak/flatpak/releases/tag/1.1.0
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       https://github.com/flatpak/flatpak/releases/tag/1.0.0
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3067">
    <title>Removal of YaST License Files from <literal>/etc</literal></title>
    <para>
     Previously, YaST license files were located in
     <literal>/etc/YaST2/licenses</literal>. They have now been moved to
     <literal>/usr/share/licenses</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327903" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Misc">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327903" -->
    <title>Connecting to a Remote Desktop via RDP Fails</title>
    <para>
     Connecting to an xrdp server with Remmina or xfreerdp fails, because no
     connection can be established.
    </para>
    <para>
     Both tools need to have the <literal>relax-order-checks</literal> and
     <literal>glyph-cache</literal> options enabled when connecting to an xrdp
     server:
    </para>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">For Remmina</bridgehead>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click "Create a new connection profile".
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Provide the server address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In the "Advanced" tab, check "Relax Order Checks" and "Glyph Cache".
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click "Connect" or "Save and Connect".
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">For xfreerdp</emphasis> append
     <literal>/relax-order-checks +glyph-cache</literal> to the command line
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Default Settings</title>
     <para>
      The <literal>relax-order-checks</literal> and
      <literal>glyph-cache</literal> options are not enabled by default,
      because they may not work with all RDP server implementations. Especially
      <literal>glyph-cache</literal> is known to cause problems when connection
      to Windows RDP servers. It is recommended to only use these settings when
      connecting to an xrdp server.
     </para>
    </note>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326682" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Misc">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326682" -->
    <title>HiDPI support in GNOME</title>
    <para>
     Starting with SLE 15 SP1, there are several improvements to HiDPI support.
     If the DPI of your display is greater than 144, GNOME will scale the
     Session to a 2:1 ratio automatically and deliver you a crisp and sharp
     user experience. You can adjust the scaling-factor value manually under
     GNOME Control Center's display panel.
    </para>
    <para>
     However, there are limitations to this support:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Fractional scaling is still considered experimental in GNOME 3.26.2, so
       you can only set the scaling factor to a whole number.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       X11 apps may appear blurry under a HiDPI Wayland session (via XWayland),
       as per-display scaling is not supported on X11.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Using multiple monitors with different DPI is not supported,
       scale-monitor-framebuffer is still an immature feature so you cannot set
       per-monitor scales in GNOME Control Center.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326665" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Misc">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326665" -->
    <title>Input Method Engines Changes for Asian Languages</title>
    <para>
     Several input methods for Traditional and Simplified Chinese are no longer
     maintained upstream and have been replaced. A new input method for
     Japanese has been added.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Added input engines <literal>ibus-anthy</literal> for Japanese (will not
       be installed by default).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Replaced <literal>ibus-table-zhuyin</literal> with
       <literal>ibus-cangjie</literal> for Traditional Chinese (will not be
       installed by default).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Dropped <literal>ibus-sunpinyin</literal>,
       <literal>ibus-googlepinyin</literal>,
       <literal>ibus-table-zhengma</literal>, and
       <literal>ibus-table-ziranma</literal> for Simplified Chinese.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="bsc-1163166">
    <!-- originally reported for openSUSE at boo#1091021 -->
    <title>Use <command>update-alternatives</command> to Set Display Manager and Desktop Session</title>
    <para>
     In SLE 12 SP5 and earlier, you could use
     <filename>/etc/sysconfig</filename> or the YaST module
     <guimenu>/etc/sysconfig Editor</guimenu> to define the display manager
     (also called the login manager) and desktop session. Starting with SLE
     15 GA, the values are not defined using
     <filename>/etc/sysconfig</filename> anymore but with the alternatives
     system.
    </para>
    <para>
     To change the defaults, use the following alternatives:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Display manager: <literal>default-displaymanager</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Wayland session: <literal>default-waylandsession.desktop</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       X desktop session: <literal>default-xsession.desktop</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For example, to check the value of
     <literal>default-displaymanager</literal>, use:
    </para>
<screen><command>sudo update-alternatives --display default-displaymanager</command></screen>
    <para>
     To switch the <literal>default-displaymanager</literal> to
     <command>xdm</command>, use:
    </para>
<screen><command>sudo update-alternatives --set default-displaymanager \
  /usr/lib/X11/displaymanagers/xdm</command></screen>
    <para>
     To enable graphical management of alternatives, use the YaST module
     <guimenu>Alternatives</guimenu> that can be installed from the package
     <package>yast2-alternatives</package>.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-Misc">
   <title>Miscellaneous</title>
   <para />
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-PED-1805">
    <title>Podman upgrade from 3.4.x to 4.3.1</title>
    <para>
     Podman 4.x is a major release with 60 new features and more than 50 bug
     fixes compared to Podman 3. It also includes a complete rewrite of the
     network stack.
    </para>
    <para>
     Podman 4.x brings a new container network stack based on
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/containers/netavark">Netavark</link>,
     the new container network stack and
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/containers/aardvark-dns">Aardvark DNS
     server</link> in addition to the existing container network interface (CNI)
     stack used by Podman 3.x . The new stack brings 3 important improvement:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>Better support for containers in multiple networks</para>
     </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Better IPv6 support</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Better performance</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To ensure that nothing break with this major change, the old CNI stack
     will remain the default on existing installations, while new installs will use
     Netavark.</para>

    <para>New installations can opt to use CNI by explicitly specifying it via
    the <literal>containers.conf</literal> configuration file, using the
    <literal>network_backend</literal> field.</para>

    <para>
     If you have run Podman 3.x before upgrading to Podman 4, Podman will
     continue to use CNI plugins as it had before. There is a marker in Podman's
     local storage that indicates this. In order to begin using Podman 4, you
     need to destroy that marker with <literal>podman system reset</literal>.
     This will destroy the marker, all of the images, all of the networks, and
     all of the containers.
    </para>

    <warning>
    <para>
     Before testing Podman 4 and the new network stack, you will have to destroy all
     your current containers, images, and networks. You must export/save any import
     containers or images on a private registry, or make sure that your Dockerfiles
     are available for rebuilding and scripts/playbooks/states to reapply any
     settings, regenerate secrets, etc.
    </para>
    </warning>

    <para>Last but not least CNI will be deprecated from upstream at a future date:
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/containers/podman/tree/main/cni"></link></para>

    <para>For a complete overview of the changes, please check out the upstream
     <link
     xlink:href="https://github.com/containers/podman/releases/tag/v4.0.0">4.0.0</link>
     but also
     <link
     xlink:href="https://github.com/containers/podman/releases/tag/v4.1.1">4.1.1</link>,
     <link
     xlink:href="https://github.com/containers/podman/releases/tag/v4.2.0">4.2.0</link>
     and
     <link
     xlink:href="https://github.com/containers/podman/releases/tag/v4.3.0">4.3.0</link>
     to be informed about all the new features and changes.</para>

   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-24988" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Misc">
    <title>Enriched system visibility in the SUSE Customer Center (SCC)</title>
    <para>
     &suse; is committed to helping provide better insights into the consumption
     of &suse; subscriptions regardless of where they are running or how they
     are managed; physical or virtual, on-prem or in the cloud, connected to SCC
     or Repository Mirroring Tool (RMT), or managed by SUSE Manager. To help you identify or filter out
     systems in SCC that are no longer running or decommissioned, SUSEConnect
     now features a daily “ping”, which will update system information
     automatically.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more details see the documentation at <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/subscription/suseconnect/single-html/SLE-suseconnect-visibility/" />.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-13241">
    <!-- jsc#SLE-13241 -->
    <title>The ODBC driver location has changed</title>
    <para>
     Previously in SLES 12, the unixODBC driver for PostgreSQL was included in
     the <literal>postgresql10-odbc</literal>
     package and was located in
     <literal>/usr/pgsql-10/lib/psqlodbcw.so</literal>. In SLES 15, this driver
     is part of the <literal>psqlODBC-&lt;version&gt;</literal> package and it
     is located in <literal>/usr/lib64/psqlodbcw.so</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     For some more information, see
     <link xlink:href="https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1169697" />.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-x86-64">
  <title>AMD64/Intel 64 (x86_64) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to the version of SUSE Linux Enterprise
   Server 15 SP1 for the AMD64/Intel 64 architectures.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-x86-64-System" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64:System">
   <title>System and Vendor Specific Information</title>
   <para/>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3193">
    <title>32-bit Runtime Environment</title>
    <para>
     SLES 15 SP1 includes 32-bit runtime components. These are supported for
     non-productive use, that is, system setup, BIOS configuration, etc.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327794" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64:System">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327794" -->
    <title>Intel Optane DC Persistent Memory Operating Modes</title>
    <para>
     With SLE 15 SP1, Intel Optane DIMMs can be used in different modes on
     YES-certified platforms:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In App Direct Mode, the Intel Optane memory is used as fast persistent
       storage, an alternative to SSDs and NVMe devices. Data is persistent: It
       is kept when the system is powered off.
      </para>
      <para>
       App Direct Mode has been supported since SLE 12 SP4.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In Memory Mode, the Intel Optane memory serves as a cost-effective,
       high-capacity alternative to DRAM. In this mode, separate DRAM DIMMs act
       as a cache for the most frequently-accessed data while the Optane DIMMs
       memory provide large memory capacity. However, compared with DRAM-only
       systems, this mode is slower under random access workloads. If you run
       applications without Optane-specific enhancements that take advantage of
       this mode, memory performance may decrease. Data is
       <emphasis>not</emphasis> persistent: It is lost when the system is
       powered off.
      </para>
      <para>
       Memory Mode has been supported since SLE 15 SP1
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In Mixed Mode, the Intel Optane memory is partitioned, so it can serve
       in both modes simultaneously.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mixed Mode has been supported since SLE 15 SP1.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Not all certified platforms support all modes mentioned
     above.</emphasis> Direct hardware-related questions at your hardware
     partner. SUSE works with all major hardware vendors to make use of Intel
     Optane a perfect experience on the OS- and open-source infrastructure
     level.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326637" remap="InfraPackArch:x86_64:System">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326637" -->
    <title>Fake NUMA Emulation in the Linux Kernel Can Now Uniformly Split Physical Nodes</title>
    <para>
     Previously, NUMA emulation capabilities for splitting system RAM by a
     fixed size or by a set number of nodes could result in some nodes being
     larger than others. This happened because the implementation prioritized
     establishing a minimum usable memory size over satisfying the requested
     number of NUMA nodes.
    </para>
    <para>
     With SLE 15 SP1, the kernel can now evenly partition each physical NUMA
     node into N emulated nodes. For example, the boot parameter
     <literal>numa=fake=3U</literal> creates a total of 6 emulated nodes on a
     system that has 2 physical nodes. This is useful for debugging and
     evaluating platform memory-side-cache capabilities as described by the
     ACPI HMAT.
    </para>
    <para>
     To use, add the boot parameter <literal>numa=fake=&lt;N&gt;U</literal>.
     The final <literal>U</literal> means that the kernel will divide each
     physical node into N emulated nodes.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-Power" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
  <title>POWER (ppc64le) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to the version of SUSE Linux Enterprise
   Server 15 SP1 for the POWER architecture.
  </para>
  <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327775" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327775" -->
   <title>Support for DRAM-Backed Persistent Volumes</title>
   <para>
    On SLES 15 SP1 for POWER, with the Linux kernel updated to at least version
    4.12.14-197 and <literal>ndctl</literal> updated to at least version 64.1-3
    and using the IBM POWER9 firmware FW940 GA, you can now use DRAM-backed
    persistent volumes. These volumes are presented as virtual SCM volumes.
    They are persistent only across partition reboots but not across CEC
    reboots.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327173" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="RAS"; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327173" -->
   <title>Reduced Memory Usage When Booting FADump Capture Kernel</title>
   <para>
    One of the primary issues with Firmware Assisted Dump (FADump) on IBM POWER
    systems is that it needs a large amount of memory to be reserved. On large
    systems with terabytes of memory, this reservation can be quite
    significant.
   </para>
   <para>
    Normally, the preserved memory is filtered to extract only relevant areas
    using the <literal>makedumpfile</literal> tool. While the tool allows
    determining what needs to be part of the dump and what memory to filter
    out, the default is to capture only kernel data and exclude everything
    else.
   </para>
   <para>
    We take advantage of this default and the Linux kernel's Contiguous Memory
    Allocator (CMA) to fundamentally change the memory reservation model for
    FADump: Instead of setting aside a significant chunk of memory that cannot
    otherwise be used, the feature uses CMA instead. It reserves a significant
    chunk of memory that the kernel is prevented from using (due to
    <literal>MIGRATE_CMA</literal>), but applications are free to use it. With
    this, FADump will still be able to accurately capture all of the kernel
    memory and most of the user-space memory except for the user pages that are
    part of the CMA region reserved for FADump.
   </para>
   <para>
    To disable this feature, pass the kernel parameter
    <literal>fadump=nocma</literal> instead of <literal>fadump=on</literal>.
    This ensures that the memory reserved for FADump is not used by
    applications. This option may be useful in scenarios where you prefer to
    also capture application data in the dump file.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326864" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326864" -->
   <title>Performance Co-pilot (PCP) Updated, Perfevent Performance Metrics Domain Agent (PMDA) Support Libraries Added</title>
   <para>
    PCP has been updated to v4.3.1 and brings many improvements in its ability
    to collect performance metrics from various sources. In addition, the
    Perfevent PMDA is now available and provides access to platform performance
    counter (PMU) data through the Linux perf_event subsystem.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326782" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326782" -->
   <title>Uprobes: Support for SDT events with reference counter (perf)</title>
   <para>
    Userspace Statically Defined Tracepoints (USDT) are dtrace-style markers
    inside userspace applications. With SLES 15 SP1, Uprobe is enhanced to
    support SDT events having reference counter (semaphore).
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326712" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326712" -->
   <title>PAPI Package Update</title>
   <para>
    Update to newer version of PAPI to pick up fixes for POWER8 events, POWER9
    events, corrections and clean up for some duplicate event names.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326521" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326521" -->
   <title>ibmvnic Device Driver</title>
   <para>
    The kernel device driver ibmvnic provides support for vNIC (virtual Network
    Interface Controller) which is a PowerVM virtual networking technology that
    delivers enterprise capabilities and simplifies network management on IBM
    POWER systems. It is an efficient high-performance technology.
   </para>
   <para>
    When combined with SR-IOV NIC, it provides bandwidth control Quality of
    Service (QoS) capabilities at the virtual NIC level. vNIC significantly
    reduces virtualization overhead resulting in lower latencies and fewer
    server resources (CPU, memory) required for network virtualization.
   </para>
   <para>
    For a detailed support statement of ibmvnic in SLES, see
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/kb/doc/?id=7023703"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326393" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326393" -->
   <title>SDT Markers added to libglib</title>
   <para>
    SDT markers for debugging and performance monitoring with tools such as
    perf and systemtap have been added to libglib.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326120" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326120" -->
   <title>Access to Additional POWER Registers in GDB</title>
   <para>
    GDB can now access more POWER architecture registers, including PPR, DSCR,
    TAR, and Hardware Transactional Memory registers.
   </para>
  </section>
  <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-SystemZ">
  <title>IBM Z (s390x) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to the version of SUSE Linux Enterprise
   Server 15 SP1 for the IBM Z architecture. For more information, see
   <link xlink:href="https://www.ibm.com/docs/en/linux-on-systems?topic=distributions-suse-linux-enterprise-server"/>
  </para>
  <para>
   IBM zEnterprise 196 (z196) and IBM zEnterprise 114 (z114), subsequently
   called z196 and z114.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-SystemZ-Virtualization" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
   <title>Virtualization</title>
   <para/>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326829" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326829" -->
    <title>Huge Pages</title>
    <para>
     Allow KVM guests to use huge page memory backing for improved memory
     performance for workloads running with large memory footprints.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326382" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326382" -->
    <title>zPCI Passthrough Support for KVM</title>
    <para>
     Allow KVM to pass control over any kind of PCI host device (a virtual
     function) to a KVM guest enabling workloads that require direct access to
     PCI functions.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326378" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326378" -->
    <title>Interactive Bootloader</title>
    <para>
     Enable to interactively select boot entries to recover misconfigured KVM
     guests.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326370" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326370" -->
    <title>Guest-Dedicated Crypto Adapters</title>
    <para>
     Allow KVM to dedicate crypto adapters (and domains) as passthrough devices
     to a KVM guest such that the hypervisor cannot observe the communication
     of the guest with the device.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326368" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326368" -->
    <title>Expose Detailed Guest Crash Information to the Hypervisor</title>
    <para>
     Provides additional debug data for operating system failures that occur
     within a KVM guest.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326355" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326355" -->
    <title>Development-Tools Module: Valgrind IBM z13 Support</title>
    <para>
     Valgrind now include instruction support for IBM z13 instructions. This
     enables debugging and validation of binaries built and optimized for IBM
     z13. In particular this covers the vector instruction set extensions
     introduced with IBM z13.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325693" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Virtualization">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325693" -->
    <title>kvm_stat Package from kernel Tree</title>
    <para>
     kvm_stat allows to display KVM trace events, which can be useful for
     trouble shooting.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-SystemZ-Network" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
   <title>Network</title>
   <para/>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326806" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326806" -->
    <title>OSA-Express7S Adapters Are Now Supported</title>
    <para>
     With the OSA 7 network cards a link speed of 25Gb/s is supported.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326383" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326383" -->
    <title>OSA IPv6 Checksum Offload</title>
    <para>
     Checksum offload now supports IPv6 Configuring checksum offload
     operations.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326377" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326377" -->
    <title>Full-blown TCP Segmentation Offload</title>
    <para>
     TCP segmentation offload is now supported on both layer 2 and layer 3 and
     is extended to IPv6.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325698" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Network">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325698" -->
    <title>Shared Memory Communications - Direct (SMC-Direct)</title>
    <para>
     Internal shared memory devices for fast communication between LPARs can be
     used via a new socket family and the existing tooling via TCP handshake. A
     preload library can be used to enable applications to use the new socket
     family transparently.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="bsc-1136157">
    <title>Speed of <literal>ibmveth</literal> Interface Not Reported Accurately</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>ibmveth</literal> interface is a paravirtualized interface.
     When communicating between LPARs within the same system, the interface's
     speed is limited only by the system's CPU and memory bandwidth. When the
     virtual Ethernet is bridged to a physical network, the interface's speed
     is limited by the speed of that physical network.
    </para>
    <para>
     Unfortunately, the <literal>ibmveth</literal> driver has no way of
     determining automatically whether it is bridged to a physical network and
     what the speed of that link is. <literal>ibmveth</literal> therefore
     reports its speed as a fixed value of 1 Gb/s which in many cases will be
     inaccurate. To determine the actual speed of the interface, use a
     benchmark. Using <command>ethtool</command>, you can then set a more
     accurate displayed speed.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="bsc-1153309">
    <title>Degraded Performance on RoCE ConnectX-4 Hardware</title>
    <para>
     Using default settings of SLES 15 SP1, 15 SP2, and 15 SP3, the performance
     of RoCE ConnectX-4 hardware on IBM z14 and IBM z15 systems is degraded
     compared to when used under SLES 15 GA.
    </para>
    <para>
     To improve performance to the same level as with SLES 15 GA, set the
     following flag for all RoCE Ethernet interfaces: <command>ethtool
     --set-priv-flags</command> <replaceable>DEVNAME</replaceable>
     rx_striding_rq. This needs to be done for each RoCE interface and at each
     boot.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-SystemZ-Security" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
   <title>Security</title>
   <para/>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326824" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326824" -->
    <title>Cryptsetup 2.0.5 for LUKS2 Support</title>
    <para>
     It is possible to use cryptsetup to handle protected keys for dm-crypt
     disks in plain format and cryptsetup provides LUKS 2 support.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326807" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326807" -->
    <title>Support Multiple zcrypt Device Nodes</title>
    <para>
     The cryptographic device driver can now provide and maintain multiple
     zcrypt device nodes. These nodes can be restricted in terms of
     cryptographic adapters, domains, and available IOCTLs.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326561" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326561" -->
    <title>SIMD Implementation of Chacha20 in OpenSSL</title>
    <para>
     This enables support for TLS 1.3 via the Chacha20 cipher suite providing
     good performance using SIMD instructions
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326390" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326390" -->
    <title>dm-crypt with Protected Keys - Change Encryption Key Tool</title>
    <para>
     Manage LUKS2 encryption keys for protected key crypto if the encryption
     key of the associated Crypto Express adapter is changed.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326389" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326389" -->
    <title>libica: Use TRNG to Seed DRBG (crypto)</title>
    <para>
     Improved generation of high (pseudo) quality random numbers via libica
     DRBG especially to generate safe random keys by use of the PRNO-TRNG
     instruction.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326375" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326375" -->
    <title>Support of CPACF Hashes in ep11 Token in openCryptoki and libica</title>
    <para>
     Provides improved performance for applications computing many digital
     signatures using EP11 like Blockchain.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326366" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326366" -->
    <title>In-kernel Crypto: Support for Protected Keys Generated by random in the paes Module</title>
    <para>
     This feature can generate volatile protected keys. This allows, for
     example, the secure encryption of swap volumes without the need for a
     CryptoExpress adapter.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326356" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326356" -->
    <title>Partial RELRO Support in binutils</title>
    <para>
     With this feature the global offset table content is rearranged to enable
     the dynamic linker write-protecting parts of the global offset table after
     initial program load. That way potential attacks requiring to rewrite such
     entries are prevented.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326354" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326354" -->
    <title>OpenSSL: Crucial Enhancements</title>
    <para>
     Improved performance of OpenSSL via extended CPACF for additional ciphers
     like AES CTR, OFB, CFB, CCM.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326351" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326351" -->
    <title>SIMD Implementation of Poly1305 in OpenSSL</title>
    <para>
     This enables support for TLS 1.3 via the Poly1305 cipher suite providing
     good performance using SIMD instructions.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325701" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325701" -->
    <title>Elliptic Curve Support for Crypto</title>
    <para>
     The strategic elliptic curve asymmetric cryptography that provides strong
     security with shorter keys is now supported by Crypto Express function
     offloads with <literal>opencryptoki</literal>, <literal> libica
     </literal>, <literal> icatoken </literal>, and
     <literal>openssl-ibmca</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325700" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325700" -->
    <title>Support 4K Sectors for Fast Clear Key dm-crypt</title>
    <para>
     Encryption is supported with 4K sectors. Using 4K sector leads to
     significant performance improvements on IBM Z using CPACF crypto hardware.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325699" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325699" -->
    <title>Enhanced SIMD Instructions in libica</title>
    <para>
     Faster execution of asymmetric cryptographic algorithms via support of new
     SIMD instructions available with IBM z13 and later hardware.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325695" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325695" -->
    <title>Support for the CEX6S Crypto Card</title>
    <para>
     The CEX6S crypto card is fully supported.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325692" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325692" -->
    <title>Support Architectural Limit of Crypto Adapters in zcrypt Device Driver</title>
    <para>
     The crypto device driver now support the theoretical maximum of 255
     adapters.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325689" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325689" -->
    <title>zcrypt DD: APQN Tags Allow Deterministic Driver Binding</title>
    <para>
     Provides deterministic hot-plugging semantics to enable the virtualization
     and unique determination of crypto adapters in KVM environments even if
     the associated hardware gets intermittently lost and reconnected.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325686" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325686" -->
    <title>In-kernel Crypto: GCM Enhancements</title>
    <para>
     Kernel services like IPSec now exploit IBM z14 crypto hardware for the
     AES-GCM cipher.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325684" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Security">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325684" -->
    <title>Protected Key dm-crypt Key Management Tool</title>
    <para>
     Protected key crypto for dm-crypt disks in plain format can be used
     without a dependency on cryptsetup support for LUKS(2) with protected
     keys. A key management tool as part of the s390-tools enables to manage a
     key repository allowing to associate secure keys with disk partitions or
     logical volumes.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-SystemZ-RAS" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
   <title>Reliability, Availability, Serviceability (RAS)</title>
   <para/>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326826" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326826" -->
    <title>PCI Error Reporting Tool</title>
    <para>
     Defective PCIe devices are now reported via error notification events that
     include health information of the adapters.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326374" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326374" -->
    <title>scsi: zfcp: Add Port Speed Capabilities</title>
    <para>
     Provides the possibility to display port speed capabilities for SCSI
     devices.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326373" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326373" -->
    <title>Handle Provisioned MAC Addresses</title>
    <para>
     You can now use provisioned MAC addresses for devices supported with IBM
     z14 and later hardware.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326362" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326362" -->
    <title>Configurable IFCC Handling</title>
    <para>
     Enables to switch off the actual handling of repeated IFCCs (Interface
     Control Check), for example, by removing paths, so that only IFCC messages
     are written to the log when thresholds are exceeded.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326361" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326361" -->
    <title>Collecting NVMe-related Debug Data</title>
    <para>
     To debug NVMe devices, the debug data gets collected and added to the
     <literal>dbginfo.sh</literal> script.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326358" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326358" -->
    <title>Raw Track Access without Prefix CCW</title>
    <para>
     This feature enables seamlessly moving Linux system volumes between zPDT
     and LPAR, allowing for greater flexibility during deployment of new
     setups.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326357" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:RAS">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326357" -->
    <title>I/O Device Pre-Configuration</title>
    <para>
     Linux in LPAR mode can now process device configuration data that is
     user-defined and obtained during boot.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-SystemZ-Performance" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
   <title>Performance</title>
   <para/>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326391" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326391" -->
    <title>Performance Counters for IBM z14 (CPU-MF)</title>
    <para>
     For optimized performance tuning the CPU-measurement counter facility now
     supports counters, including the MT-diagnostic counter set, that were
     introduced with IBM z14.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326350" remap="InfraPackArch:SystemZ:Performance">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326350" -->
    <title>Network Performance Improvements</title>
    <para>
     Enhanced performance for OSA and Hipersockets via code improvements and
     exploitation of further kernel infrastructure.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="InfraPackArch-AArch64" remap="InfraPackArch:AArch64">
  <title>ARM 64-Bit (AArch64) Specific Information</title>
  <para>
   Information in this section pertains to the version of SUSE Linux Enterprise
   Server 15 SP1 for the AArch64 architecture.
  </para>
  <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327734" remap="InfraPackArch:AArch64">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327734" -->
   <title>System-on-Chip Driver Enablement</title>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for Arm 15 SP1 includes driver enablement for
    the following System-on-Chip chipsets:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      AMD Opteron A1100
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Ampere Computing X-Gene, eMAG
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Broadcom BCM2837
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Huawei Kunpeng 916, Kunpeng 920
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Marvell ThunderX1, ThunderX2, Octeon TX, Armada 7040, Armada 8040
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Mellanox BlueField
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      NXP QorIQ LS1043A, LS1046A, LS1088A, LS2088A, LX2160A; i.MX 8M
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Qualcomm Centriq 2400
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Rockchip RK3399
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Socionext SynQuacer SC2A11
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Xilinx Zynq UltraScale+ MPSoC
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326668" remap="InfraPackArch:AArch64">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326668" -->
   <title>Driver Enablement for NXP SC16IS7xx UARTs</title>
   <para>
    The Raspberry Pi 3 Model B/B+ has only one serial port available on its
    40-pin GPIO connector.
   </para>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server now includes a device driver for NXP SC16IS7xx
    series of I²C or SPI bus connected serial ports. These chipsets are found
    on multiple third-party expansion boards for the Raspberry Pi. For
    instructions how to describe such boards in the Device Tree for use with
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for Arm, please refer to the respective
    vendor's documentation and compare the SUSE Release Notes for the Raspberry
    Pi (in particular, recommended use of <literal>extraconfig.txt</literal>
    instead of <literal>config.txt</literal>).
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325731" remap="InfraPackArch:AArch64">
   <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
   <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325731" -->
   <title>Boot and Driver Enablement for Raspberry Pi</title>
   <para>
    Bootloaders and a supported microSD card image of SUSE Linux Enterprise
    Server for Arm 15 SP1 for the Raspberry Pi are available. The selection of
    preinstalled packages and first-boot assistant in the SUSE image are now
    aligned with the JeOS images, reducing image size. To aid with installing a
    minimal graphical desktop as found in previous image versions, a new
    pattern <literal>x11_raspberrypi</literal> is provided for package
    installation (<literal>zypper in -t pattern x11_raspberrypi</literal>). The
    template of the SUSE Linux image is available as profile "RaspberryPi" in
    the package <literal>kiwi-templates-SLES15-JeOS</literal> to derive custom
    appliances, including appliances with X11 graphical environment
    preinstalled.
   </para>
   <bridgehead renderas="sect5">New Features</bridgehead>
   <para>
    The Raspberry Pi 7" Touch Display connected via the MIPI DSI flat ribbon
    cable is now supported in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for Arm 15 SP1.
   </para>
   <para>
    Audio via the HDMI connector on Raspberry Pi 3 Model B/B+ is now supported.
    It may require PulseAudio to be installed and started.
   </para>
   <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Expansion Boards</bridgehead>
   <para>
    The Raspberry Pi 3 Model B/B+ offers a 40-pin General Purpose I/O
    connector, with multiple software-configurable functions such as UART, I²C
    and SPI. This pin mux configuration along with any external devices
    attached to the pins is defined in the Device Tree which is passed by the
    bootloader to the kernel.
   </para>
   <para>
    SUSE does not currently provide support for any particular HATs or other
    expansion boards attached to the 40-pin GPIO connector. However, insofar as
    drivers for pin functions and for attached chipsets are included in SUSE
    Linux Enterprise, they can be used. SUSE does not provide support for
    making changes to the Device Tree, but successful changes will not affect
    the support status of the operating system itself. Be aware that errors in
    the Device Tree can stop the system from booting successfully or can even
    damage the hardware.
   </para>
   <para>
    The bootloader and firmware in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1 support
    Device Tree Overlays. The recommended way of configuring GPIO pins is to
    create a file <literal>extraconfig.txt</literal> on the FAT volume
    (<literal>/boot/efi/extraconfig.txt</literal> in the SUSE image) with a
    line <literal>dtoverlay=filename-without-.dtbo</literal> per Overlay. For
    more information about the syntax, see the documentation by the Raspberry
    Pi Foundation.
   </para>
   <para>
    If not already shipped in the <literal>/boot/efi/overlays/</literal>
    directory (<literal>raspberrypi-firmware-dt</literal> package),
    <literal>.dtbo</literal> files can be obtained from the manufacturer of the
    HAT or compiled from self-authored sources.
   </para>
   <bridgehead renderas="sect5">For More Information</bridgehead>
   <para>
    For more information, see the SUSE Best Practices documentation for the
    Raspberry Pi at
    <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sbp/all/"/>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section xml:id="Packages">
  <title>Packages and Functionality Changes</title>
  <para>
   This section comprises changes to packages, such as additions, updates,
   removals and changes to the package layout of software. It also contains
   information about modules available for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. For
   information about changes to package management tools, such as Zypper or
   RPM, see <xref linkend="InfraPackArch-ArchIndependent-SystemsManagement"/>.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="Packages-New" remap="Packages:New">
   <title>New Packages</title>
   <remark> *** Description of the new package with direct link to the official website (need the
    URL tag) *** Version and release of the package *** Why this new package: enhancements request
    *** link to the official documentation *** link to the SUSE's documentation *** Dependencies and
    Build requires </remark>
   <para/>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-12120">
    <title>Go Has Been Added As a Fully-supported Language</title>
    <para>
     The Go language has been added as a fully-supported language. The package
     versions are aligned with the versions supported by the upstream.
     Currently, these are:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       go1.15
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       go1.15-doc
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       go1.16
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       go1.16-doc
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-12481">
    <title><literal>sssd-winbind-idmap</literal> Has Been Added</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>sssd-winbind-idmap</literal> package has been added.
    </para>
    <para>
     In large Active Directory environments, Linux clients often use
     <literal>samba-winbind</literal> and <literal>sssd</literal> together. The
     two packages hower use different algorithms to create UID/GUID. This
     package provides a way for <literal>samba-winbind</literal> to call
     <literal>sssd</literal> to map UIDs/GIDs and SIDs, effectively unifying
     them.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="jsc-SLE-12396">
    <title>Git Has Been Updated to Version 2.26.2</title>
    <para>
     SLES 12 SP4 now includes version 2.26.2 of the version control Git. This
     version of Git supports the SHA-256 cipher.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information, see the
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/git/git/blob/main/Documentation/RelNotes/2.26.0.txt">Git
     Release Notes</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
     This update fixes the following security vulnerabilities:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2017-15298"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2018-11233"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2018-11235"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2018-17456"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1348"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1349"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1350"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1351"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1352"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1353"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1354"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-1387"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2019-19604"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2020-11008"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/CVE-2020-5260"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326395" remap="Packages:New">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326395" -->
    <title>NumaTOP Has Been Added</title>
    <para>
     The NumaTOP tool version 2.1 now ships with SLE 15 SP1 for the
     architectures x86-64 and ppc64le. NumaTOP is a tool to observe the NUMA
     locality of processes and threads running on a system. It relies on
     hardware performance monitoring counters present in a subset of Intel Xeon
     and IBM POWER 8/POWER 9 processors.
    </para>
    <para>
     NumaTOP can be used to:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Characterize the locality of all running processes and threads to
       identify those with the poorest locality in the system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Identify “hot” memory areas, report average memory access latency, and
       provide the location where accessed memory is allocated.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Provide the call-chain(s) in the process/thread code that accesses a
       given hot memory area.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Provide the call-chain(s) when the process/thread generates certain
       counter events. The call-chain(s) help(s) to locate the source code that
       generates the events.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Provide per-node statistics for memory and CPU utilization.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Show the list of processes/threads sorted by metrics (by default, by CPU
       utilization). You can also resort the output by the following metrics:
       Remote Memory Accesses (RMA), Local Memory Accesses (LMA), RMA/LMA
       ratio, Cycles Per Instruction (CPI), and CPU utilization.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325727" remap="Packages:New">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325727" -->
    <title>Package insserv-compat Has Been Added to SAP Application Server Base Pattern</title>
    <para>
     SAP applications depend on the <literal>sapinit</literal> System V script.
     Other third-party software not yet updated to include systemd unit scripts
     may also depend on System V init scripts. On its own, systemd does not
     support System V init scripts anymore.
    </para>
    <para>
     The package <literal>insserv-compat</literal> adds compatibility with
     System V init scripts to systemd and can be used both SAP and non-SAP
     applications. This package is now also included in the <emphasis>SAP
     Applications Server Base</emphasis> pattern.
    </para>
    <para>
     That way, <literal>insserv-compat</literal> will provide System V
     compatibility until SAP and other third parties fully adopt systemd unit
     scripts.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Packages-Update" remap="Packages:Update">
   <title>Updated Packages</title>
   <remark> *** Description of the new package with direct link to the official website *** version
    comparison table from previous SP/product *** Bugs fixed since previous SP/Product (link to
    Bugzilla) *** Enhancements request (link to Fate number) *** link to the official documentation
    *** link to the SUSE's documentation *** Security fixes (link to CVE or SUSE's security web
    site), link to PIF *** Changelog diff (all other information non relative to security/fate/bugs) </remark>
   <para/>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-17936">
    <title><literal>dnsmasq</literal> has been updated</title>
    <para>The <literal>dnsmasq</literal> package has been updated to version 2.86.</para>
    <para>If you have DNSSEC enabled and are encountering issues with DNS resolution, see <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/kb/doc/?id=000020508" /> for more information.</para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327114">
    <title>GnuTLS Has Been Updated To Version 3.6.6</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>gnutls</literal> package has been updated to version 3.6.6.
     The support for the recently-standardized TLSv1.3 protocol has been added
     and enabled by default in GnuTLS version 3.6.4. GnuTLS version 3.6.6 is
     binary-compatible with version 3.6.2.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-10669">
    <title><literal>python-apache-libcloud</literal> Has Been Updated To Version 2.8.0</title>
    <para>
     The package <literal>python-apache-libcloud</literal> has been updated to
     version 2.8.0. This release contains important fixes and enhancements over
     2.0.0, especially for new APIs related to Microsoft Azure, and Amazon EC2
     zones. For more information about the changes in this release, see
     <link xlink:href="http://libcloud.apache.org/blog/2020/01/02/libcloud-2-8-0-released.html"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-ECO-1179">
    <title>Strongswan Has Been Updated</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>Strongswan</literal> package has been updated to version
     5.8.2. For the full changelog, see
     <link xlink:href="https://wiki.strongswan.org/versions/75"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3103">
    <title><literal>libtss2</literal> Has Been Updated</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>libtss2-*</literal> packages have been updated to version
     2.0. This package is an implementation of the TCG TPM2 Software Stack
     (TSS2).
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information, see
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/tpm2-software/tpm2-tss/releases/tag/2.0.0"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-12800">
    <title>Salt Has Been Updated to Version 3002</title>
    <para>
     The <literal>salt</literal> package has been updated to version 3002. This
     update also includes patches, backports, and enhancements by SUSE for the
     SUSE Manager Server, Proxy and Client Tools. This applies to client
     operating systems with Python 3.5+. Otherwise Salt 3000 or 2016.11 is
     used.
    </para>
    <para>
     We intend to regularly upgrade Salt to more recent versions.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more details about changes in your manually-created Salt states, see
     <link xlink:href="https://docs.saltproject.io/en/latest/topics/releases/3002.html"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-11590" remap="Packages:Update">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327121" -->
    <title>LibreOffice Has Been Updated to Version 6.4</title>
    <para>
     LibreOffice has been updated to the new major version 6.4. For information
     about major changes, see the LibreOffice 6.4 release notes at
     <link xlink:href="https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/ReleaseNotes/6.4"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326347" remap="Packages:Update">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326347" -->
    <title>OpenJDK 11 Has Replaced OpenJDK 10</title>
    <para>
     OpenJDK 10 which was shipped with SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 was not a
     long-term supported version. OpenJDK 11 which is a long-term supported
     version has meanwhile been released by upstream, and is also part of SUSE
     Linux Enterprise 15 SP1.
    </para>
    <para>
     In SUSE Linux Enterprise 15, OpenJDK 10 has been replaced with OpenJDK 11
     through a package update. OpenJDK 10 will not receive further updates.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325659" remap="Packages:Update">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325659" -->
    <title>PostgreSQL Has Been Upgraded to Version 10</title>
    <tip role="compact">
     <para>
      This entry has appeared in a previous release notes document.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
     SLES 12 SP4 and SLES 15 ship with PostgreSQL 10 by default. To enable an
     upgrade path for customers, SLE 12 SP3 now includes PostgreSQL 10 in
     addition to PostgreSQL 9.6 (the version that was originally shipped).
    </para>
    <para>
     To upgrade a PostgreSQL server installation from an older version, the
     database files need to be converted to the new version.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>PostgreSQL Upgrade Needs to Be Performed Before Upgrade to New SLES Version</title>
     <para>
      Neither SLES 12 SP4 nor SLES 15 include PostgreSQL 9.6. However,
      availability of PostgreSQL 9.6 is a requirement for performing the
      database upgrade to the PostgreSQL 10 format. Therefore, you must upgrade
      the database to the PostgreSQL 10 format before upgrading to the desired
      new SLES version.
     </para>
    </important>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Major New Features</bridgehead>
    <para>
     The following major new features are included in PostgreSQL 10:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Logical replication: a publish/subscribe framework for distributing data
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Declarative table partitioning: convenience in dividing your data
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Improved query parallelism: speed up analyses
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Quorum commit for synchronous replication: distribute data with
       confidence
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SCRAM-SHA-256 authentication: more secure data access
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     PostgreSQL 10 also brings an important change to the versioning scheme
     that is used for PostgreSQL: It now follows the format
     <emphasis>major.minor</emphasis>. This means that minor releases of
     PostgreSQL 10 are for example 10.1, 10.2, ... and the next major release
     will be 11. Previously, both the parts of the version number were
     significant for the major version. For example, PostgreSQL 9.3 and
     PostgreSQL 9.4 were different major versions.
    </para>
    <para>
     For the full PostgreSQL 10 release notes, see
     <link xlink:href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/10/release-10.html"/>.
    </para>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Upgrading</bridgehead>
    <para>
     Before starting the migration, make sure the following preconditions are
     fulfilled:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The packages of your current PostgreSQL version must have been upgraded
       to their latest maintenance update.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The packages of the new PostgreSQL major version need to be installed.
       For SLE 12, this means installing <literal>postgresql10-server</literal>
       and all the packages it depends on. Because
       <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> is contained in the package
       <literal>postgresql10-contrib</literal>, this package must be installed
       as well, at least until the migration is done.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Unless <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> is used in link mode, the server
       must have enough free disk space to temporarily hold a copy of the
       database files. If the database instance was installed in the default
       location, the needed space in megabytes can be determined by running the
       following command as <literal>root</literal>: <literal>du -hs
       /var/lib/pgsql/data</literal>. If there is little disk space available,
       run the command <literal>VACUUM FULL</literal> SQL command on each
       database in the PostgreSQL instance that you want to migrate. This
       command can take very long.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     Upstream documentation about <literal>pg_upgrade</literal> including
     step-by-step instructions for performing a database migration can be found
     locally at
     <literal>file:///usr/share/doc/packages/postgresql10/html/pgupgrade.html</literal>
     (if the <literal>postgresql10-docs</literal> package is installed), or
     online at
     <link xlink:href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/10/pgupgrade.html"/>.
     The online documentation explains how you can install PostgreSQL from the
     upstream sources (which is not necessary on SLE) and also uses other
     directory names (<literal>/usr/local</literal> instead of the
     <literal>update-alternatives</literal> based path as described above).
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section xml:id="jsc-SLE-12188">
    <title><command>jq</command> Has Been Updated to Version 1.6</title>
    <para>
     Through a maintenance update, SLES 15 SP1 now includes the JSON query tool
     <command>jq</command> in version 1.6. For more information about this
     release, see
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/stedolan/jq/releases/tag/jq-1.6">the
     upstream release notes</link>.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Packages-Removed">
   <title>Removed Packages and Features</title>
   <para>
    The following packages have been removed from this version of SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server.
   </para>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326853">
    <title>Rados Block Device (RBD) Support Has Been Removed From <literal>multipath-tools</literal></title>
    <para>
     Multi-pathed RBD has been deprecated and consequently removed by the
     upstream Ceph community due to data corruption issues. There was never an
     upstream Ceph release based on it, and because of the corruption, there
     should be no users of this code.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="bsc-1150224">
    <title>libjpeg-turbo and libjpeg62-turbo Have Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     The packages <package>libjpeg-turbo</package> and
     <package>libjpeg62-turbo</package> are not available in SLE 15 anymore.
     Use <package>libjpeg</package> instead.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Packages-Deprecated-Future" remap="Packages:Deprecated:Future">
   <title>Deprecated Packages and Features</title>
   <para>
    The following packages are deprecated and will be removed with a future
    service pack of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server.
   </para>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-3034">
    <title>Reduced Usage of <literal>cron</literal></title>
    <para>
     With the upstream development of the <literal>cronie</literal> package
     slowing down due to the preference of the <literal>systemd-timer</literal>
     functionality by its developer Red Hat, packages in SLE 15 SP1 have been
     converted to using <literal>systemd-timer</literal> as well. This decision
     was taken in order to lessen the maintenance burden and to avoid diverging
     from upstream.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="jsc-SLE-16552-1">
    <title>OpenLDAP Is Considered Deprecated</title>
    <para>
     For more information about the deprecation of OpenLDAP, see
     <xref linkend="jsc-SLE-16552"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327901" remap="Packages:Deprecated:Future">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327901" -->
    <title>klogconsole and setctsid Are Considered Deprecated</title>
    <para>
     Support for the commands <literal>klogconsole</literal> and
     <literal>setctsid</literal> will be dropped in SLE 15 SP2.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">klogconsole</emphasis>: Migrate your tools to a
     combination of the commands <literal>setlogcons</literal> and
     <literal>dmesg --console-level</literal>. The
     <literal>/etc/sysconfig/boot</literal> variable
     <literal>KLOGCONSOLE_PARAMS</literal> will be migrated automatically and
     no longer be available in SLE 15 SP2. SLE 15 SP2 will introduce
     <literal>KLOG_CONSOLE</literal> and <literal>CONSOLE_LOGLEVEL</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">setctsid</emphasis>: Migrate your tools to
     <literal>setsid --ctty/tt&gt;.</literal>
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-325947" remap="Packages:Deprecated:Future">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325947" -->
    <title>Chelsio T3 Driver (cxgbe3) Is Deprecated</title>
    <para>
     The driver for Chelsio T3 networking equipment (<literal>cxgbe3</literal>)
     is now deprecated and may become unsupported in a future Service Pack of
     SLE 15.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <!-- Originally via FATE and a bit too harsh, updates to soften wording after
    email from meissner -->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-323868">
    <title>TLS 1.0 and 1.1 Are Considered Deprecated</title>
    <para>
     The TLS 1.0 and 1.1 standards are superseded by TLS 1.2 and TLS 1.3. SUSE
     Linux Enterprise will keep backward compatibility with TLS 1.0 and 1.1
     until at least 2020. However, starting with SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 SP2,
     these old standards will be considered deprecated.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Packages-Modules" remap="Packages:Modules">
   <title>Modules</title>
   <para>
    This section contains information about important changes to modules. For
    more information about available modules, see
    <xref linkend="Intro-Module"/>.
   </para>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326919" remap="Packages:Modules">
    <!-- sort_key="100"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326919" -->
    <title>Web and Scripting Module: Support for NodeJS 10.x</title>
    <para>
     Older version of NodeJS are approaching their end of life, NodeJS 8.x
     which is currently shipped is already considered deprecated.
    </para>
    <para>
     NodeJS 10.x, the current LTS version of NodeJS is now available in the
     <emphasis>Web and Scripting</emphasis> module of SLE.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-327577" remap="Packages:Modules">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/327577" -->
    <title>Python 2 Module: python Executable Is Not Available in Standard Distribution</title>
    <para>
     With SLE 15 SP1, SUSE has started to phase out the support for Python 2 in
     its enterprise distribution. Within the standard distribution, only Python
     3 (executable name <literal>python3</literal>) is available. Python 2
     (executable names <literal>python2</literal> and
     <literal>python</literal>) is now only provided via the <emphasis>Python
     2</emphasis> module which is disabled by default.
    </para>
    <para>
     Python scripts usually expect the <literal>python</literal> executable
     (note the lack of a version number) to refer to the Python 2.x interpreter
     of the system. If instead the Python 3 interpreter were started, that
     would likely lead to misbehaving applications. For this reason, SUSE has
     decided not ship a symbolic link for <literal>/usr/bin/python</literal> to
     the Python 3 executable by default.
    </para>
    <para>
     To run Python 2 scripts, make sure to enable the SLE module
     <emphasis>Python 2</emphasis> and install the package
     <literal>python</literal> from it.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-326488" remap="Packages:Modules">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326488" -->
    <title>Package supportutils-plugin-salt Has Been Moved to the Base System Module</title>
    <para>
     In SLE 15 GA, the package <literal>supportutils-plugin-salt</literal> was
     only available from the SUSE Manager module, whereas Salt itself was
     available from the SLE Base System module.
    </para>
    <para>
     With SLE 15 SP1, this situation has been corrected: both the packages
     <literal>salt</literal> and <literal>supportutils-plugin-salt</literal>
     are now available from the SLE Base System module.
    </para>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="TechInfo">
  <title>Technical Information</title>
  <para>
   This section contains information about system limits, technical changes and
   enhancements for experienced users.
  </para>
  <!-- bnc#483250 -->
  <para>
   When talking about CPUs, we use the following terminology:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>CPU Socket</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The visible physical entity, as it is typically mounted to a mainboard or
      an equivalent.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>CPU Core</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The (usually not visible) physical entity as reported by the CPU vendor.
     </para>
     <para>
      On IBM Z, this is equivalent to an IFL.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Logical CPU</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is what the Linux Kernel recognizes as a <quote>CPU</quote>.
     </para>
     <para>
      We avoid the word <quote>thread</quote> (which is sometimes used), as the
      word <quote>thread</quote> would also become ambiguous subsequently.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Virtual CPU</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A logical CPU as seen from within a virtual machine.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <section xml:id="TechInfo-Kernel">
   <title>Kernel Limits</title>
   <!-- FIXME for 12 SP2? aginies says values should still be fine but might still
    be updated before release. - sknorr, 2016-06-13 -->
   <para>
    This table summarizes the various limits which exist in our recent kernels
    and utilities (if related) for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1.
   </para>
   <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="5">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="feature"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="x86-64"/>
     <colspec colnum="3" colname="z"/>
     <colspec colnum="4" colname="power"/>
     <colspec colnum="5" colname="aarch64"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry><emphasis>SLES 15 SP1 (Linux 4.12)</emphasis>
       </entry>
       <entry>AMD64/Intel 64 (x86_64)</entry>
       <entry>IBM Z (s390x)</entry>
       <entry>POWER (ppc64le)</entry>
       <!-- AArch64 for SLES 12 SP2 values per bsc#988955. -->
       <entry>AArch64 (ARMv8)</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         CPU bits
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         64
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of logical CPUs
        </para>
       </entry>
       <!-- FATE#316883 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         8192
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256
        </para>
       </entry>
       <!-- FATE#315438 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         2048
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         480
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum amount of RAM (theoretical/certified)
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         &gt; 1 PiB/64 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         10 TiB/256 GiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <!-- FATE#315439 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         1 PiB/64 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256 TiB/n.a.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum amount of user space/kernel space
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         128 TiB/128 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         n.a.
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         512 TiB <superscript>1</superscript>/2 EiB
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         256 TiB/256 TiB
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <!-- bnc#708969 -->
        <para>
         Maximum amount of swap space
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         Up to 29 * 64 GB (x86_64) or 30 * 64 GB (other architectures)
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of processes
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         1048576
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum number of threads per process
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         Upper limit depends on memory and other parameters (tested with more
         than 120,000)<superscript>2</superscript>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Maximum size per block device
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         Up to 8 EiB on all 64-bit architectures
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <!-- bnc#550958 -->
       <entry>
        <para>
         FD_SETSIZE
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry namest="x86-64" nameend="aarch64">
        <para>
         1024
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>1</superscript></emphasis> By default,
    the user space memory limit on the POWER architecture is 128 TiB. However,
    you can explicitly request mmaps up to 512 TiB.
   </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>2</superscript></emphasis> The total
    number of all processes and all threads on a system may not be higher than
    the <quote>maximum number of processes</quote>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="TechInfo-Virtualization">
   <title>Virtualization</title>
   <section xml:id="TechInfo-live-migration">
    <!-- v/ FATE#324059 -->
    <title>Supported Live Migration Scenarios</title>
    <para>
     You can migrate a virtual machine from one physical machine to another.
     The following live migration scenarios are supported under both KVM and
     Xen:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SLE 12 SP3 to SLE 15
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SLE 12 SP4 to SLE 15 (after SLE 12 SP4 has been released)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SLE 15 to SLE 15
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SLE 15 to SLE 15 SP1 (after SLE 15 SP1 has been released)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="TechInfo-KVM">
    <title>KVM Limits</title>
    <informaltable frame="all">
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry><emphasis>SLES 15 SP1 Virtual Machine (VM)</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry>Limits</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum Physical Memory per Host
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          64 TiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum Physical CPUs per Host
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          8192
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum VMs per Host
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Unlimited (total number of virtual CPUs in all guests being no
          greater than 8 times the number of CPU cores in the host)
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum Virtual CPUs per VM
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          288
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum Memory per VM
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          4 TiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
     Virtual Host Server (VHS) limits are identical to those of SUSE Linux
     Enterprise Server.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="TechInfo-XEN">
    <title>Xen Limits</title>
    <para>
     Since SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 SP2, we removed the 32-bit
     hypervisor as a virtualization host. 32-bit virtual guests are not
     affected and are fully supported with the provided 64-bit hypervisor.
    </para>
    <!-- bnc#732995 -->
    <informaltable frame="all">
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry><emphasis>SLES 15 SP1 Virtual Machine (VM)</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry>Limits</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum number of virtual CPUs per VM
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          128
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum amount of memory per VM
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 GiB x86_32, 2 TiB x86_64
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Suspend and hibernate modes
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Not supported
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <informaltable frame="all">
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry><emphasis>SLES 15 SP1 Virtual Host Server (VHS)</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry>Limits</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum number of physical CPUs
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1024
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum number of virtual CPUs
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Unlimited (total number of virtual CPUs in all guests being no
          greater than 8 times the number of CPU cores in the host)
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum amount of physical memory
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 TiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum amount of Dom0 physical memory
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          500 GiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <!-- FIXME: The legends we use across these tables are very differently
     formatted. Unify. - sknorr, 2016-07-14 -->
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>PV:</title>
       <para>
        Paravirtualization
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>FV:</title>
       <para>
        Full virtualization
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For more information about acronyms, see the virtualization documentation
     provided at
     <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/"/>.
    </para>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="TechInfo-Filesystems" remap="TechInfo:Filesystems">
   <title>File Systems</title>
   <!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" xml:id="fate-322477" remap="TechInfo:Filesystems">
    <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
    <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322477" -->
    <title>Creating a Swap-File on a Btrfs File System</title>
    <para>
     Creating a swap file on a Btrfs file system fails with "BTRFS warning
     (device …): swapfile must not be copy-on-write".
    </para>
    <para>
     A swap file needs to be explicitly excluded from copy-on-write updates.
     You can achieve this by running <literal>chattr +C</literal> on the file.
     The following example creates a 512MB swap file at
     <literal>/swap.img</literal>.
    </para>
<screen>touch /swap.img
chattr +C /swap.img
dd bs=512M count=1 if=/dev/zero of=/swap.img
chmod 600 /swap.img
mkswap /swap.img
swapon /swap.img</screen>
   </section>
   <!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section xml:id="TechInfo-Filesystems-Comparison">
    <title>Comparison of Supported File Systems</title>
    <para>
     SUSE Linux Enterprise was the first enterprise Linux distribution to
     support journaling file systems and logical volume managers back in 2000.
     Later, we introduced XFS to Linux, which today is seen as the primary work
     horse for large-scale file systems, systems with heavy load and multiple
     parallel reading and writing operations. With SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, we
     went the next step of innovation and started using the copy-on-write file
     system Btrfs as the default for the operating system, to support system
     snapshots and rollback.
    </para>
    <!-- bnc#903673: use ascii symbols -->
    <!-- bsc#1064279: update for SLE 12/15-->
    <simplelist type="vert"><member><emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> supported</member><member><emphasis role="bold">–</emphasis> unsupported</member>
    </simplelist>
    <informaltable frame="all">
     <tgroup cols="5">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="28*"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="18*"/>
      <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="18*"/>
      <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4" colwidth="18*"/>
      <colspec colnum="5" colname="c5" colwidth="18*"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry>Feature</entry>
        <entry>Btrfs</entry>
        <entry>XFS</entry>
        <entry>Ext4</entry>
        <entry>OCFS 2 <superscript>1</superscript>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Support in products
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          SLE HA
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Data/metadata journaling
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A <superscript>2</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Journal internal/external
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A <superscript>2</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Journal checksumming
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A <superscript>2</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Subvolumes
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Offline extend/shrink
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / – <superscript>3</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Online extend/shrink
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Inode allocation map
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          B-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          B+-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          table
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          B-tree
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Sparse files
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Tail packing
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Small files stored inline
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + (in metadata)
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + (in inode)
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + (in inode)
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Defragmentation
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <!-- FIXME: Plans to add defragmentation for OCFS 2, ask again. -
          sknorr, 2017-10-27 -->
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Extended file attributes/ACLs
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          User/group quotas
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          – / –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          + / +
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Project quotas
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Subvolume quotas
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          N/A
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <!-- All fs's can dump/restore metadata, but not all can
          dump/restore actual data (via Goldwyn Rodrigues). - sknorr,
          2017-10-26 -->
         <para>
          Data dump/restore
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          +
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          –
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Block size default
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry namest="c2" nameend="c5">
         <para>
          4 KiB <superscript>4</superscript>
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum file system size
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          8 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          4 PiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum file size
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          16 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          8 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          1 EiB
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          4 PiB
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <!-- FIXME: Better make these footnotes? Need to check compatibility of the
     yast XSL stylesheet first. - sknorr, 2016-07-14 -->
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>1</superscript></emphasis> OCFS 2 is
     fully supported as part of the SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability
     Extension.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>2</superscript></emphasis> Btrfs is a
     copy-on-write file system. Instead of journaling changes before writing
     them in-place, it writes them to a new location and then links the new
     location in. Until the last write, the changes are not
     <quote>committed</quote>. Because of the nature of the file system, quotas
     are implemented based on subvolumes (<literal>qgroups</literal>).
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>3</superscript></emphasis> To extend an
     OCFS 2 file system, the cluster must be online but the file system itself
     must be unmounted.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold"><superscript>4</superscript></emphasis> The block
     size default varies with different host architectures. 64 KiB is used on
     POWER, 4 KiB on other systems. The actual size used can be checked with
     the command <command>getconf</command>
     <replaceable>PAGE_SIZE</replaceable>.
    </para>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">Additional Notes</bridgehead>
    <para>
     Maximum file size above can be larger than the file system's actual size
     because of the use of sparse blocks. All standard file systems on SUSE
     Linux Enterprise Server have LFS, which gives a maximum file size of
     2<superscript>63</superscript> bytes in theory.
    </para>
    <para>
     The numbers in the above table assume that the file systems are using a
     4 KiB block size which is the most common standard. When using different
     block sizes, the results are different.
    </para>
    <para>
     In this document: 1024 Bytes = 1 KiB; 1024 KiB = 1 MiB; 1024 MiB = 1 GiB;
     1024 GiB = 1 TiB; 1024 TiB = 1 PiB; 1024 PiB = 1 EiB. See also
     <link xlink:href="http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     <!-- bnc#608543 and bnc#574572 -->
     NFSv4 with IPv6 is only supported for the client side. An NFSv4 server
     with IPv6 is not supported.
    </para>
    <para>
     <!-- bnc#606288 -->
     The version of Samba shipped with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1
     delivers integration with Windows Active Directory domains. In addition,
     we provide the clustered version of Samba as part of SUSE Linux Enterprise
     High Availability Extension 15 SP1.
    </para>
    <para>
     <!-- bsc#1073261 -->
     Some file system features are available in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15
     SP1 but are not supported by SUSE. By default, the file system drivers in
     SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP1 will refuse mounting file systems that
     use unsupported features (in particular, in read-write mode). To enable
     unsupported features, set the module parameter
     <literal>allow_unsupported=1</literal> in
     <filename>/etc/modprobe.d</filename> or write the value
     <literal>1</literal> to
     <filename>/sys/module/<replaceable>MODULE_NAME</replaceable>/parameters/allow_unsupported</filename>.
     However, note that setting this option will render your kernel and thus
     your system unsupported.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="TechInfo-Filesystems-Btrfs">
    <title>Supported Btrfs Features</title>
    <para>
     The following table lists supported and unsupported Btrfs features across
     multiple SLES versions.
    </para>
    <simplelist type="vert"><member><emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> supported</member><member><emphasis role="bold">–</emphasis> unsupported</member>
    </simplelist>
    <!-- Table according to bsc#979501, this attachment:
     https://bugzilla.suse.com/attachment.cgi?id=687340 -->
    <informaltable>
     <tgroup cols="6">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="feature" colwidth="6.5cm"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="11SP4" colwidth="*"/>
      <colspec colnum="3" colname="12SP3" colwidth="*"/>
      <colspec colnum="4" colname="12SP4" colwidth="*"/>
      <colspec colnum="5" colname="15GA" colwidth="*"/>
      <colspec colnum="6" colname="15SP1" colwidth="*"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <!-- Remove unsupported OS's. -->
        <entry>Feature</entry>
        <entry>SLES 11 SP4</entry>
        <entry>SLES 12 SP3</entry>
        <entry>SLES 12 SP4</entry>
        <entry>SLES 15 GA</entry>
        <entry>SLES 15 SP1</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>Copy on Write</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Free Space Tree (Free Space Cache v2)</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Snapshots/Subvolumes</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Swap Files</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Metadata Integrity</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Data Integrity</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Online Metadata Scrubbing</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Automatic Defragmentation</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Manual Defragmentation</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>In-band Deduplication</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Out-of-band Deduplication</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Quota Groups</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Metadata Duplication</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Changing Metadata UUID</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Multiple Devices</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 0</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 1</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 10</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 5</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>RAID 6</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Hot Add/Remove</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Device Replace</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Seeding Devices</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Compression</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Big Metadata Blocks</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Skinny Metadata</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Send Without File Data</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Send/Receive</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Inode Cache</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>Fallocate with Hole Punch</entry>
        <entry>–</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
        <entry>+</entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="TechInfo-Java">
   <title>Supported Java Versions</title>
   <para>
    The following table lists Java implementations available in SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server 15 SP1.
   </para>
   <!-- see: jsc#SLE-3101 -->
   <para>
    Please note that the OpenJDK development model has changed and with it the
    way we update and support it. In the future, we will upgrade Java to a new
    release with every service pack and we will remove older, unsupported
    releases with every service pack. The LTS version will be the default JDK.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see
    <link xlink:href="https://www.oracle.com/java/technologies/java-se-support-roadmap.html"/>.
   </para>
   <!-- relevant source: https://confluence.suse.com/display/SLEPM/openJDK+lifecycle
    and: bsc#1171541 -->
   <informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="4">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2"/>
     <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3"/>
     <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>Name (Package Name)</entry>
       <entry>Version</entry>
       <entry>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server Module</entry>
       <entry>Support</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>OpenJDK (<package>java-11-openjdk</package>)</entry>
       <entry>11</entry>
       <entry>Base System</entry>
       <entry>SUSE, L3, until 2026-12-31</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>OpenJDK (<package>java-1_8_0-openjdk</package>)</entry>
       <entry>1.8.0</entry>
       <entry>Legacy</entry>
       <entry>SUSE, L3, until 2026-12-31</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>IBM Java (<package>java-1_8_0-ibm</package>)</entry>
       <entry>1.8.0</entry>
       <entry>Legacy</entry>
       <entry>External, until 2025-04-30</entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="Sourcecode">
  <title>Obtaining Source Code</title>
  <para>
   This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU General
   Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the source code that
   corresponds to the GPL-licensed material.
   <!-- bsc#1150672 -->
   The source code is available for download at
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/server/download/"/> on
   Medium 2. For up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
   request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Send requests by e-mail
   to <link xlink:href="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/>. SUSE may charge
   a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="Legal">
  <title>Legal Notices</title>
  <para>
   SUSE makes no representations or warranties with regard to the contents or
   use of this documentation, and specifically disclaims any express or implied
   warranties of merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose.
   Further, SUSE reserves the right to revise this publication and to make
   changes to its content, at any time, without the obligation to notify any
   person or entity of such revisions or changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Further, SUSE makes no representations or warranties with regard to any
   software, and specifically disclaims any express or implied warranties of
   merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose. Further, SUSE
   reserves the right to make changes to any and all parts of SUSE software, at
   any time, without any obligation to notify any person or entity of such
   changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Any products or technical information provided under this Agreement may be
   subject to U.S. export controls and the trade laws of other countries. You
   agree to comply with all export control regulations and to obtain any
   required licenses or classifications to export, re-export, or import
   deliverables. You agree not to export or re-export to entities on the
   current U.S. export exclusion lists or to any embargoed or terrorist
   countries as specified in U.S. export laws. You agree to not use
   deliverables for prohibited nuclear, missile, or chemical/biological
   weaponry end uses. Refer to
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> for more
   information on exporting SUSE software. SUSE assumes no responsibility for
   your failure to obtain any necessary export approvals.
  </para>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
   <?dbtimestamp format="Y"?>
   SUSE LLC.
  </para>
  <para>
   This release notes document is licensed under a Creative Commons
   Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License (CC-BY-ND-4.0). You
   should have received a copy of the license along with this document. If not,
   see <link xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE has intellectual property rights relating to technology embodied in the
   product that is described in this document. In particular, and without
   limitation, these intellectual property rights may include one or more of
   the U.S. patents listed at
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> and one or more
   additional patents or pending patent applications in the U.S. and other
   countries.
  </para>
  <para>
   For SUSE trademarks, see SUSE Trademark and Service Mark list
   (<link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/>). All third-party
   trademarks are the property of their respective owners.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
