<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications</productname>
  <productnumber>12 SP2</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications combines SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server and its High Availability Extension with additional
    software specifically meant to simplify running and managing SAP
    applications. These are the release notes of SLES for SAP Applications.
   </para>

   <para>
    Manuals can be found in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of the
    installation media for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
    Applications. Any documentation (if installed) can be found in the
    <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> directory of the installed system.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SLES for SAP Applications</title>
  <para>
   Make sure to also review the release notes for the base product, SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP2 which are published at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SUSE-SLES/12-SP2/"/>.
  </para>
<!-- This section is commented because we are (ab)using the FATE category of
  the same name for "Features." This one was empty anyway- sknorr, 2016-09-12
  -->
<!-- <section id="Intro.New" role="remove-empty">
   <title>What Is New?</title>
   <para></para>
  </section> -->
  <section id="Intro.Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SLES for SAP Applications</title>
   <para>
    Support requires an appropriate subscription from SUSE. For more
    information, see
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    General Support Statement
   </para>
   <para>
    The following definitions apply:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L1: Installation and problem determination - technical support
      designed to provide compatibility information, installation and
      configuration assistance, usage support, on-going maintenance and
      basic troubleshooting. Level 1 Support is not intended to correct
      product defect errors.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L2: Reproduction of problem isolation - technical support designed to
      duplicate customer problems, isolate problem areas and potential
      issues, and provide resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1
      Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L3: Code Debugging and problem resolution - technical support designed
      to resolve complex problems by engaging engineering in patch
      provision, resolution of product defects which have been identified by
      Level 2 Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    SUSE will only support the usage of original (unchanged or not
    recompiled) packages.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- There is no 12 version of the "Features" category, so we are using
 Intro.New as a catch-all. - sknorr, 2016-09-12 -->
 <section id="Intro.New" remap="Intro:New">
  <title>Features</title>
  <para>
   This section includes an overview of major new features provided by SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications.
  </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320360" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="5"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320360" -->
   <title>saptune: Comprehensive System Tuning Management for SAP Applications</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis>Automatically adjust system parameters to allow running SAP
    applications at satisfactory performance.</emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    SLES for SAP Applications 12 SP2 now ships with the system tuning
    utility <literal>saptune</literal>. It can be used to replace
    <literal>sapconf</literal> (which is still available, however). The
    utility unleashes the full potential of system hardware for all SAP
    workloads by optimizing the CPU scheduler, memory management,
    disk/network I/O and more. <literal>saptune</literal> can also tune for
    the following scenarios:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">SAP S/4 HANA:</emphasis> These applications use
      the same tuning techniques that also apply to SAP HANA and SAP
      NetWeaver and they do not require special tuning techniques.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Virtualized environments:</emphasis> You are
      advised to carefully review tuning techniques described by SAP in
      various SAP notes with regard to virtualized environments, especially
      the parameters involving the hypervisor software itself.
      <literal>saptune</literal> helps implement SAP Note 2161991 by
      adjusting the I/O scheduler. This technique is generally favorable in
      all virtualized guests and cloud instances.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For information about the usage of <literal>saptune</literal>, see the
    <literal>saptune</literal> documentation.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320633" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="10"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320633" -->
   <title>Benchmarking HANA Performance Under Optimized System Configuration</title>
   <para>
    Optimize the operating system configuration for running SAP HANA
    benchmarks.
   </para>
   <para>
    The new program <literal>saptune</literal> can automate system
    optimization to unleash the full potential of your SAP HANA deployment.
    Explore all tuning options of the program and find the best combination
    for your system with SAP HANA benchmarks. For information about the
    usage of <literal>saptune</literal>, see the <literal>saptune</literal>
    documentation.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-321142" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321142" -->
   <title>Accessing SUSE Product Registration, Modules, and Extensions from the Desktop</title>
   <para>
    In SLES for SAP 12 SP2, the desktop includes a shortcut
    <emphasis>Product Registration</emphasis> which allows starting YaST's
    SCC Registration module. This enables you to easily discover software
    and services that support SAP solutions.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320566" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320566" -->
   <title>Monitor and Control saprouter via systemd</title>
   <para>
    You can now monitor and control the SAP Network Interface Router via
    systemd with the new service <literal>saprouter.service</literal>
    (contained in the software package <literal>saprouter-systemd</literal>).
   </para>
   <para>
    Make sure to install the SAP Network Interface Router first, then
    install the package <literal>saprouter-systemd</literal>. You can then
    control the SAP router daemon via standard systemd mechanisms and
    commands.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320564" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320564" -->
   <title>New Features in HANA Firewall Configuration Editor</title>
   <para>
    The revamped HANA Firewall configuration editor in YaST offers a
    simplified user interface and enhanced configuration capabilities:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If there are new SAP HANA instances installed after an initial
      firewall configuration, a dialog will prompt you to apply a firewall
      setup to the new instances.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The editor can generate a default set of firewall rules that open
      running SAP HANA services on all network interfaces, including the
      services required for a high availability setup.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320408" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320408" -->
   <title>Support for SAP HANA TDI Environments in the SAP Installation Wizard</title>
   <para>
    The SAP Installation Wizard now follows SAP's recommendation for
    partitioning and creates the following setup:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>/hana/data</literal>, size: RAM*1
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>/hana/log</literal>, size: RAM*1, with a maximum of 512 GB
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>/hana/shared</literal>, size: RAM*1, with a maximum of 1 TB
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>/usr/sap</literal>, size: 52 GB
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320367" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320367" -->
   <title>cryptctl: New Disk Encryption Utility</title>
   <para>
    The new disk encryption utility <literal>cryptctl</literal> helps set up
    LUKS-based disk encryption using randomly generated keys and safely
    keeps them on a dedicated key server.
   </para>
   <para>
    <literal>cryptctl</literal> comprehensively and transparently protects
    application data including configuration files, logs, and databases. It
    does so fulfilling many encryption compliance requirements. The
    encryption mechanism takes full advantage of hardware acceleration to
    improve speeds, incurring only negligible overhead to applications such
    as SAP NetWeaver.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-318793" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318793" -->
   <title>Support for Scale-Out Scenarios in SAPHanaSR</title>
   <para>
    The SAPHanaSR resource agents now also support SAP HANA System
    Replication for scale-out in the performance optimized scenario (package
    SAPHanaSR-ScaleOut).
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.SystemsManagement" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
  <title>Systems Management</title>
  <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-321766" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321766" -->
   <title>Requirements for Installation of SAP HANA SPS 12</title>
   <para>
    Before installing HANA SPS 12 on SLES for SAP 12 SP2, make sure that
    your hardware meets all prerequisites. The root partition must have a
    size of at least 25 GB to fit the operating system and a copy of the SAP
    HANA installer. Ideally, use a size of 50 GB for the root partition.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see
    <ulink url="http://launchpad.support.sap.com/#/notes/1944799">SAP Note
    1944799</ulink> and the <emphasis>Configuration Guide</emphasis>
    attached to it.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-321680" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321680" -->
   <title>Cannot Log In to SAP HANA Graphical User Interface</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis>When a SAP HANA database is installed on SLES for SAP, the
    database administrator user is not able to log in to the graphical
    interface. This issue also occurs when installing with the newest
    available release of the SAP HANA installer.</emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    There are currently no workarounds available.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320407" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320407" -->
   <title>Enrolling in a Microsoft Active Directory Domain via YaST</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis>You can configure a SLES computer to become a member in
    Microsoft Active Directory to leverage its user account and group
    management. In previous versions of SLES, enrolling a computer in a
    Microsoft Active Directory was a lengthy and error-prone
    procedure.</emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    In SLES 12 SP2, YaST ships with the new configuration tool
    <emphasis>User Logon Management</emphasis> (previously
    <emphasis>Authentication Client</emphasis>) which offers a powerful yet
    simple user interface for joining an Active Directory domain and allows
    authenticating users using those domain accounts. In addition to Active
    Directory, the editor can also set up authentication against a generic
    Kerberos or LDAP service.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="Miscellaneous">
  <title>Miscellaneous</title>
  <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-323648" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323648" -->
   <title>MSR Cannot Be Modified When UEFI Secure Boot Is On</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis> Write access to MSRs (model-specific registers) allows
    userspace applications to modify the running kernel which runs counter
    to the goals of UEFI Secure Boot. Therefore, MSRs cannot be written to
    by tools like </emphasis><literal>cpupower</literal><emphasis> to
    control processor performance when UEFI Secure Boot is enabled on a
    system. </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis> This also prevents tuning tools, such as
    </emphasis><literal>saptune</literal><emphasis> and
    </emphasis><literal>sapconf</literal><emphasis> from working correctly.
    </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    The only current workaround is disabling Secure Boot.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="Sourcecode">
  <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
<!-- msvec and legal (ciaran), 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location as the first chapter -->
  <para>
   This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
   General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the source
   code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material. The source code is
   available for download at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. Also,
   for up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
   request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Requests should be
   sent by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/> or as
   otherwise instructed at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. SUSE
   may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Feedback">
  <title>More Information and Feedback</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Read the READMEs on the media.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get detailed changelog information about a particular package from the
     RPM:
    </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp <replaceable>FILE_NAME</replaceable>.rpm</screen>
    <para>
     <replaceable>FILE_NAME</replaceable> is the name of the RPM.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
     first medium for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated
     packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of
     first medium of the SLES for SAP Applications media.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/sles_for_sap/"/> contains
     additional or updated documentation for SLES for SAP Applications.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For the latest product news from SUSE, visit
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?>
   SUSE LLC.
  </para>
  <para>
   Thank you for using SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications in
   your business.
  </para>
  <para>
   The SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications Team.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
