<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications</productname>
  <productnumber>12 SP3</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications combines SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server and its High Availability Extension with additional
    software specifically meant to simplify running and managing SAP
    applications. These are the release notes of SLES for SAP Applications.
   </para>

   <para>
    Manuals can be found in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of the
    installation media for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
    Applications. Any documentation (if installed) can be found in the
    <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> directory of the installed system.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="Intro" remap="Intro">
  <title>SLES for SAP Applications</title>
  <para>
   Make sure to also review the release notes for the base product, SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP3 which are published at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SUSE-SLES/12-SP3/"/>.
  </para>
<!-- This section is commented because we are (ab)using the FATE category of
  the same name for "Features." This one was empty anyway- sknorr, 2016-09-12
  -->
<!-- <section id="Intro.New" role="remove-empty">
   <title>What Is New?</title>
   <para></para>
  </section> -->
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-324251" remap="Intro">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324251" -->
   <title>ESPOS Updates Shipped Directly in Update Repositories</title>
   <para>
    In SLES for SAP 11, updates related to Extended Service Pack Overlay
    Support (ESPOS) were shipped from special repositories.
   </para>
   <para>
    In SLES for SAP 12 SP3 and later, updates related to ESPOS are shipped
    directly from the <literal>Update</literal> repositories. This means,
    there is no separate ESPOS repository to set up.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  <section id="Intro.Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SLES for SAP Applications</title>
   <para>
    Support requires an appropriate subscription from SUSE. For more
    information, see
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    General Support Statement
   </para>
   <para>
    The following definitions apply:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L1: Installation and problem determination - technical support
      designed to provide compatibility information, installation and
      configuration assistance, usage support, on-going maintenance and
      basic troubleshooting. Level 1 Support is not intended to correct
      product defect errors.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L2: Reproduction of problem isolation - technical support designed to
      duplicate customer problems, isolate problem areas and potential
      issues, and provide resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1
      Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L3: Code Debugging and problem resolution - technical support designed
      to resolve complex problems by engaging engineering in patch
      provision, resolution of product defects which have been identified by
      Level 2 Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    SUSE will only support the usage of original (unchanged or not
    recompiled) packages.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- There is no 12 version of the "Features" category, so we are using
 Intro.New as a catch-all. - sknorr, 2016-09-12 -->
 <section id="Intro.New" remap="Intro:New">
  <title>Features</title>
  <para>
   This section includes an overview of major new features provided by SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications.
  </para>
  <section role="notoc" id="jsc-SLE-12242">
   <title>Priority Fencing Delay Has Been Added</title>
   <para>
    This change introduces a specified delay for the fencings that are targeting
    the lost nodes with the highest total resource priority in case there is no
    majority of the nodes in the given cluster partition.
   </para>
   <para>
     By default, priority fencing delay is disabled.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see <literal>priority-fencing-delay</literal> in the
    <ulink url="https://www.clusterlabs.org/pacemaker/doc/2.1/Pacemaker_Explained/html/options.html#cluster-options">Pacemaker documentation</ulink>.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-322293" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="5"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322293" -->
   <title>cryptctl Disk Encryption Utility Verifies Client Computer Identity via TLS certificates</title>
   <para>
    Previously, the <literal>cryptctl</literal> server would hand out an
    encryption key to all computers that requested one using a valid disk
    UUID. The client computer's identity was not further verified.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the version of <literal>cryptctl</literal> shipped with SLES for SAP
    12 SP3, servers can optionally also verify the identity of client
    computers via TLS certificates for all communications that take place
    between them.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-322979" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="10"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322979" -->
   <title>cryptctl Disk Encryption Utility Can Work with Dedicated Key Management Appliances</title>
   <para>
    KMIP (Key Management Interoperability Protocol) is an industrial
    standard protocol for managing cryptographic keys. In the latest
    <literal>cryptctl</literal>, KMIP version 1.3 is supported so that
    <literal>cryptctl</literal> can store and manage disk encryption keys on
    a KMIP-compatible key management appliance.
   </para>
   <para>
    Be aware that the decision to use a key management appliance for key
    storage must be made during the initial server setup. There is no
    migration path between storing keys on a key management appliance versus
    on a server's hard drive.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-326973" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326973" -->
   <title>SLES for SAP Identifies as SLES in /etc/os-release</title>
   <para>
    SLES for SAP 12 SP3 now uses the value <literal>SUSE Linux Enterprise
    Server 12 SP3</literal> as its <literal>PRETTY_NAME</literal> in
    <literal>/etc/os-release</literal>.This change improves general
    compatibility with application checking for a standard SLES installation
    only.
   </para>
   <para>
    However, if you are using a tool that identifies operating systems by
    their <literal>NAME</literal>, <literal>PRETTY_NAME</literal>, or
    <literal>ID</literal> value, make sure to adapt to the change. For
    example, the configuration management tool Ansible uses
    <literal>PRETTY_NAME</literal> to check for the OS.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-323465" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323465" -->
   <title>SAP NetWeaver Integration</title>
   <para>
    The SAP NetWeaver integration has been improved to match the growing
    usability of cluster solutions especially during SAP maintenance
    procedures. This includes the visibility of the cluster solution in the
    SAP Management Console (SAP MC) and support for SAP kernel updates.
   </para>
   <para>
    <literal>sap_suse_cluster_connector</literal> has been updated to API
    version 3 to support the newest features and calls from
    <literal>sapstartsrv</literal>. This includes transparent support for
    SAP rolling kernel switches (RKS) for central services instances and
    replication instances.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-322612" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322612" -->
   <title>Improved Documentation for Setup and Usage of clamsap</title>
   <para>
    The documentation for <literal>clamsap</literal> has been added to the
    package and a new chapter in the online documentation has been added.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-322387" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322387" -->
   <title>Modified RPM Software Pattern for SAP Business One</title>
   <para>
    The RPM software pattern for SAP Business One has been adjusted to
    include packages required by version 9.3.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-322281" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322281" -->
   <title>Installation Wizard Support for SAP HANA MDC</title>
   <para>
    SAP HANA allows installing multiple database containers (MDC) within a
    single SAP HANA installation. Now the SAP Installation Wizard allows for
    such an installation as well.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-322066" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322066" -->
   <title>Extended clone-master-clean-up.sh Script</title>
   <para>
    Further clean up steps have been added to
    <literal>clone-master-clean-up.sh</literal>, such as
    <literal>MachineId</literal> and UUIDs within
    <literal>/etc/fstab</literal>, etc.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320408" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320408" -->
   <title>Support for SAP HANA TDI Environments in the SAP Installation Wizard</title>
   <tip role="compact">
    <para>
     This entry has appeared in a previous release notes document.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
    The SAP Installation Wizard now follows SAP's recommendation for
    partitioning and creates the following setup:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>/hana/data</literal>, size: RAM*1
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>/hana/log</literal>, size: RAM*1, with a maximum of 512 GB
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>/hana/shared</literal>, size: RAM*1, with a maximum of 1 TB
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>/usr/sap</literal>, size: 52 GB
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320368" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320368" -->
   <title>yast2-hana-update Provides an Easier Way to Upgrade SAP HANA Cluster</title>
   <para>
    An important and regularly occurring maintenance task for SAP HANA
    clusters is upgrading the SAP HANA database. If installing the initial
    cluster is already critical, upgrading is even more so, as you now need
    to care about data integrity and system availability.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <literal>yast2-hana-update</literal> module provides a YaST workflow
    that will guide you step-by-step on the process of upgrading your SAP
    HANA in a SUSE cluster setup. The entire process is based on the
    so-called Near Zero Downtime Upgrade process described in the official
    SAP HANA documentation. The wizard handles the part of the procedure
    related to the SUSE cluster, leaving only some steps related to be
    performed manually by the SAP HANA administrator.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320359" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320359" -->
   <title>Extended sapconf/saptune Coverage</title>
   <para>
    The packages <literal>sapconf</literal> and <literal>saptune</literal>
    have been extended to cover system tuning for SAP Adaptive Server
    Enterprise and SAP Business Objects.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.Power" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
  <title>POWER-Specific Features</title>
  <para>
   The following notes apply to SLES for SAP Applications on the POWER
   architecture.
  </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-322470" remap="InfraPackArch:Power">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322470" -->
   <title>512 TB Virtual Address Space on POWER</title>
   <para>
    Certain workloads require a large virtual address space for a single
    process
   </para>
   <para>
    The virtual address space limit has been increased from 64 TB to 512 TB
    on the POWER architecture. To maintain compatibility with older software
    and hardware, processes are limited to 128 TB virtual address space
    unless they explicitly map memory above 128 TB.
   </para>
   <para>
    This functionality is supported starting with kernel 4.4.103. We always
    recommend using the latest kernel update to get fixes for any issues
    found over the product lifetime.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="Sourcecode">
  <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
<!-- msvec and legal (ciaran), 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location as the first chapter -->
  <para>
   This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
   General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the source
   code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material. The source code is
   available for download at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. Also,
   for up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
   request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Requests should be
   sent by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/> or as
   otherwise instructed at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. SUSE
   may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Feedback">
  <title>More Information and Feedback</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Read the READMEs on the media.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get detailed changelog information about a particular package from the
     RPM:
    </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp <replaceable>FILE_NAME</replaceable>.rpm</screen>
    <para>
     <replaceable>FILE_NAME</replaceable> is the name of the RPM.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
     first medium for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated
     packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of
     first medium of the SLES for SAP Applications media.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/sles_for_sap/"/> contains
     additional or updated documentation for SLES for SAP Applications.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For the latest product news from SUSE, visit
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?>
   SUSE LLC.
  </para>
  <para>
   Thank you for using SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications in
   your business.
  </para>
  <para>
   The SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications Team.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
