<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
<?dbsuse-bugtracker url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi" product="SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 12 SP3" component="Release Notes" assignee="lukas.kucharczyk@suse.com" ?>
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications</productname>
  <productnumber>15 GA</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    These are the release notes of SLES for SAP Applications. SLES for SAP
    Applications combines SUSE Linux Enterprise Server and its High
    Availability Extension with additional software specifically meant to
    simplify running and managing SAP applications.
   </para>

   <para condition="beta;pre">
    This product will be released in June 2018.
   </para>

   <para condition="maintained">
    These release notes are updated periodically. The latest version is
    always available at <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>.
    General documentation can be found at:
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles_for_sap/"/>.
   </para>

   <para condition="unmaintained">
    The support period for SLES for SAP Applications 15 GA has ended. To
    keep systems secure and supported, upgrade to a current SLES for SAP
    Applications version. Before starting the upgrade, make sure to apply
    all maintenance updates.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SLES for SAP Applications</title>
  <para>
   Make sure to also review the release notes for the base product, SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server 15 GA which are published at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SUSE-SLES/15"/>.
  </para>
<!-- This section is commented because we are (ab)using the FATE category of
  the same name for "Features." This one was empty anyway- sknorr, 2016-09-12
  -->
<!-- <section id="Intro.New" role="remove-empty">
   <title>What Is New?</title>
   <para></para>
  </section> -->
  <section id="Intro.Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SLES for SAP Applications</title>
   <para>
    Support requires an appropriate subscription from SUSE. For more
    information, see
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    General Support Statement
   </para>
   <para>
    The following definitions apply:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L1: Installation and problem determination - technical support
      designed to provide compatibility information, installation and
      configuration assistance, usage support, on-going maintenance and
      basic troubleshooting. Level 1 Support is not intended to correct
      product defect errors.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L2: Reproduction of problem isolation - technical support designed to
      duplicate customer problems, isolate problem areas and potential
      issues, and provide resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1
      Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L3: Code Debugging and problem resolution - technical support designed
      to resolve complex problems by engaging engineering in patch
      provision, resolution of product defects which have been identified by
      Level 2 Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    SUSE will only support the usage of original (unchanged or not
    recompiled) packages.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- There is no 12 version of the "Features" category, so we are using
 Intro.New as a catch-all. - sknorr, 2016-09-12 -->
 <section id="Intro.New" remap="Intro:New">
  <title>Features</title>
  <para>
   This section includes an overview of major new features provided by SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications.
  </para>
  <section role="notoc" id="jsc-SLE-12242">
   <title>Priority Fencing Delay Has Been Added</title>
   <para>
    This change introduces a specified delay for the fencings that are targeting
    the lost nodes with the highest total resource priority in case there is no
    majority of the nodes in the given cluster partition.
   </para>
   <para>
     By default, priority fencing delay is disabled.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see <literal>priority-fencing-delay</literal> in the
    <ulink url="https://www.clusterlabs.org/pacemaker/doc/2.1/Pacemaker_Explained/html/options.html#cluster-options">Pacemaker documentation</ulink>.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325363" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325363" -->
   <title>sapconf Automatically Starts Dependent Daemons After Installation</title>
   <para>
    <literal>sapconf</literal> now will automatically set parameters and
    start necessary daemons after the installation of the
    <literal>sapconf</literal> package. The following daemons will be
    started automatically via systemd dependencies: <literal>tuned</literal>, <literal>uuidd.socket</literal>, and <literal>sysstat</literal>.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Reboot to Enable Parameter UserTaskMax</title>
    <para>
     During the first installation of the <literal>sapconf</literal>
     package, the parameter <literal>UserTaskMax</literal> will be set to
     the recommended value. However, to be effective, a system reboot is
     still needed.
    </para>
   </important>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-324490" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324490" -->
   <title>sapconf Legacy Command-Line Interface /usr/sbin/sapconf Has Been Removed</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis> The CLI of </emphasis><literal>sapconf</literal><emphasis>
    was deprecated since the release of SLES for SAP 12 SP1 and kept only
    for backward compatibility with SLES 11. </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    With SLES 15, <literal>/usr/bin/sapconf</literal> was removed
    completely. To enable tuning profiles, use <literal>tuned-adm</literal>
    directly: <literal>tuned-adm profile [PROFILE]</literal>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-324489" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324489" -->
   <title>New sapconf Profile Is Used Instead of Profiles for Specific SAP Applications</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis> In the past, </emphasis><literal>sapconf</literal><emphasis>
    provided profiles for specific SAP applications that was deployed, for
    example, SAP HANA, SAP Netweaver, SAP ASE, SAP BOBJ, but then demanded
    more steps during the system configuration for SAP applications.
    </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    To simplify the system configuration for deployment of SAP applications
    and after a revision of the configurations needed by each profile, all
    configurations were consolidated in only one profile, called
    <literal>sapconf</literal> that will is used to configure the system for
    any SAP applications.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325727" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325727" -->
   <title>Package insserv-compat Has Been Added to SAP Application Server Base Pattern</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis> SAP Applications depends on a
    </emphasis><literal>sapinit</literal><emphasis> System V script that is
    widely used in all SAP Applications. </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    The package <literal>insserv-compat</literal> was included to be
    installed on the SAP Applications Server Base pattern by default, as
    this pattern is used and recommended to configure a SAP Application
    Server. That way, it will provide the System V compatibility until SAP
    fully adopts systemd unit scripts.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-326967" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/326967" -->
   <title>Support for SAP HANA Workloads on Intel Optane DC Memory</title>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 and SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
    Applications 15 add support for Intel Optane DC memory. This enables SAP
    workloads, such as SAP HANA to benefit from persistent memory in the
    future to shorten start times of the system and provide better overall
    system stability. Currently, configurations up to 12 TB of NVDIMMs plus
    3 TB of regular DIMMS of supported memory and 4 socket machines have
    been tested. Additional configurations will be tested over time.
   </para>
   <para>
    From a file system perspective, the XFS file system is supported for the
    NVDIMMs, with SAP HANA running in DAX mode. SUSE intends to keep the
    leading position as technology provider, working closely with SAP on
    future developments.
   </para>
   <para>
    If there are <literal>pmem</literal> namespaces, these need to be
    destroyed before the installation. To mount persistent memory directly
    on boot, we recommend adding the <literal>nofail</literal> mount option
    in <literal>/etc/fstab</literal> as it can take a long time for the
    <literal>/dev/pmem</literal> devices to become usable.
   </para>
   <para>
    For example:
   </para>
<screen>/dev/pmem0    /mnt/pmem0    xfs    dax,nofail    0  0
/dev/pmem1    /mnt/pmem1    xfs    dax,nofail    0  0</screen>
   <para>
    Namespaces need to be created individually. That means, you need to
    execute the following command for each namespace you want to create:
   </para>
<screen>ndctl create-namespace --mode=fsdax --map=dev</screen>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="InstUpgrade">
  <title>Installation and Upgrade</title>
  <para/>
  <section id="InstUpgrade.Installation" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
   <title>Installation</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325479" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325479" -->
    <title>New SLES for SAP Applications System Role</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>With the adoption of a unified installer in SLE 15, system
     roles are the way to customize the installation for each product's
     needs.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The new SLES for SAP Applications system roles provides the same
     installation workflow provided on the SLES for SAP 12 SP3 installation
     media, offering specific steps specially designed for SAP Applications,
     such as:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SAP Installation Wizard usage option
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Special partitioning recommendations
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       RDP access enablement
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Skip the first user creation
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Base, Gnome Basic and SAP Server Pattern installation
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-323778" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
 <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
 <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323778" -->
    <title>Page Cache Limit Is Now Opt-in cgroup Isolation</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The kernel swaps out rarely accessed memory pages to use freed
     memory pages as cache to speed up file system operations, for example
     during backup operations. Certain applications use large amounts of
     memory for accelerated access to business data. Rarely accessed parts of
     this memory are subject of this swap out. Later access to swapped out
     memory regions results in poor application response times.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In previous SUSE Linux Enterprise versions there was a tunable known as
     page cache limit to mitigate this problem. This has now been replaced
     with a more mature mainline mechanism known as opt-in memory cgroup
     isolation.
    </para>
    <para>
     A memory cgroup can define its so-called low limit (<literal>memory.low_limit_in_bytes</literal>) which works as a
     protection against memory pressure. Work loads that need to be isolated
     from outside memory management activity should set the value to the
     expected Resident Set Size (RSS) plus some head room. If a memory
     pressure condition triggers on the system and the particular group is
     still under its low limit, its memory is protected against being
     reclaimed. As a result, work loads outside of the cgroup do not need the
     aforementioned capping.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-325548" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Performance">
 <!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
 <!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325548" -->
    <title>sapconf SAP Tuning Tool Sets All Specified Tuning Values on OS Irrespective of Current Value</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> The previous solution only allowed
     </emphasis><literal>sapconf</literal><emphasis> to increase values, but
     in some cases a lower value may be the correct path to take. Therefore,
     </emphasis><literal>sapconf</literal><emphasis> needed to set all values
     irrespective of whether the current value is greater than or less than
     what </emphasis><literal>sapconf</literal><emphasis> wants to set.
     </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <literal>sapconf</literal> provides a default set of values for SAP
     workloads which should apply to the majority of use cases. If a default
     <literal>sapconf</literal> value is not appropriate for any reason (for
     example, special workloads, support cases), then
     <literal>sapconf</literal> offers the possibility to enter own values.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Deprecated">
   <title>Deprecated and Removed Packages</title>
   <section id="jsc-SLE-12171">
     <title><literal>sles4sap-white-papers</literal></title>
     <para>
      The <literal>sles4sap-white-papers</literal> package is obsolete.
      You can find the most recent documentation at <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/sles-sap/15-GA/"/>
     </para>
   </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Feedback">
  <title>More Information and Feedback</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Read the READMEs on the media.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get detailed changelog information about a particular package from the
     RPM:
    </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp <replaceable>FILE_NAME</replaceable>.rpm</screen>
    <para>
     <replaceable>FILE_NAME</replaceable> is the name of the RPM.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
     first medium for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated
     packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of
     first medium of the SLES for SAP Applications media.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles_for_sap/"/>
     contains additional or updated documentation for SLES for SAP
     Applications.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For the latest product news from SUSE, visit
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section id="Sourcecode">
  <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
  <para>
   This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
   General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the source
   code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material.
   The source code is available for download at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/download/sle-sap/"/> on Medium 2.
   For up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon request,
   SUSE will mail a copy of the source code.
   Send requests by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/>.
   SUSE may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Legal">
  <title>Legal Notices</title>
  <para>
   SUSE makes no representations or warranties with regard to the contents
   or use of this documentation, and specifically disclaims any express or
   implied warranties of merchantability or fitness for any particular
   purpose. Further, SUSE reserves the right to revise this publication and
   to make changes to its content, at any time, without the obligation to
   notify any person or entity of such revisions or changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Further, SUSE makes no representations or warranties with regard to any
   software, and specifically disclaims any express or implied warranties of
   merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose. Further, SUSE
   reserves the right to make changes to any and all parts of SUSE software,
   at any time, without any obligation to notify any person or entity of
   such changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Any products or technical information provided under this Agreement may
   be subject to U.S. export controls and the trade laws of other countries.
   You agree to comply with all export control regulations and to obtain any
   required licenses or classifications to export, re-export, or import
   deliverables. You agree not to export or re-export to entities on the
   current U.S. export exclusion lists or to any embargoed or terrorist
   countries as specified in U.S. export laws. You agree to not use
   deliverables for prohibited nuclear, missile, or chemical/biological
   weaponry end uses. Refer to
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> for more information
   on exporting SUSE software. SUSE assumes no responsibility for your
   failure to obtain any necessary export approvals.
  </para>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?>
   SUSE LLC. This release notes document is licensed under a Creative
   Commons Attribution-NoDerivs 3.0 United States License (CC-BY-ND-3.0 US,
   <ulink url="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/us/"/>).
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE has intellectual property rights relating to technology embodied in
   the product that is described in this document. In particular, and
   without limitation, these intellectual property rights may include one or
   more of the U.S. patents listed at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> and one or more
   additional patents or pending patent applications in the U.S. and other
   countries.
  </para>
  <para>
   For SUSE trademarks, see SUSE Trademark and Service Mark list
   (<ulink url="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/>). All third-party
   trademarks are the property of their respective owners.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
