<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
<?dbsuse-bugtracker url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi"
   product="SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 12 SP4"
   component="Release Notes"
   assignee="sknorr@suse.com" ?>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications</productname>
  <productnumber>12 SP4</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications combines SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server and its High Availability Extension with additional
    software specifically meant to simplify running and managing SAP
    applications. These are the release notes of SLES for SAP Applications.
   </para>

   <para>
    Manuals can be found in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of the
    installation media for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
    Applications. Any documentation (if installed) can be found in the
    <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> directory of the installed system.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SLES for SAP Applications</title>
  <para>
   Make sure to also review the release notes for the base product, SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 which are published at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SUSE-SLES/12-SP4/"/>.
  </para>
<!-- This section is commented because we are (ab)using the FATE category of
  the same name for "Features." This one was empty anyway- sknorr, 2016-09-12
  -->
<!-- <section id="Intro.New" role="remove-empty">
   <title>What Is New?</title>
   <para></para>
  </section> -->
  <section id="Intro.Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SLES for SAP Applications</title>
   <para>
    Support requires an appropriate subscription from SUSE. For more
    information, see
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    General Support Statement
   </para>
   <para>
    The following definitions apply:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L1: Installation and problem determination - technical support
      designed to provide compatibility information, installation and
      configuration assistance, usage support, on-going maintenance and
      basic troubleshooting. Level 1 Support is not intended to correct
      product defect errors.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L2: Reproduction of problem isolation - technical support designed to
      duplicate customer problems, isolate problem areas and potential
      issues, and provide resolution for problems not resolved by Level 1
      Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      L3: Code Debugging and problem resolution - technical support designed
      to resolve complex problems by engaging engineering in patch
      provision, resolution of product defects which have been identified by
      Level 2 Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    SUSE will only support the usage of original (unchanged or not
    recompiled) packages.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
<!-- There is no 12 version of the "Features" category, so we are using
 Intro.New as a catch-all. - sknorr, 2016-09-12 -->
 <section id="Intro.New" remap="Intro:New">
  <title>Features</title>
  <para>
   This section includes an overview of major new features provided by SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications.
  </para>
  <section role="notoc" id="jsc-SLE-12242">
   <title>Priority Fencing Delay Has Been Added</title>
   <para>
    This change introduces a specified delay for the fencings that are targeting
    the lost nodes with the highest total resource priority in case there is no
    majority of the nodes in the given cluster partition.
   </para>
   <para>
     By default, priority fencing delay is disabled.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see <literal>priority-fencing-delay</literal> in the
    <ulink url="https://www.clusterlabs.org/pacemaker/doc/2.1/Pacemaker_Explained/html/options.html#cluster-options">Pacemaker documentation</ulink>.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325957" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325957" -->
   <title>Unattended Mode for SAP HANA-SR Wizard on Bare-Metal</title>
   <para>
    Setting up a reproducable SAP HANA-SR infrastructure on several machines
    can be lot of administrative work. The SAP HANA-SR wizard is a manual
    tool that reduces the workload. However, it still requires some manual
    steps by admins to set it up.
   </para>
   <para>
    With this version of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications,
    we are introducing a new unattended mode for the SAP HANA-SR wizard.
    Administrators now only have to define a configuration inside the wizard
    once and can then re-apply the saved configuration file without user
    interaction.
   </para>
   <para>
    To deploy a preconfigured HANA-SR environments, we offer an unattended
    installation mode for the HANA-SR wizard on bare-metal servers. To use
    it, first create a configuration file by running the YaST
    <literal>sap_ha</literal> module manually and saving the configuration
    on its last screen. This configuration can then be used for automatic
    deployments using the following CLI commands:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Upload and validate the configuration automatically: <literal>yast2
      sap_ha readconfig &lt;CONFIGURATION_FILE_PATH&gt;</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Import, validate, and install the cluster unattendedly, based on the
      provided configuration file: <literal>yast2 sap_ha readconfig
      &lt;CONFIGURATION_FILE_PATH&gt; unattended</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-324542" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/324542" -->
   <title>SAP HANA System Replication Wizard Now Available for Azure Deployments</title>
   <para>
    Setting up a reproducible SAP HANA System Replication infrastructure on
    several machines can be a lot of administrative work. The SAP HANA-SR
    wizard is a manual tool that reduces the workload. However, it still
    requires some manual steps by administrators to set it up.
   </para>
   <para>
    With this version of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications,
    we are extending the SAP HANA-SR wizard capabilities for the Azure
    Cloud. Administrators can now use the SAP HANA-SR Wizard to configure
    the SAP HANA cluster on Azure and only have to define a configuration
    inside the wizard once and can then re-apply the saved configuration
    without user interaction.
   </para>
   <para>
    To deploy a preconfigured SAP HANA-SR environments, we offer an
    unattended installation mode for the SAP HANA-SR wizard. To use it,
    first create a configuration file by running the YaST module
    <literal>sap_ha</literal> manually and saving the configuration on its
    last screen. This configuration can then be used for automatic
    deployments using the following commands:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Upload and validate the configuration automatically: <literal>yast2
      sap_ha readconfig &lt;CONFIGURATION_FILE_PATH&gt;</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Import, validate, and install the cluster unattendedly, based on the
      provided configuration file: <literal>yast2 sap_ha readconfig
      &lt;CONFIGURATION_FILE_PATH&gt; unattended</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    For information on Near Zero Downtime for SAP HANA System Replication,
    see also
    <ulink url="https://help.sap.com/viewer/2c1988d620e04368aa4103bf26f17727/2.0.03/en-US/ee3fd9a0c2e74733a74e4ad140fde60b.html">Use
    SAP HANA System Replication for Near Zero Downtime Upgrades</ulink>.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-323465" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/323465" -->
   <title>SAP NetWeaver Integration</title>
   <para>
    The SAP NetWeaver integration has been improved to match the growing
    usability of cluster solutions especially during SAP maintenance
    procedures. This includes the visibility of the cluster solution in the
    SAP Management Console (SAP MC) and support for SAP kernel updates.
   </para>
   <para>
    <literal>sap_suse_cluster_connector</literal> has been updated to API
    version 3 to support the newest features and calls from
    <literal>sapstartsrv</literal>. This includes transparent support for
    SAP rolling kernel switches (RKS) for central services instances and
    replication instances.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-320368" remap="Intro:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320368" -->
   <title>yast2-hana-update Provides an Easier Way to Upgrade SAP HANA Cluster</title>
   <para>
    An important and regularly occurring maintenance task for SAP HANA
    clusters is upgrading the SAP HANA database. If installing the initial
    cluster is already critical, upgrading is even more so, as you now need
    to care about data integrity and system availability.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <literal>yast2-hana-update</literal> module provides a YaST workflow
    that will guide you step-by-step on the process of upgrading your SAP
    HANA in a SUSE cluster setup. The entire process is based on the
    so-called Near Zero Downtime Upgrade process described in the official
    SAP HANA documentation. The wizard handles the part of the procedure
    related to the SUSE cluster, leaving only some steps related to be
    performed manually by the SAP HANA administrator.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-325647" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/325647" -->
   <title>Support for SAP HANA Workloads on Intel Optane DC Memory</title>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 and SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for
    SAP Applications 12 SP4 add support for Intel Optane DC memory. This
    enables SAP workloads, such as SAP HANA to benefit from persistent
    memory in the future to shorten start times of the system and provide
    better overall system stability. Currently, configurations up to 12 TB
    of NVDIMMs plus 3 TB of regular DIMMS of supported memory and 4 socket
    machines have been tested. Additional configurations will be tested over
    time.
   </para>
   <para>
    From a file system perspective, the XFS file system is supported for the
    NVDIMMs, with SAP HANA running in DAX mode. SUSE intends to keep the
    leading position as technology provider, working closely with SAP on
    future developments.
   </para>
   <para>
    If there are <literal>pmem</literal> namespaces, these need to be
    destroyed before the installation. To mount persistent memory directly
    on boot, we recommend adding the <literal>nofail</literal> mount option
    in <literal>/etc/fstab</literal> as it can take a long time for the
    <literal>/dev/pmem</literal> devices to become usable.
   </para>
   <para>
    For example:
   </para>
<screen>/dev/pmem0    /mnt/pmem0    xfs    dax,nofail    0  0
/dev/pmem1    /mnt/pmem1    xfs    dax,nofail    0  0</screen>
   <para>
    Namespaces need to be created individually. That means, you need to
    execute the following command for each namespace you want to create:
   </para>
<screen>ndctl create-namespace --mode=fsdax --map=dev</screen>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
 </section>
 <section id="Sourcecode">
  <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
<!-- msvec and legal (ciaran), 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location as the first chapter -->
  <para>
   This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
   General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the source
   code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material. The source code is
   available for download at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. Also,
   for up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
   request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Requests should be
   sent by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/> or as
   otherwise instructed at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. SUSE
   may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section id="Feedback">
  <title>More Information and Feedback</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Read the READMEs on the media.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get detailed changelog information about a particular package from the
     RPM:
    </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp <replaceable>FILE_NAME</replaceable>.rpm</screen>
    <para>
     <replaceable>FILE_NAME</replaceable> is the name of the RPM.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
     first medium for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated
     packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of
     first medium of the SLES for SAP Applications media.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/sles_for_sap/"/> contains
     additional or updated documentation for SLES for SAP Applications.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For the latest product news from SUSE, visit
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?>
   SUSE LLC.
  </para>
  <para>
   Thank you for using SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications in
   your business.
  </para>
  <para>
   The SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications Team.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
