<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en" id="rnotes">
 <title>Release Notes</title>
 <articleinfo>
<?dbsuse-bugtracker url="https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi"
   product="SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 SP2"
   component="Release Notes"
   assignee="sknorr@suse.com" ?>
  <releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo><productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop</productname>
  <productnumber>12 SP2</productnumber><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    These release notes are generic for all SUSE Linux Enterprise
    Desktop 12 SP2 based products. Some parts may not apply to particular
    architectures or products. Where this is not the case, the respective
    architecture is listed explicitly. General documentation may be found
    at: <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/sled-12/"/>
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
 <section id="Intro">
  <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop</title>
  <remark> SLE definition: general information </remark>
  <para>
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop is the market's only enterprise-quality
   Linux desktop ready for routine business use. Developed and backed by
   SUSE, SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop provides market-leading usability,
   seamless interoperability with existing IT systems, and dozens of
   essential applications—all at a fraction of the price of proprietary
   operating systems.
  </para>
  <section id="Intro.Interoperability">
   <title>Interoperability and Hardware Support</title>
<!-- Novell Teaming is now Micro Focus Vibe. Not sure we still integrate
  with it. - sknorr, 2016-10-21 -->
   <para>
    It comes bundled with the latest versions of leading applications such
    as LibreOffice office productivity suite, Mozilla Firefox web browser,
    and Evolution e-mail and calendar suite. In addition, it integrates with
    Microsoft SharePoint
<!--and
   Novell Teaming -->
    for group collaboration and supports a wide range of multimedia file
    formats, wireless and networking standards, and plug-and-play devices.
   </para>
   <para>
    Through the latest enhancements in power management and security, SUSE
    Linux Enterprise Desktop also provides an environmentally friendly IT
    experience (Green IT) and an error-proof desktop. Finally, SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Desktop offers unparalleled flexibility. You can deploy it on
    a wide range of thick client devices (including desktops, notebooks,
    netbooks, and workstations), on thin client devices, or as a virtual
    desktop. By leveraging the power of SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop, your
    business can dramatically reduce costs, improve end user security and
    increase workforce productivity.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Lifecycle">
   <title>Support and Life Cycle</title>
<!-- bsc#882262, bsc#999197 -->
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 has a 7 year life cycle. The current
    version (SP2) will be fully maintained and supported until 6 months
    after the release of SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 SP3.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="intro.new">
   <title>What Is New?</title>
   <remark> Marketing POV. </remark>
   <remark> ** Update information : link to severity ratings documentation ** Installation : change,
    new kernel, compatibility ** features : features description (not technical) ** System update :
    link to the documentation (not just the tittle) ** Update related notes : specific change to
    focus on </remark>
   <para>
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 introduces a number of innovative
    changes. Here are some of the highlights:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Robustness on administrative errors and improved management
      capabilities with full system rollback based on Btrfs as the default
      file system for the operating system partition and snapper technology
      from SUSE.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      An overhaul of the installer introduces a new workflow that allows you
      to register your system and receive all available maintenance updates
      as part of the installation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      New core technologies like systemd, replacing the time honored System
      V based init process.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GNOME 3.20 gives users a modern desktop environment with a choice of
      several different look and feel options, including a special SUSE
      Linux Enterprise Classic mode for easier migration from earlier SUSE
      Linux Enterprise Desktop environments.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For users wishing to use the full range of productivity applications
      of a Desktop with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, we are now offering
      the SUSE Linux Enterprise Workstation Extension
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Integration with the new SUSE Customer Center, the central web portal
      from SUSE to manage subscriptions, entitlements, and provide access to
      support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!-- Commented for the moment: only intro.support has content and thus this
   section looks a bit pathetic. - sknorr, 2016-08-04 -->
<!-- <remark> This is Read Me First information. </remark> -->
<!-- <para> For users upgrading from a previous &sled; release it is recommended to review: </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="Intro.Support"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="InstUpgrade.Upgrade"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="TechInfo"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>-->
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Documentation">
   <title>Documentation and Other Information</title>
   <para/>
   <section>
    <title>Available on the Product Media</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Read the READMEs on the media.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Get the detailed changelog information about a particular package
       from the RPM (<replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable> is the name of the
       RPM):
      </para>
<screen>rpm --changelog -qp <replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable>.rpm</screen>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
       media for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated
       packages.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory of
       the media of SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 SP2. This directory
       includes PDF versions of the SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 SP2
       Installation Quick Start and Deployment Guides. Documentation (if
       installed) is available below the
       <filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> directory of an installed
       system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The up-to-date version of these release notes is available online
       from <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Release notes usually only list changes that happened between two
       subsequent releases. Therefore, if you are skipping one or more
       service packs, check the release notes of the skipped service packs
       as well.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Additional or Updated Documentation</title>
    <para>
     For SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 documentation, see
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/sled-12/"/>, where you
     can download PDF documents. For installation with YaST software
     management or with zypper, packages are available on the product media.
     Some of these packages are installed by default. These are the package
     names:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <systemitem>sled-installquick_en-pdf</systemitem>: SLED 12 SP2
       Installation Quick Start
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <systemitem>sled-gnomeuser_en-pdf</systemitem>: SLED 12 SP2 GNOME
       User Guide
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <systemitem>sled-admin_en-pdf</systemitem>: SLED 12 SP2
       Administration Guide
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <systemitem>sled-deployment_en-pdf</systemitem>: SLED 12 SP2
       Deployment Guide
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <systemitem>sled-security_en-pdf</systemitem>: SLED 12 SP2 Security
       Guide
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <systemitem>sled-tuning_en-pdf</systemitem>: SLED 12 SP2 Tuning
       Guide
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <systemitem>sled-manuals_en</systemitem>: the set of all SLED books
       in HTML format
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Sourcecode">
   <title>How to Obtain Source Code</title>
<!-- msvec and legal (ciaran), 2013-05-13 -->
<!-- moved from the abstract to this location as the first section -->
   <para>
    This SUSE product includes materials licensed to SUSE under the GNU
    General Public License (GPL). The GPL requires SUSE to provide the
    source code that corresponds to the GPL-licensed material. The source
    code is available for download at
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>.
    Also, for up to three years after distribution of the SUSE product, upon
    request, SUSE will mail a copy of the source code. Requests should be
    sent by e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:sle_source_request@suse.com"/> or
    as otherwise instructed at
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/download-linux/source-code.html"/>. SUSE
    may charge a reasonable fee to recover distribution costs.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Support">
   <title>Support Statement for SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop</title>
   <para>
    To learn how to obtain support, see
    <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/desktop/"/>.
   </para>
   <section id="Intro.Support.Techpreviews" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews">
    <title>Technology Previews</title>
    <para>
     Technology Preview features are either not supported or supported in a
     limited fashion. These features are mainly included for customer
     convenience and may be functionally incomplete, unstable or in other
     ways not suitable for production use.
    </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-320388" remap="Intro:Support:Techpreviews">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320388" -->
     <title>Support for Current AMD Radeon GPUs</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis> As a technical preview, SUSE Linux Enterprise ships the
      graphics driver
      </emphasis><literal>xf86-video-amdgpu</literal><emphasis> for current
      AMD Radeon GPUs. </emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Since this driver is still in an experimental state, it is
      not installed by default. By default, it is only enabled for one GPU
      on which it was tested successfully.</emphasis>
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Important:</emphasis> At this stage, this driver
      is not supported.
     </para>
     <para>
      To be able to use the driver, first install the package
      <literal>xf86-video-amd</literal>. Then, enable it for your GPU by
      editing <literal>/etc/X11/xorg_pci_ids</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The required format is:
      <literal>\&lt;VendorID\&gt;\&lt;DeviceID\&gt;</literal>. It is also
      described in the configuration file itself.
     </para>
     <para>
      To find vendor ID and device ID, use the command:
     </para>
<screen>lspci -n | grep 0300</screen>
     <para>
      All supported vendor IDs/device IDs are already in the file but are
      commented out. For your vendor ID/device ID combination, remove the
      comment character <literal>#</literal> from the beginning of the line.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Intro.Derived_Products">
   <title>Related Products</title>
   <para>
    This sections lists related products. In many cases, these products have
    own release notes documents that are available from
    <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Enterprise Storage:
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-enterprise-storage"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Server:
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/server"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications:
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Manager:
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-manager"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE OpenStack Cloud:
      <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-openstack-cloud"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Additionally, there are the following extensions which are not covered
    by SUSE support agreements, available at no additional cost and without
    an extra registration key:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Package Hub: <ulink url="https://packagehub.suse.com/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SUSE Linux Enterprise Software Development Kit
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="InstUpgrade" remap="InstUpgrade">
  <title>Installation and Upgrade</title>
  <para>
   This section includes information related to the initial installation of
   SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 SP2. For information about installing,
   see <citetitle>Deployment Guide</citetitle> at
   <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sled-12/book_sle_deployment/data/book_sle_deployment.html"/>.
  </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
  <section role="notoc" id="fate-319716" remap="InstUpgrade">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319716" -->
   <title>Updating the Installer at the Beginning of the Installation or Upgrade</title>
   <para>
    <emphasis>Until SLES 12 SP1, the only method of updating the installer
    was through the use of a driver update disk. This required manual work
    such as downloading the driver update and explicitly pointing the
    installer at it.</emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    Starting with the SLES 12 SP2 installer, at the beginning of the
    installation or upgrade, the installer can contact the update server to
    find out whether updates for the installer are available. If there are,
    they are automatically applied and YaST is restarted. The installer is
    able to download the updates from the regular update server, a local SMT
    server, or a custom URL.
   </para>
   <para>
    By default, this functionality is off. Enable this feature using the
    boot option <literal>self_update=1</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see the documentation at
    <ulink url="https://github.com/yast/yast-installation/blob/SLE-12-SP2/doc/SELF_UPDATE.md">https://github.com/yast/yast-installation/blob/SLE-12-SP2/doc/SELF_UPDATE.md</ulink>.
   </para>
  </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  <section id="InstUpgrade.Installation" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
   <title>Installation</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-322147" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322147" -->
    <title>Installer Crashes When Set to Mount by Label by Default</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> When setting the default mount value to </emphasis>By
     Label<emphasis> during partitioning, the installer will report an error
     and crash. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     As a workaround, use another option for installation. If needed, switch
     back to <emphasis>By Label</emphasis> on the running system.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320494" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320494" -->
    <title>Media-based Sources Are Disabled After Installation If They Are Not Needed</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Previously, when installing from local media, like a CD/DVD
     or USB drive, these sources remained enabled after the
     installation.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>This could cause problems during software installation,
     upgrade or migration because an old or obsolete installation source
     remained there. Additionally, if the source was physically removed (for
     instance, by ejecting the CD/DVD), Zypper would complain about the
     source not being available.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     After the installation, YaST will now check every local source to
     determine if the product they provide is also available through a
     remote repository. In that case, the local source will be disabled.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320111" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320111" -->
    <title>Partitioning Proposal: "Flexible Partitioning" Feature Has Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>YaST is a highly configurable installer that allows setting
     very different behaviors for each product using it (SUSE Enterprise
     Linux, openSUSE, etc.). In previous versions of YaST, it was possible
     to use a feature called "Flexible Partitioning". This feature has
     become obsolete, as the more standard proposal mechanism has been used
     by SLE and openSUSE in all recent releases.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The new version of YaST detects when a (modified) installer tries to
     use the obsolete "Flexible Partitioning" feature, alerts the user and
     falls back to the standard proposal mechanism automatically.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317970" remap="InstUpgrade:Installation">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317970" -->
    <title>Option to Create AutoYaST Profile During Installation Has Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>In earlier versions of SUSE Linux Enterprise, you could clone
     the system configuration as an AutoYaST profile during installation.
     However, many services and system parameters can only be configured
     after the installation process has completed and the system is up and
     running. This can result in an AutoYaST profile missing parts of the
     desired configuration.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The option of creating an AutoYaST profile during installation has been
     removed. However, you can still create an AutoYaST profile from the
     running system, after you have made sure that the system configuration
     fits your needs.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent">
  <title>Architecture Independent Information</title>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Kernel" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
   <title>Kernel</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320305" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Kernel">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320305" -->
    <title>Incompatible Changes in the New 4.4 Kernel</title>
    <para>
     The following minor changes have been identified in the 4.4 kernel:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Support for TCP Limited Slow Start (RFC3742) has been removed. This
       feature had multiple drawbacks and questionable benefit. Its
       implementation was inefficient and difficult to configure. The
       problem that Limited Slow Start was trying to solve is now better
       covered by the Hybrid Slow Start algorithm which is part of default
       congestion control algorithm, CUBIC.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>kernel.blk_iopoll</literal> sysctl has been removed.
       This setting allowed toggling some block device drivers between
       iopoll and non-iopoll mode. This allowed for easier debugging of
       these drivers during early development. Since using this toggle was
       dangerous and the toggle is not needed for production setups, it has
       been removed.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>cgroup.event_control</literal> file is only available in
       cgroups with a memcg attached to it. There was no code using this
       interface outside of memcg, so this change is considered harmless.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>vm.scan_unevictable_pages</literal> sysctl has been
       removed because the functionality it was backing had been removed in
       2011. Any usage of the file has been reported to the kernel log with
       an explanation that the file has no effect. There were no reports
       about a use case requiring this functionality.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The
       <literal>/sys/devices/system/memory/memory%d/end_phys_index</literal>
       file has been removed, because the information it exposed is
       considered internal to the kernel and an implementation detail. This
       information is not required for the memory hotplug functionality.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.SystemsManagement" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
   <title>Systems Management</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-321157" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321157" -->
    <title>SASL Integration in sudo</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> When SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 was first released, the
     </emphasis><literal>sudo</literal><emphasis> binary did not correctly
     support SASL authentication for LDAP because the package was built
     without a build dependency on the package
     </emphasis><literal>cyrus-sasl-devel</literal><emphasis>. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     To be able to use <literal>sudo</literal> with SASL, update to the
     latest version of the package <literal>sudo</literal>. For information
     about enabling SASL authentication for <literal>sudo</literal>, see
     <literal>man 5 sudoers.ldap</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320973" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320973" -->
    <title>systemd: Support for System V and LSB Init Scripts Has Been Moved Out of Core Daemon</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> To ease future maintenance, in SLE 12 SP2, systemd was
     updated to version 228. This version does not support using System V
     and LSB init scripts from the
     </emphasis><literal>systemd</literal><emphasis> daemon itself any more.
     </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     This functionality is now implemented as a generator that creates
     systemd unit files from System V/LSB init scripts. These unit files are
     generated at boot or when systemd is reloaded. Therefore, to have
     changed System V init scripts recognized by systemd, run
     <literal>systemctl daemon-reload</literal> or reboot the machine.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information, see the man page of
     <literal>systemd-sysv-generator</literal> (<literal>man
     systemd-sysv-generator</literal>).
    </para>
    <para>
     If you are packaging software that ships System V init scripts, use the
     RPM macros documented at
     <ulink url="https://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Systemd_packaging_guidelines#Register_services_in_install_scripts">https://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Systemd_packaging_guidelines</ulink>
     (Section "Register Services in Install Scripts").
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320958" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320958" -->
    <title>AutoYaST: Applying the First-Stage Network Configuration to the Installed System</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> Due to a problem in the AutoYaST version shipped with SLE 12
     SP1, the network configuration used during the first stage was always
     copied to the installed system. This happened regardless of the value
     of </emphasis><literal>keep_install_network</literal><emphasis> in the
     AutoYaST profile. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     SLE 12 SP2 behaves as expected and
     <literal>keep_install_network</literal> will be set to
     <literal>true</literal> by default.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320392" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:SystemsManagement">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320392" -->
    <title>ntp 4.2.8</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>ntp was updated to version 4.2.8.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis> The ntp server ntpd does not synchronize with its peers
       anymore and the peers are specified by their host name in
       </emphasis><literal>/etc/ntp.conf</literal><emphasis>. </emphasis>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis> The output of </emphasis><literal>ntpq
       --peers</literal><emphasis> lists IP numbers of the remote servers
       instead of their host names. </emphasis>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Name resolution for the affected hosts works
     otherwise.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Parameter changes</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The meaning of some parameters for the sntp command-line tool have
     changed or have been dropped, for example <literal>sntp -s</literal> is
     now <literal>sntp -S</literal>. Please review any
     <literal>sntp</literal> usage in your own scripts for required changes.
    </para>
    <para>
     After having been deprecated for several years, ntpdc is now disabled
     by default for security reasons. It can be re-enabled by adding the
     line <literal>enable mode7</literal> to
     <literal>/etc/ntp.conf</literal>, but preferably
     <literal>ntpq</literal> should be used instead.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Network" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
   <title>Networking</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-322007" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/322007" -->
    <title>Improved Bridge Handling in YaST</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>The configuration UI for bridges in YaST did not always show
     all information and did not always convert parameters properly when
     editing older configurations.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In SLE 12 SP2, this behavior has been improved upon:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The information about bridge ports and bridges is shown for each
       interface.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In the case of old configuration, upon reading the configuration, the
       bootproto <literal>static</literal> will be converted to
       <literal>none</literal> and the parameter <literal>zero
       IPADDR</literal> will be removed.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Additionally, to improve the user experience, the management of bridges
     and bonding has been unified and the interface is now updated after any
     change.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320709" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Network">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320709" -->
    <title>No Support for Samba as Active Directory-Style Domain Controller</title>
    <para>
     The version of Samba shipped with SLE 12 GA and newer does not include
     support to operate as an Active Directory-style domain controller. This
     functionality is currently disabled, as it lacks integration with
     system-wide MIT Kerberos.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Virtualization">
   <title>Virtualization</title>
   <para/>
   <section id="InfraPackArch.ArchIndependent.Virtualization.Other" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Other">
    <title>Others</title>
    <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318990" remap="InfraPackArch:ArchIndependent:Virtualization:Other">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="Interoperability,Virtualization"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318990" -->
     <title>Support for 3D Graphics in VMware Guest</title>
     <para>
      The <literal>vmwgfx</literal> driver supports 3D with VMware hardware
      version 11.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Packages">
  <title>Packages and Functionality Changes</title>
  <section id="Packages.New" remap="Packages:New">
   <title>New Packages</title>
   <remark> *** Description of the new package with direct link to the official website (need the
    URL tag) *** Version and release of the package *** Why this new package: enhancements request
    *** link to the official documentation *** link to the SUSE's documentation *** Dependencies and
    Build requires </remark>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320751" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320751" -->
    <title>Mutt Has Been Updated to 1.6.0</title>
    <para>
     Mutt has been updated to version 1.6.0. This version has the following
     new features:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Better internationalization support: UTF-8 mailbox support for IMAP
       and improved support for internationalized email and SMTPUTF8
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>$use_idn</literal> has been renamed to
       <literal>$idn_decode</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Expandos for comma-separated lists of To (<literal>%r</literal>)
       and CC recipients (<literal>%R</literal>).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Improved handling of drafts: <literal>-E</literal> command-line
       argument for edit draft or include files,
       <literal>$resume_draft_files</literal> and
       <literal>$resume_edited_draft_files</literal> to control processing
       of draft files, and support for multipart draft files
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>$reflow_space_quotes</literal> allows
       <literal>format=flowed</literal> email quotes to be displayed with
       spacing between them.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The S/MIME message digest algorithm is now specified using the option
       <literal>$smime_sign_digest_alg</literal>.
       <literal>$smime_sign_command</literal> should be modified to include
       <literal>-md %d</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For classic GPG mode, set <literal>$pgp_decryption_okay</literal> to
       verify that multipart/encrypted mails are actually encrypted.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       By default, mailto URL header parameters are restricted to
       <literal>body</literal> and <literal>subject</literal>. To add or
       remove allowed mailto URL header parameters, use
       <literal>mailto_allow</literal> and <literal>unmailto_allow</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>$hostname</literal> is set differently: the domain will now
       be determined using DNS calls
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320018" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320018" -->
    <title>Devilspie 2 Has Been Added</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Desktop users often want the size and position of windows to
     remain the same, even across application restarts. Such functionality
     usually has to be implemented at the application level but not all
     applications do so.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     In SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 SP2, Devilspie 2 (package
     <literal>devilspie2</literal>) has been added. Desvilspie 2 is a
     window matching utility that allow you to script actions on windows as
     they are created, such as maximizing windows or setting their size and
     position.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319461" remap="Packages:New">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats="LDAP Service,Security"; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319461" -->
    <title>openldap2-ppolicy-check-password Has Been Added: OpenLDAP Password Strength Policy Enforcer</title>
    <para>
     To allow evaluating and enforcing password strength in an OpenLDAP
     deployment, the package
     <literal>openldap2-ppolicy-check-password</literal> has been added. It
     is an OpenLDAP password policy plugin which evaluates and enforces
     strength in new user passwords, and denies weak passwords in password
     change operations. Configuration options of the plugin allow system
     administrators to adjust password strength requirements.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
  <section id="Packages.Update" remap="Packages:Update">
   <title>Updated Packages</title>
   <remark> *** Description of the new package with direct link to the official website *** version
    comparison table from previous SP/product *** Bugs fixed since previous SP/Product (link to
    Bugzilla) *** Enhancements request (link to Fate number) *** link to the official documentation
    *** link to the SUSE's documentation *** Security fixes (link to CVE or SUSE's security web
    site), link to PIF *** Changelog diff (all other information non relative to security/fate/bugs) </remark>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320541" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320541" -->
    <title>lsof Has Been Updated to Version 4.89</title>
    <para>
     lsof has been updated from version 4.84 to 4.89. The changelog can be
     found in the file <literal>/usr/share/doc/packages/lsof/DIST</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320330" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320330" -->
    <title>Qt 5 Has Been Updated to 5.6.1</title>
    <para>
     The Qt 5 libraries were updated to 5.6.1, a Qt 5.6 LTS based release.
     Qt 5.6.1 includes new features and security fixes for known
     vulnerabilities over Qt 5.5.1 (the version shipped in an upgrade to
     SP1).
    </para>
    <para>
     This release includes many bug fixes and changes that improve
     performance and reduce memory consumption.
    </para>
    <para>
     For security reasons, the MNG and JPEG2000 image format plugins are not
     shipped anymore, because the underlying MNG and JPEG2000 libraries have
     known security issues.
    </para>
    <para>
     New features include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Better support for high-DPI screens
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Update of QtWebEngine which updates the included Chromium snapshot to
       version 45 and now uses many of the system libraries instead of
       bundled ones
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       New Qt WebEngineCore module for new low-level APIs
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The Qt Location module is not fully supported.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Improved compatibility with C++11 and the STL
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       New QVersionNumber class
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Added support for HTTP redirection in QNetworkAccessManager
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Improved support for OpenGL ES 3
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Qt Multimedia got a new PlayList QML type and an audio role API for
       the media player
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Qt Canvas 3D now supports Qt Quick Items as textures and can directly
       render to the QML scenes foreground or background
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Qt 3D has received many improvements and new functionality
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Many other features and bugfixes
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     As part of this update, Qt Creator has been updated to 4.0.1 (from Qt
     Creator 3.5.1 shipped as an update to SP1).
    </para>
    <para>
     New features of Qt Creator include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Clang static analyzer integration, extended QML profiler features,
       path editor of Qt Quick Designer and auto test integration
       (experimental) are now available
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The Clang code model is now automatically used if the (experimental)
       plugin is turned on
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Improved workflow for CMake-based projects
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The Analyze mode was merged with Debug mode, so that the new unified
       Debug mode includes the Debugger, Clang Static Analyzer, Memcheck,
       Callgrind and QML Profiler tools
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Many other features and bugfixes
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320001" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320001" -->
    <title>More IBus Engines Available</title>
    <para>
     To improve Asian language support, there are now more IBus engines
     available:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ibus-rime</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ibus-skk</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ibus-kkc</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ibus-table</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ibus-chewing</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ibus-libzhuyin</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ibus-sunpinyin</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ibus-mozc</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       various <literal>ibus-table-*</literal> engines
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     As a result of this, some components, such as openCC, were updated to
     more recent versions. <literal>libopencc1</literal> package is no
     longer provided and has been replaced by <literal>libopencc2</literal>.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-319675" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319675" -->
    <title>OpenSSH Has Been Updated to Version 7.2</title>
    <para>
     OpenSSH received numerous changes and improvements in the last years.
     To ease further maintenance, OpenSSH was upgraded to a more current
     release.
    </para>
    <para>
     Note that the SSHv1 protocol is no longer supported.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-317043" remap="Packages:Update">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/317043" -->
    <title>openSSL Has Been Updated to Version 1.0.2</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>openSSL has been updated from version 1.0.1 to 1.0.2 which is
     a compatible minor version update. This will help future maintenance,
     and also brings many bug fixes.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     The update to openSSL 1.0.2 should be transparent to existing programs.
    </para>
    <para>
     However, there were some functional changes were done: SSL 2 support is
     now fully disabled and certain weak ciphers are no longer built in.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section id="Features.Kernel">
    <title>Kernel and Toolchain</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       GCC 4.8
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       glibc 2.22
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Linux kernel 4.4
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section id="Features.Desktop">
    <title>Desktop</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       GNOME 3.20
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       X.org 7.6
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section id="Features.Other">
    <title>Other Changes and Version Updates</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Samba 4.4.2
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       UEFI Enablement on AMD64/Intel 64
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SWAP over NFS
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Python 2.7.9 and Python 3.4.1
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Perl 5.18.2
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Ruby 2.1
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Packages.Deprecated" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
   <title>Deprecated Functionality</title>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-321164" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321164" -->
    <title>SLED Installation Media Without SLED Images</title>
    <para>
     SLED images are no longer shipped on the SLED installation media.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320900" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320900" -->
    <title>librpcsecgss3 Has Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     <literal>librpcsecgss</literal> (packages:
     <literal>librpcsecgss3</literal>,
     <literal>librpcsecgss-devel</literal>) has been removed. With the
     release of <literal>libtirpc</literal>, the development of libsecgss
     stopped and it fell out of use. We recommend using
     <literal>libtirpc</literal> instead.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-320654" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/320654" -->
    <title>python-tornado Has Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     The package <literal>python-tornado</literal> is no longer provided, as
     it was not required by any packages on SLED 12 SP2.
    </para>
   </section>
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-316813" remap="Packages:Deprecated">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/316813" -->
    <title>Flash Player Has Been Removed</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Starting with SLE 12 SP2, the Adobe Flash Player plugin for
     the Firefox browser is no longer provided by SUSE.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     Adobe provides a third-party RPM repository which can be used to
     install Flash Player. To install Flash Player from this repository, do
     the following:
    </para>
    <para>
     To add this repository to your system, in a terminal, run:
    </para>
<screen>sudo zypper ar --check --refresh http://linuxdownload.adobe.com/linux/x86_64/ adobe</screen>
    <para>
     To see the packages provided by this repo, use:
    </para>
<screen>sudo zypper se -s -r adobe</screen>
    <para>
     There are two packages: the Flash Player plugin itself and a package
     named <literal>adobe-release-x86_64</literal>. First install this
     additional package and add the repository key that it contains:
    </para>
<screen>sudo zypper in adobe-release-x86_64
sudo rpm --import /etc/pki/rpm-gpg/RPM-GPG-KEY-adobe-linux</screen>
    <para>
     Then, to install the Adobe Flash Player RPM package, run:
    </para>
<screen>zypper in flash-plugin</screen>
    <para>
     To make Mozilla Firefox detect the Flash plugin, restart Mozilla
     Firefox.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   <section id="Packages.Deprecated.Future" remap="Packages:Deprecated:Future">
    <title>Packages and Features to Be Removed in the Future</title>
    <para>
     The following packages are deprecated and will be removed with SUSE
     Linux Enterprise Desktop 13.
    </para>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-319095" remap="Packages:Deprecated:Future">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/319095" -->
     <title>fcitx Is Deprecated and Will Be Replaced with the IBus Input Method</title>
     <para>
      With SLE 12 SP1, the fcitx input method is deprecated. Starting with
      SLE 12 SP2, it will no longer be supported nor shipped. You can switch
      to the IBus input method.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section role="notoc" id="fate-318930" remap="Packages:Deprecated:Future">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/318930" -->
     <title>Xemacs Has Been Removed</title>
     <para>
      Xemacs has been removed in favor of GNU Emacs. Starting with SLE 12
      SP2, it will no longer be provided or supported. We suggest switching
      to GNU Emacs which is fully supported.
     </para>
    </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Packages.Packaging" remap="Packages:Packaging">
   <title>Changes in Packaging and Delivery</title>
   <para/>
<!--v Items below imported from FATE-->
   <section role="notoc" id="fate-321179" remap="Packages:Packaging">
<!-- sort_key="None"; non-rn-fate-cats=""; -->
<!-- href="https://fate.novell.com/321179" -->
    <title>GNOME Desktop: Clicking "Open in Terminal" on the Desktop Now Opens the Home Directory</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis> When right-clicking the GNOME desktop and selecting
     </emphasis>Open in Terminal<emphasis>, GNOME Terminal will now open
     with the working directory set to the home directory (</emphasis><literal>~</literal><emphasis>) and not set to the Desktop
     directory (</emphasis>~/Desktop<emphasis>). This happens because the
     package
     </emphasis><literal>nautilus-extension-terminal</literal><emphasis> is
     now installed by default. </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     To switch to the former behavior, first uninstall
     <literal>nautilus-extension-terminal</literal> and then install
     <literal>nautilus-open-terminal</literal>. However, note that the
     package <literal>nautilus-open-terminal</literal> may not be provided
     in future service packs.
    </para>
   </section>
<!--^ End of Items imported from FATE-->
  </section>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Legal Notices</title>
  <para>
   SUSE makes no representations or warranties with respect to the contents
   or use of this documentation, and specifically disclaims any express or
   implied warranties of merchantability or fitness for any particular
   purpose. Further, SUSE reserves the right to revise this publication and
   to make changes to its content, at any time, without the obligation to
   notify any person or entity of such revisions or changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Further, SUSE makes no representations or warranties with respect to any
   software, and specifically disclaims any express or implied warranties of
   merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose. Further, SUSE
   reserves the right to make changes to any and all parts of SUSE software,
   at any time, without any obligation to notify any person or entity of
   such changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Any products or technical information provided under this Agreement may
   be subject to U.S. export controls and the trade laws of other countries.
   You agree to comply with all export control regulations and to obtain any
   required licenses or classifications to export, re-export, or import
   deliverables. You agree not to export or re-export to entities on the
   current U.S. export exclusion lists or to any embargoed or terrorist
   countries as specified in U.S. export laws. You agree to not use
   deliverables for prohibited nuclear, missile, or chemical/biological
   weaponry end uses. Refer to
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> for more information on
   exporting SUSE software. SUSE assumes no responsibility for your failure
   to obtain any necessary export approvals.
  </para>
  <para>
   Copyright © 2010-
<?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?>
   SUSE LLC. This release notes document is licensed under a Creative
   Commons Attribution-NoDerivs 3.0 United States License (CC-BY-ND-3.0 US,
   <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/us/"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   SUSE has intellectual property rights relating to technology embodied in
   the product that is described in this document. In particular, and
   without limitation, these intellectual property rights may include one or
   more of the U.S. patents listed at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/> and one or more
   additional patents or pending patent applications in the U.S. and other
   countries.
  </para>
  <para>
   For SUSE trademarks, see SUSE Trademark and Service Mark list
   (<ulink url="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/>). All third-party
   trademarks are the property of their respective owners.
  </para>
 </section>
</article>
